<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>xahteiwi.eu - Philosophy</title><link href="https://fghaas.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://fghaas.github.io/feeds/tag/philosophy.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://fghaas.github.io/</id><updated>2019-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Team meetings</title><link href="https://fghaas.github.io/blog/2019/06/06/team-meetings/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>florian</name></author><id>tag:fghaas.github.io,2019-06-06:/blog/2019/06/06/team-meetings/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Distributed teams need to meet in person every once in a while. Here are some thoughts and suggestions on team meetings.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve run a distributed team — nominally the same team, though through
people joining and leaving I am the sole original band member at this
point — for almost 8 years. And about 3 years in was the first time we
were sufficiently spread &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; had enough money to spare to warrant
flying everyone to the same place for one week per year. We have been
doing that ever since. Every year, it’s an exceedingly enlightening
and pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this year was the first time that we did not one but &lt;strong&gt;two&lt;/strong&gt; team
meetings back to back: first with my core team running education
services at City Network, in the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellerup"&gt;Hellerup&lt;/a&gt; neighborhood in
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copenhagen"&gt;Copenhagen&lt;/a&gt;, and then as
part of the complete City Network all-hands meeting on the island of
Tjärö in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blekinge_archipelago"&gt;Blekinge
archipelago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is how we do these things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accommodation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except for the very first team meeting we did in 2014 when we put
everyone up in hotel rooms, we’ve always rented a house. I’m a
believer in small team sizes — 5 people being the maximum number of
direct reports a leader can realistically have —, so that means that
we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; still find houses where everyone has a room to themselves,
and nobody has to queue for a shower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider both of these things extremely important. Many, many people
working in tech are introverts, even more so for people working &lt;em&gt;from
home&lt;/em&gt; in tech. Many of us find the experience of constantly being
around people emotionally draining, and we need solitude to
recharge. Also, privacy. Our personal lives don’t stop while we’re
having a team meeting, so you might want to have a room in which you
can talk about your kid’s health issue with your spouse, without
concern about colleagues overhearing the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Price-wise, since this puts us in an accommodation category that can
qualify as a penthouse or mansion, this won’t be significantly cheaper
than hotel accommodation — but it won’t be &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; expensive either,
and it’ll be a much nicer experience. Particularly if you also have
the joy of interacting with an exceedingly pleasant, nice, and helpful
person for a host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; scouts the accommodation, my rule has always been this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case we have a person on the team who lives, or has lived, in the
  city we’re going to, and who thus is very familiar with the locality
  and surroundings, I delegate the search to them. You can never beat
  local personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, I do the scouting on the web, and I usually run it by the
  team — after I have made the booking, but while we can still cancel
  or change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Arrival&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever did the scouting for the accommodation travels a day
early, gets the key, settles in, and reports back. This has multiple
purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they are local and so is the host, &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; that’ll facilitate
  matters a lot. Particularly if we’re in a country where that one
  team member speaks the language, and the rest of us don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there’s something seriously wrong with the property, they can
  still cry foul and we can make other arrangements while we’re not
  all congregated in the same spot. (This has never happened to us,
  but just in case.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That person is our support backstop who can field issues and
  customer questions, while everyone else is in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That person can also meet and collect people at the airport or train
  station, if getting to our accommodation is nontrivial or
  difficult. Also, this is particularly helpful when we have a new
  team member who is perhaps less travel experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I normally don’t schedule any formal work sessions for the first
day. People will be jet-lagged and fatigued from travel, we are often
re-meeting in person for the first time in a year, and there is a lot
of catching up to do about family, hobbies, recent travel, and all
sorts of things that are not work. Somebody might be new and we might
see them for the first time ever, in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then of course people might be delayed in travel, may have had
flights cancelled, or may have missed connections. So that means if
you’re actually &lt;em&gt;planning&lt;/em&gt; the first day to be full of “work”
sessions, you ran a significant chance of your schedule getting
wrecked by a flight delay. So we just don’t do that. Instead, we try
to make the first day as relaxed and as enjoyable as possible,
including a nice first group dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then sometimes, as happened this year, a &lt;em&gt;remarkably&lt;/em&gt; serious and
productive discussion over work issues ensues over a glass of wine in
the evening. But that’s not part of the expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tend to have half-day work sessions these days, where we focus on
one topic for 3-4 hours straight. These can get intense, and sometimes
heated, but they are nearly always very, very productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We typically use a place like our house’s kitchen (if it’s roomy, and
has a table), or patio (if it’s bearable outside), or sitting room (if
it’s cozy) for work sessions. They are usually quite analog, with
frequently just one person — the assigned record-keeper, often me —
with a laptop open to take notes and record the discussion and its
outcomes. I’ve found that on occasion, when discussing complex issues,
working with a roll of brown paper and thick felt-tip markers
(“sharpies” for you Americans out there) can be &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more useful
than with anything pushing bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoy food, and I’ve never worked with anyone who doesn’t. So we
make that part enjoyable in whatever way we fancy. We might go for
lunch to the neighborhood bagel store that our host recommended for
their excellent pastrami. We might jump on a train to get to a street
food spot, or head out for pizza or tacos or curry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’m buying. These meetings are for work, my team is traveling for
just that purpose, so whenever we eat together (and we practically
always do), the tab is on me. What I can put on the company and what
comes out of my own pocket is my job to sort out later, but we’re
definitely not going Dutch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interesting things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our meetings are usually in an interesting city with art,
architecture, and history, and not seeing any of that would be a bit
of a waste. So there’s usually maybe two to three things that we just
go and do. It could be a harbor or river cruise, a visit to a castle
or palace, a bicycle tour criss-crossing the city, or a museum
visit. Depends a bit on the weather and a bit on individual interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Epilogue: going larger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what works for a 5-person team clearly doesn’t work for a whole
company, not least because you’ll be hard pressed to find a rental
home with 40 bedrooms — I guess such a dwelling would be appropriately
referred to as a palace, and last I checked the Queen wasn’t on
Airbnb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can take a page out of City Network’s playbook and do
something else, which is to book an island. Yes, you read that right,
immediately after our &lt;em&gt;team&lt;/em&gt; meeting we packed up and boarded a train
to join our &lt;em&gt;company&lt;/em&gt; all-hands meeting, in which we had an island
practically to ourselves. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>Working from home, with little kids in the house</title><link href="https://fghaas.github.io/blog/2018/02/18/working-from-home-with-little-kids/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>florian</name></author><id>tag:fghaas.github.io,2018-02-18:/blog/2018/02/18/working-from-home-with-little-kids/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I very much prefer working from home to working from an office. But with little kids in the house, that’s a nontrivial endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked exclusively from home&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for the last 6½ years, and
when I first started, my older kids were 7 and 6 years old. For the
last 3 years after the arrival of our two younger children, though,
I’ve worked from home &lt;strong&gt;with infants/toddlers in the house,&lt;/strong&gt; and
that’s a wholly different ball game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The basic rules of working from home&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve dealt with the idea of working from home, or have
done it before, then you’re surely familiar with a few basic rules to
follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure that you have a &lt;em&gt;home office,&lt;/em&gt; that is a working space to
  yourself that allows you to close a door and be undisturbed when you
  need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set aside some time to go outside. Office workers have a commute
  that ensures they get out of the house; as a home worker you’re
  running a certain risk of turning into a hermit. Make sure you run
  errands, take walks, go for runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep tabs on your working hours. Home workers are frequently at risk
  of working too much or too long, which puts a strain on yourself,
  your significant other, and your family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintain relationships with others who work from home. Chat with
  them, call them, invite them over for dinner if they live close
  by. Working from home is still not a common thing to do in general
  (however common it might be in the tech industry), so exchanging
  thoughts with people in the same boat is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be ready to try out working-from-home strategies that have worked
  for others. Fortunately for all of us, there are quite a few people
  who talk about the experience publicly — for example,
  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/johndalton"&gt;John Dalton&lt;/a&gt; did so in a
  &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/qFWkDPTjjEM"&gt;45-minute talk&lt;/a&gt; at linux.conf.au
  2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Now, the challenging part: &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; kids&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone reading this wants to pre-emptively freak out and berate me
for being an irresponsible or unloving parent, you are politely asked
to chill and if incapable of doing so, to GTFO. I absolutely love
being around my children, and I wouldn’t even &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; to trade my job
for an office-dwelling one. Being able to work from home is generally
a wonderful privilege, and so is being around my kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to be aware of two things: one, working from home with a
family is different from working from home when you’re alone or living
with an adult partner or roomie. Two, working from home with a family
with little children is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different from a family with school-age
kids. School-age children don’t permanently need an adult in the room,
they spend a significant amount of their time outside the house,
they’re usually not particularly prone to tantrums, and in the event
that you really, really need some quiet, they can be asked to give you
that for a limited amount of time. Kids under two?  Good luck with
that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not striking a balance here, here’s what’s likely to
happen: you’ll think that you are a completely inadequate parent, or a
terrible employee, or both. So, never lose sight of the fact that
you’re probably a wonderful parent and a highly productive employee —
but that you can do &lt;em&gt;anything,&lt;/em&gt; but not &lt;em&gt;everything.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My most important piece of advice here is that you &lt;strong&gt;should not attempt
to &lt;em&gt;simultaneously&lt;/em&gt; be a primary parent and an employee.&lt;/strong&gt; (Please
note the emphasis on “simultaneously.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it’s fundamentally impossible to be a mindful parent of your
kids, and &lt;em&gt;at the same time&lt;/em&gt; a productive knowledge worker. And the
repeated attempt will lead to frustration and burnout. Of course, you
can split your day in half with your significant other, if for example
you happen to be a night owl and they are not, and you can put in a
full day of work between 1pm and 9pm (but do ensure you get enough
sleep, which is probably a topic for another post). Or you could rise
early and start working at 6 while your other half drops your kids off
at daycare, from whence you pick them up at 2. But whatever it is that
you decide, please don’t fool yourself into thinking that you can work
productively, and be a good parent for your kids at the very same
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Productivity tips during work hours&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we’ve established that work time and parenting time shouldn’t
overlap. So what can you do while you’re at work, and your kids are in
the house (under the supervision of your spouse or partner, or other
trusted guardian)? Spoiler: “please, kids, be quiet for a bit” isn’t
going to work. Not with toddlers. And sound-proofing your room is
quite expensive, and also remarkably ineffective for the deep bass
&lt;em&gt;whooomp&lt;/em&gt; of an exuberant kid jumping off a couch upstairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find myself being able to focus extremely well if I &lt;strong&gt;play
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_noise"&gt;pink noise&lt;/a&gt; through my
headphones.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It drowns out practically all background noise, and
is uniform enough that my brain eventually drops it as an input, and I
barely notice it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also habitually &lt;strong&gt;close my door&lt;/strong&gt; when I need to work. Obviously, my
family knows that they can call on me when something urgent comes up,
but little kids rightfully take an open door as an invitation. And as
much as I would like to be able to tolerate interruptions of my
thinking flow to play with a little one for a few minutes, and then
immediately pick up where I left off,
&lt;a href="http://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/"&gt;I am not.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
So, this is a classic trade-off: I can either enjoy the interaction
with my kids and then deal with the frustration that comes with not
getting things done, or I can get things done and regret that I didn’t
spend more time with my kids. There’s no right answer. The wrong
answer that I choose is that my door stays closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Striking a balance (or trying to)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things I do to try and balance my in-house family
absence (I’m dead serious, that’s what working from home is):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m home, &lt;strong&gt;I don’t miss lunch.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I can’t say that I’ve &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt;
  missed lunch because I have done so when a customer’s or colleague’s
  environment had just reached the
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halt_and_Catch_Fire"&gt;HCF instruction&lt;/a&gt;,
  but I won’t miss lunch for a meeting that can also be scheduled to
  an hour earlier or later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;strong&gt;tucking the little ones in&lt;/strong&gt; is my job every night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don’t travel when it would mean being absent for a child’s
  birthday.&lt;/strong&gt; Which is actually not that easy to do when you’re on the
  conference circuit, travel about 100 days per year, and you have a
  big family — thus far, if my math is right I’ve successfully
  navigated 28 kids’ birthdays.&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Am I succeeding?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s be real: &lt;strong&gt;I have no way of knowing.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether I’m being a
decent parent will ultimately be judged by my children when they’ve
grown up. Whether I’ve had a successful career is something I’ll
decide upon my retirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hey, such is life. And thus far it looks like I don’t
suck at it. I hope. 🙂 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on my blog on &lt;code&gt;fghaas.github.io&lt;/code&gt; (now defunct).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; from home. Throughout the last few years I’ve
traveled rather extensively, so I’ve also worked from planes,
airport lounges, trains, hotel rooms, customer offices, cafes and
parks. What I mean is that I haven’t had to go to an office on a
daily basis, since 2011. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hat tip to
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Allen_(author)"&gt;David Allen&lt;/a&gt;,
whose &lt;a href="http://a.co/iZhglcP"&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/a&gt; is not the
ultimate fount of all self-management wisdom, but definitely a
good source to have read at least once. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a Linux box with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SoX"&gt;SoX&lt;/a&gt;,
you can generate an Ogg Vorbis file containing 25 minutes of pink
noise with
&lt;code&gt;sox -n pinknoise.ogg synth 25:00 pinknoise&lt;/code&gt;
— the 25-minute length may come in handy if you’re using
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique"&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/a&gt;. As
with music, I play my pink noise from
&lt;a href="https://audacious-media-player.org/"&gt;Audacious&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;a href="https://specifications.freedesktop.org/mpris-spec/latest/"&gt;MPRIS&lt;/a&gt;-2
plugin enabled, which allows me to pause and play from
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/GnomeShell"&gt;gnome-shell&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;a href="https://extensions.gnome.org/extension/55/media-player-indicator/"&gt;Media Player Indicator&lt;/a&gt;
extension. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not consider myself a programmer. But the issue described
in the cartoon applies to any knowledge worker. In fact, it
probably applies to &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; worker, it’s just that I’ve been doing
knowledge work for the entirety of my career, and can’t comment
authoritatively on anything else. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who grew up outside central Europe: over here,
lunch (not dinner) is traditionally considered the “big” meal of
the day. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also took uninterrupted travel breaks of 6 and 10 weeks,
respectively, when our younger kids were born. (When the older
ones arrived, I was traveling way less overall, so those travel
schedule adjustments were easy at the time.) &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>Fragile Development: Scrum is terrible, and you should ditch it</title><link href="https://fghaas.github.io/blog/2016/07/05/fragile-development/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>florian</name></author><id>tag:fghaas.github.io,2016-07-05:/blog/2016/07/05/fragile-development/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scrum is irrational, impractical, and outright dangerous for software development. It is time to stop considering it a viable method for building software.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a writeup of an
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignite_(event)"&gt;Ignite&lt;/a&gt; talk I gave at
&lt;a href="http://www.openstack-israel.org"&gt;OpenStack Israel 2016&lt;/a&gt;. The
paragraph headings below approximately correspond to the content of my
talk slides; the paragraphs themselves are an approximation of what I
said. If you're interested in the exact slide content, you can find
that &lt;a href="//fghaas.github.io/openstackisrael2016-ignite"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Zero flexibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;_____&lt;/code&gt;'s roles, artifacts, events, and rules are &lt;em&gt;immutable&lt;/em&gt; and
although implementing only parts of &lt;code&gt;_____&lt;/code&gt; is possible, &lt;em&gt;the result
is not&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;_____&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you see a statement like this and wonder what should be filled in
for the blanks, it's rather quite likely that you would guess either a
radical political ideology, a very strict religious sect or cult, or
something to that effect. You couldn't be further from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Scrum&lt;/code&gt;'s roles, artifacts, events, and rules are &lt;em&gt;immutable&lt;/em&gt; and
although implementing only parts of &lt;code&gt;Scrum&lt;/code&gt; is possible, &lt;em&gt;the result
is not&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;Scrum&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that's a
&lt;a href="http://www.scrumguides.org/scrum-guide.html#end-note"&gt;direct quote from the Scrum guide.&lt;/a&gt;
Scrum, by its own definition, can either be implemented completely —
that is, with all its roles, artifacts, events, and rules &lt;em&gt;unchanged&lt;/em&gt;
— or not at all. This sounds ludicrous enough as it is, and any sane,
thinking person should reject or at least resent &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; such statement
outright. But let's give Scrum the benefit of doubt, and let's
actually start examining some of its postulates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teams are self-organizing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrum hinges on the idea that teams are comprised of capable
individuals forming teams, which then self-organize. Now I'm sure
nobody would argue that self-organizing teams cannot exist, so this
postulate does not invalidate itself outright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is missing an important prerequisite: teams can
self-organize &lt;strong&gt;if they are stable.&lt;/strong&gt; And team stability is a
precondition that almost never exists in the software industry: our
industry is &lt;em&gt;growth-oriented,&lt;/em&gt; and driven by quickly-growing startups,
so in a successful organization having a new colleague every other
month is not unheard of. It is also highly &lt;em&gt;competitive&lt;/em&gt; for talent,
so having a colleague leave every few months isn't unusual either. The
moment a new person joins or leaves, you have a new team. Team
stability goes out the window, and with it any reasonable expectation
of self-organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sprint after sprint after sprint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Scrum Guide explicitly states that every &lt;em&gt;sprint&lt;/em&gt; (a time frame of
one month or less, in which the team completes objectives agreed to
for the sprint backlog) is &lt;em&gt;immediately followed by the next sprint.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is mind-bogglingly ludicrous and outright dangerous to your
team's mental health. Software development is a marathon, and running
a marathon as an unbroken series of sprints leads to collapse or
death. In software development, it's likely to cause burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Daily Scrum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Scrum's immutable events is the Daily Scrum. The Scrum Guide
defines this event as a specific, daily occurrence, time-boxed to 15
minutes and involving the entirety of the development team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is staggeringly out of place in the modern development team,
which may well be spread out over multiple offices and timezones, and
may not even physically be in one place more than a handful of times a
year. Even in the unlikely event that everyone &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; get together in
one room for precisely fifteen minutes each day, have you ever been in
a meeting involving more than 3 people that got anything accomplished
in 15 minutes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, 15 minutes. Time-boxed, immutable. If you think &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt;
Daily Scrum can be 30 or 45 minutes, or you can do it just every other
day or maybe thrice a week, recall: if you do that, you're no longer
doing Scrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;No planning beyond the current sprint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrum is quite emphatic that the only thing developers should be
really concerned about in terms of planning is the next 24 hours (the
plan for which is ostensibly being laid out in the Daily Scrum), and
beyond that, the current sprint at a maximum. Now, while the idea of
freeing people's minds and allowing them to focus on a single task at
hand is certainly laudable, the practical implications of having no
medium to long-term planning is insane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd venture a guess that an approach where no planning is for more
than a month out is viable, under one condition: having exactly zero
users and/or customers for the product you are developing. I leave it
to you to decide how valuable it is, then, to develop the product in
the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Permanent emergency mode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguably, some of the methods proposed in Scrum are quite suitable for
emergency situations. In a situation where you need to come up with a
solution that requires creativity, hustle, and speed, you may well sit
down, put down a requirements list, elect a coordinator and
spokesperson for your team, and just start hacking. I'd fully agree
that such situations can be extremely challenging, and quite
satisfying to come out of with flying colors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if your organization is permanently operating in this mode,
&lt;strong&gt;quit.&lt;/strong&gt; It doesn't matter which role you're in: as a developer,
you're headed for burnout. As a manager, you're herding your team into
burnout. Either way, you shouldn't be doing this job, either in your
own interest or in that of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Novelty?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrum proponents frequently argue in its favor as the antithesis of
the obsolete waterfall model, where all deliverables are defined from
the outset and there is no room for deviation, leading to products
that are either broken, or outdated, or both the moment they are
completed. If you think we only found out recently that waterfall is
bad, you've been asleep at the switch for over 30 years. In his
seminal
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mythical_Man-Month"&gt;Mythical Man-Month&lt;/a&gt;
essay collection from 1975, Fred Brooks pointed out some weaknesses of
this model, and in his 1986 follow-up
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_Silver_Bullet"&gt;No Silver Bullet,&lt;/a&gt; he
proposes organic, incremental software development as an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Your team can't work with Scrum?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrum advocates frequently argue that if Scrum doesn't work with your
team, chances are that your team is the problem. This means that you
should either replace them, or at least educate them in the ways and
means of Scrum, so they can become a better-performing team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, it should be fairly obvious that if Scrum doesn't work
for your team, the problem is not your team. The problem is Scrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What if Scrum doesn't deliver?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, Scrum proponents usually argue that if Scrum fails to
deliver adequate results in your organization, it's likely because you
aren't applying its central tenets correctly. In other words, you must
come to your senses, and implement Scrum as designed, and which point
results with magically appear, and your team will be in a constant
state of flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is nonsense. &lt;strong&gt;If&lt;/strong&gt; you were able to actually do Scrum (meaning
in its pure, immutable, One True Way), it would surely lead to
disaster. But, it's impossible to do so anyway, so go ahead and ditch
it — stop being a scrumbag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on my blog on the &lt;code&gt;hastexo.com&lt;/code&gt; website (now defunct).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Philosophy"></category><category term="Development"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on "ecosystems"</title><link href="https://fghaas.github.io/blog/2012/12/16/thoughts-on-ecosystems/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-16T14:47:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-12-16T14:47:00+00:00</updated><author><name>florian</name></author><id>tag:fghaas.github.io,2012-12-16:/blog/2012/12/16/thoughts-on-ecosystems/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past couple of years, it seems that the term &lt;em&gt;ecosystem&lt;/em&gt; is
being broadly applied to what we previously called a &lt;em&gt;community.&lt;/em&gt; I
don't like that, and here's why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origin of the term &lt;em&gt;ecosystem,&lt;/em&gt; when applied to the environment in
which a software project is being developed, used …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past couple of years, it seems that the term &lt;em&gt;ecosystem&lt;/em&gt; is
being broadly applied to what we previously called a &lt;em&gt;community.&lt;/em&gt; I
don't like that, and here's why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origin of the term &lt;em&gt;ecosystem,&lt;/em&gt; when applied to the environment in
which a software project is being developed, used and promoted, is
unknown, at least to the best of my knowledge. Some say that it was
&lt;a href="http://krow.net/" title="Brian Aker"&gt;Brian Aker&lt;/a&gt; who first spoke of “the
MySQL ecosystem”, and it seemed rather fitting at the time. Presently
though, it seems there's ecosystems everywhere: the Linux ecosystem, the
OpenStack ecosystem, the Python ecosystem, you name it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it annoys me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It annoys me not in the way marketing drone babbling annoys me, like
when someone waxes lyrical about synergies or paradigm shifts — that's
the kind of fluff you automatically filter out and disregard, a bit like
page numbers in the slide decks of presenters stuck in the 20th century.
But the ecosystem thing is frequently used also by developers and users,
the actual movers and shakers, in the way we would previously use
&lt;em&gt;community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's look for a moment at how a community works. A community is
governed by rules and morals. Those can be explicit, as written-down
laws, covenants or contracts. Much more commonly though, they are
implicit: everybody understands them, everybody is expected to abide by
them, and if you break them, you're being shunned — but there's no
requirement to write these rules down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we think about communities, most will naturally associate this with
a large group of people, like a clan or tribe, maybe a few hundred or
even a few thousand individuals. Puny, right? We need something grander,
something that alludes to hundreds or thousands of species with maybe
millions of individuals playing a part. Let's pick a term: &lt;em&gt;ecosystem.&lt;/em&gt;
Yay! Problem solved. Waaaay bigger than a community. So much more
awe-inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But guess what: &lt;strong&gt;an ecosystem is fundamentally amoral.&lt;/strong&gt; In an
ecosystem, there is no right or wrong — other than survival being right,
and if it happens to be at everyone else's expense, that doesn't make it
wrong. From the inside perspective of an ecosystem, if an invasive
species intrudes and steamrolls the entire habitat, so be it: it just
changed the ecosystem. Nature shrugs. Nature also shrugs at parasites,
disease, deception, camouflage, poison, and gangs of predators
collaborating with swift and deadly force to mercilessly kill a
defenseless herbivore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you're welcome to call me out on my naïveté, and point out that it
is precisely those things that happen in business every day. I am
acutely aware of that. I believe, however, we ought to consider them
evils, and some may consider them &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; evils at times. They
shouldn't the foundations on which we build our &lt;em&gt;communities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speech_acts"&gt;Words matter.&lt;/a&gt; I think we
should use them wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on my blog on the &lt;code&gt;hastexo.com&lt;/code&gt; website (now defunct).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>On the merits of working from home, in a distributed virtual team</title><link href="https://fghaas.github.io/blog/2012/12/06/on-the-merits-of-working-from-home-in-a-distributed-virtual-team/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-06T17:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-12-06T17:38:00+00:00</updated><author><name>florian</name></author><id>tag:fghaas.github.io,2012-12-06:/blog/2012/12/06/on-the-merits-of-working-from-home-in-a-distributed-virtual-team/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During lunch at the EMEA OpenStack day in London this week, I had a
brief but excellent conversation with fellow OpenStacker &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adamspiers"&gt;Adam
Spiers&lt;/a&gt; from SUSE. Our chat turned to
the merits of working from home, and he encouraged me to write up a blog
post about some of the ideas …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During lunch at the EMEA OpenStack day in London this week, I had a
brief but excellent conversation with fellow OpenStacker &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adamspiers"&gt;Adam
Spiers&lt;/a&gt; from SUSE. Our chat turned to
the merits of working from home, and he encouraged me to write up a blog
post about some of the ideas of mine and of my co-founders' which we
have since made hastexo policy, however informal or unwritten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that much of what follows aren't necessarily original ideas of
ours. Many of my thoughts I owe to some very insightful chats I've had
over the past few months with the delightful &lt;a href="http://sarahnovotny.com/"&gt;Sarah
Novotny&lt;/a&gt;, original co-founder of &lt;a href="http://bluegecko.com/"&gt;Blue
Gecko&lt;/a&gt;, seasoned
&lt;a href="http://www.oscon.com/oscon2012"&gt;OSCON&lt;/a&gt; conference chair and now CIO at
&lt;a href="http://meteor-ent.com/"&gt;Meteor Entertainment&lt;/a&gt;. If you get a chance to
talk to Sarah at a conference and poll her views on this, I can highly
recommend you seize that chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all starts with the observation that the separation of the place you
live in, and the place you work at, is a fairly recent concept in human
history. Prior to the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Industrial_Revolution"&gt;Industrial
Revolution&lt;/a&gt;, which
originated in late 18th century England and steamrolled first Europe and
then the rest of the world, no such separation was common: the
blacksmith would live upstairs in his shop, so would the bakerman or the
butcher. The teacher would dwell, with his family, in the local school.
The farmer, and the farmhands, would live on that farm. In such a
setting it follows naturally that the work day spans essentially your
entire waking time: you would start your day's work as soon as you got
up, and finished it when you retired for the night. It would be equally
natural to close the shop and interrupt your work for perhaps an hour at
a time, in order to consume a meal with your family or run an errand, or
to hold the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siesta"&gt;siesta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; common in
the Mediterranean to pass the hottest hours of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then with the Industrial Revolution, everything changed. In the name of
efficiency and progress, we decided that we had to pool workers in one
place — called a factory, or perhaps a shipyard — because now we needed
collaboration: one person could no longer fulfill the task alone, so we
had to get many people to one place to fulfill it together. And as a
natural continuation of our pre-industrial routine, people would work
ten to twelve hours a day, six days a week — until we realized that it
started messing up our lives, inflicting misery on our families and
social ties. And we invented a new concept called spare time: time we
could spend by ourselves, or with our families and friends, something we
didn't have to ask for in the pre-industrial age when our work and life
would naturally have been integrated. And we gradually got to “advances”
like first the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffalo_switchmen%27s_strike"&gt;10-hour&lt;/a&gt;
workday, then the 8-hour workday, then the 40-hour &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Workweek"&gt;work
week&lt;/a&gt; when we decided it would be
better to have a rest of two days a week rather than one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we invented white-collar, office jobs, and we gradually moved from
an industry-dominated to a service-dominated economy. And because by
this time we were all well trained in the rules of industrial life, and
because it had brought us progress and prosperity, we applied the same
concepts to offices that we previously had applied to factories and
shipyards: we would gather everyone in the same place, removed from home
and families, and we would get everyone to accept fixed “office hours”
when all hands would have to be present. Of course, we still needed to
collaborate, it's just that the tasks differed from the ones we faced in
factories and shipyards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the early 21st century, where we are suddenly endowed
with an abundance of readily available, cheap technology that allows us
to communicate and collaborate instantly, from almost anywhere. And it
is at this point that the unnatural split between work and non-work
life, which we inflicted upon ourselves during the Industrial Revolution
and which we have managed to rationalize with the brainwash that a
“clean separation” of “work and private life” is “essential” to
well-being — that has become a complete anachronism. It is no longer
vital for the people making up a company to physically be in the same
place to collaborate, to serve customers, and to be productive and make
a difference to communities. In fact, I consider it counterproductive.
We've finally arrived in a position where we can restore the very
natural way for humans to live and work, namely integrated with our
families, from home, connected through technology that enables us to
communicate just as effectively as sitting at the same desk. It also
enables us to live healthier, better lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm fully aware that this style of work is probably not for everyone.
But if you're thinking it's not for you (and I was one of those, until a
little over a year ago) it's worth asking yourself &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you're thinking
that. Is it really because you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to work in an office, or because
everyone has &lt;em&gt;told you&lt;/em&gt; for most of your career that you want to work in
an office?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here at hastexo, it took us some time — several months — to figure out
all-electronic collaboration, but the machinery is working extremely
well now. The &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/work/apps/business/"&gt;Google Apps&lt;/a&gt;
stack has been enormously useful for us in that regard. We practically
live in &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/+/learnmore/hangouts/"&gt;Google Hangouts&lt;/a&gt;
and documents shared on &lt;a href="http://drive.google.com"&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;. We jot
down ideas in Google Docs and sketch architectures in Google Drawings.
We do our weekly standups that way, and increasingly customer meetings,
too. We collaboratively draft and edit slide decks for training. And we
rehearse conference talks via video call. It just works, and it's huge
fun that way. And it enables us to close our laptops and go read bedtime
stories to our kids when we're done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on my blog on the &lt;code&gt;hastexo.com&lt;/code&gt; website (now defunct).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Philosophy"></category></entry></feed>