<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>xahteiwi.eu - Politics</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/feeds/tag/politics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://xahteiwi.eu/</id><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Why do they always lie?</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2020/02/04/why-do-they-always-lie/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2020-02-04:/blog/2020/02/04/why-do-they-always-lie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When politicians (and their supporters) keep lying even though their lies are easily exposed, it’s a strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across a tweet from my Irish OpenStack community
friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nearyd"&gt;Dave Neary&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nearyd/status/1224727999951572993"&gt;in which he wondered
aloud&lt;/a&gt; why a
picture, which was very obviously (and poorly) doctored, made its way
onto Twitter. As if, so goes the reasoning, the creator of the picture
was ass enough to assume that no-one would notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s so obvious [...] I just don’t understand why you’d bother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More generally, you can summarize this befuddlement by rephrasing the
question as follows: “why would anyone, in a political campaign even,
run with a lie that’s so easily called out?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This assumes that lying, deception, is something you’d prefer to go
undetected. And generally that’s true, human behavior works exactly
that way: when we lie and deceive — and humans do this all them time
for many reasons, some of them benign — the deception only works if it
isn’t caught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why do they lie, when it’s so easy to tell?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, what makes humans lie and spread falsehoods, even when they’re
easily detected?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I submit that to understand why, you should play a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is called &lt;a href="https://ncase.me/trust/"&gt;The Evolution of Trust&lt;/a&gt;,
and its creator is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ncasenmare"&gt;Nicky Case&lt;/a&gt;. You
can play it online, it’s available in multiple languages. And it will
take only about 15 minutes to complete. Go play it. No, really do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you play it? No? Well &lt;a href="https://ncase.me/trust/"&gt;it’s here&lt;/a&gt;. Please
go play it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done? OK. Let’s carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does The Evolution of Trust tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game-theoretical concepts that The Evolution of Trust introduces
tell you three things about its simple game of cooperation and
defection (playing by the rules vs. cheating):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If communications between players are &lt;em&gt;perfect,&lt;/em&gt; then the most
  successful strategy is tit-for-tat (“copycat”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If communications are &lt;em&gt;imperfect,&lt;/em&gt; then the most successful strategy
  is tit-for-two-tats (or “tit for tat with forgiveness,” or
  “copykitten”) — &lt;em&gt;up to a certain error rate in communications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If communications are &lt;em&gt;imperfect beyond that error rate threshold,&lt;/em&gt;
  then the most successful strategy is to always cheat (“cheater”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; human communications are always messy, so the perfect
communications scenario is out the window. We’re always dealing with
imperfect communications, but we never know how high our error rate
is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And most of us are brought up with the Golden Rule and a certain
measure of forgiveness. We tend to be “copykittens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now put yourself in the shoes of someone who has decided they’ll
take the cheater role. They’ll not play by the rules, they’ll only
ever fend for themselves and their own, everyone else be
damned. They’ve chosen the asshole route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their problem is, they can’t win. Game theory literally tells us that
the forgiveness strategy is superior. &lt;strong&gt;Except if the cheater manages
to increase the error rate beyond the threshold.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If you’ve decided you want to be an asshole, lie. It’s your only chance.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So once you’ve decided that you’ll not play by the rules, your only
shot at winning is to destroy communications — for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And your best shot at that is to lie. Never tell the truth, contradict
objective facts, say the stupidest, dumbest, most blatantly false
things. Small lies, large lies, medium-sized lies. It does not matter
if your lie is exposed, in fact, your lies &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be exposed for your
strategy to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now you know how to spot someone in politics who has decided to
break the rules. And why you shouldn’t assume they’re stupid, just
because they say objectively stupid things.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Why upload filters don’t work (really simple math!)</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2019/03/25/upload-filter-math/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-25T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-25T20:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2019-03-25:/blog/2019/03/25/upload-filter-math/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“I can’t figure out how upload filters should work, but I’m not a
technical person — surely someone who is can sort it out!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a misconception. I’ll be happy to explain, requiring — I
promise! — no technical understanding of what an upload filter is, or
how it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;“I can’t figure out how upload filters should work, but I’m not a
technical person — surely someone who is can sort it out!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a misconception. I’ll be happy to explain, requiring — I
promise! — no technical understanding of what an upload filter is, or
how it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--break--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current draft of the EU Directive “on copyright and related
rights in the Digital Single Market”, available
&lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/doceo/document/A-8-2018-0245-AM-271-271_EN.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
(PDF in English), also known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directive_on_Copyright_in_the_Digital_Single_Market"&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;EU Copyright
Directive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
requires in its Article 17 (formerly Article 13), clause 4, that the
service provider undergoes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in accordance with high industry standards of professional
diligence, best efforts to ensure the unavailability of specific
works and other subject matter for which the rightholders have
provided the service providers with the relevant and necessary
information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that the only way any platform hosting
user-generated content would thus have to intercept any such content
&lt;em&gt;on upload,&lt;/em&gt; failing which it would immediately become potentially liable for a
copyright violation. This would require a technical facility commonly
called an &lt;em&gt;upload filter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;We don't need to talk about how upload filters &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, an upload filter is immensely complex and there are tons of
technical difficulties — the only time this has been attempted on a
large scale is YouTube’s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_ID_(algorithm)"&gt;Content
ID&lt;/a&gt;, and it is
exceedingly unreliable and prone to overblocking. But for the purposes
of this discussion, it doesn’t matter whether implementing an upload
filter is difficult to do.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume for a moment someone has built a magnificent upload
filter. Something that operates on magic pixie dust that catches &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
copyright violations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interactions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s call every instance of someone uploading content to the
internet an “interaction”. Every tweet, every Facebook post and
comment, every comment on your favorite news site, every blog post you
write, every picture that you take and post to a WhatsApp group of 50
people or more, every YouTube video and comment — let’s call all of
those “interactions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And let’s make an outrageously overblown assumption: suppose that on
the internet today, 1% of such interactions infringe someone’s
copyright. Again, let me reiterate that this is ludicrously high. The vast
majority of internet interactions today are either completely trivial
and thus irrelevant to copyright, or works of your own, or a perfectly
legal fair-use way of using someone else’s work, such as when you
quote a passage of a book. But purely for the sake of this discussion,
let’s say it’s 1%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So then let’s look at 10,000 interactions that completely random
people make on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those would then break down like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Perfectly legal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,900&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Infringing copyright&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Catching copyright violations. Or non-violations.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK. Now, suppose we built a &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; upload filter, i.e. one that
catches &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; copyright infringements. Remember, the Directive calls
for “best effort to ensure the &lt;strong&gt;unavailability&lt;/strong&gt;” (emphasis mine) of
potentially infringing content. It does not allow providers to balance
for freedom of expression or the like, so to err on the side of
caution, they must strive to over- rather than underblock. So a
perfect filter is one that has &lt;strong&gt;no false negatives&lt;/strong&gt; — meaning if
content infringes, it is always caught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, suppose further that the filter mis-identifies content (meaning,
flags content as infringing when it is not) with a rate of only
2%. That means it has &lt;strong&gt;2% false positives.&lt;/strong&gt; That, now, is
ridiculously low for any automated screening procedure.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that means that out of our 10,000 interactions tracked by our
“perfect” content filter, the numbers break down like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Flagged as legal&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Flagged as infringing&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Perfectly legal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,900&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,802&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;198&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Infringing copyright&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,802&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;298&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Congratulations, a coin toss beats your upload filter.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leads us to the question: if you upload something and it gets
flagged, how likely is it that it is &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; infringing any
copyright? Answer: 100 in 298. Roughly one in three. &lt;strong&gt;Yes, that is
worse than a coin toss.&lt;/strong&gt; And remember, this is assuming an
implausibly high rate of infringements overall, and a ludicrously low
false-positive and false-negative rate on your filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and play with the numbers, tweak the false-negatives and
false-positives, whatever. &lt;strong&gt;As long as what you’re looking for is
exceedingly rare, automated filters detect it with poor accuracy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you leave all parameters the same, but consider a probably much
more realistic infringement rate of 1 in 1000, that is, 0.1%, then
things look like this: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Flagged as legal&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Flagged as infringing&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Perfectly legal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,990&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,800&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Infringing copyright&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,800&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;300&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there’s a one-in-thirty chance that an upload block is
legitimate. Assuming there is an appeals process, and all false
positives get appealed, then that means the &lt;strong&gt;human&lt;/strong&gt; going through
the appeals will have to undo a block &lt;strong&gt;29 times out of 30.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A cheap optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d like to propose an optimization here: any website seeking to
implement a content filter should consider to just use a &lt;strong&gt;random
number generator to reject your upload, comment, tweet, or post with a
certain probability that is demonstrably larger than that of an upload
filter.&lt;/strong&gt; I’d posit that that would be by far the safest, cheapest way
to comply with the directive — if it becomes law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, everyone who is now in favor of this directive (including
its Article 17) will hate that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also easy to dismiss with a “try harder”
retort, which is completely disingenuous, because it’s akin to
saying, doc, this patient has terminal pancreatic cancer, but you
&lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; cure her. Inoperable? Terminal? No there’s &lt;em&gt;got&lt;/em&gt; to be a
way. Sometimes there is no way, and it’s OK when an expert tells
you that. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t believe YouTube releases numbers on its ContentID error
rate, but it’s apparently &lt;a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20181214/17272041233/youtubes-100-million-upload-filter-failures-demonstrate-what-disaster-article-13-will-be-internet.shtml"&gt;pretty
bad&lt;/a&gt;
for a system that cost $100M to build. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Article 17: The time to act is now.</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2019/03/21/copyright-reform/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-21T17:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-21T17:38:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2019-03-21:/blog/2019/03/21/copyright-reform/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Next Tuesday, the European Parliament is due to vote on something that will impact your life. Yes, yours.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, March 26 at half-past noon Central European Time, the
European Parliament is due to vote on an issue that will definitely
impact your life, no matter if you live in or outside the EU. No, it
has nothing to do with Brexit. Brexit has just managed to monopolise
your attention. The Tuesday vote has much more far-reaching
consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What’s going on here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, the EP will vote on a Directive “on copyright and related
rights in the Digital Single Market”, the draft of which you can look
up
&lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/doceo/document/A-8-2018-0245-AM-271-271_EN.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
(PDF in English), also known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directive_on_Copyright_in_the_Digital_Single_Market"&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;EU Copyright
Directive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this thing attempts to be a 21st-century copyright law, which is
laudable, but it does absolutely awful things: go take a look at &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/CyUh9wOp_Rw"&gt;this
video&lt;/a&gt; to get the quick run-down. It’ll
only take 4 minutes of your time. And as you’ll see from the video,
&lt;strong&gt;this law will have a devastating global impact&lt;/strong&gt; on society at
large. (While completely failing to achieve its ostensible goals, mind
you.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is apparent from the discussion around this directive is that it
isn’t being pushed by exceptionally clueful people. One MEP in favor
of the directive once publicly surmised that he was dealing with a
concerted campaign from Google, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/schulzeeuropa/status/1096445520770404352"&gt;because lots of the email in his
inbox came from &lt;code&gt;gmail.com&lt;/code&gt;
addresses&lt;/a&gt;. The
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committees_of_the_European_Parliament"&gt;rapporteur&lt;/a&gt;
on the directive &lt;a href="https://www.vice.com/de/article/vbw8zy/streit-um-uploadfilter-und-artikel13-wie-axel-voss-das-internet-sieht"&gt;hasn’t subscribed to any YouTube channel and thinks
that there is a Memes section on
Google&lt;/a&gt;,
and when properly roasted on Twitter, someone representing
his party &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CDU_CSU_EP/status/1108372306101968901"&gt;publicly doubled
down&lt;/a&gt; on
his behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the words of Janus Kopfstein:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/pggamb/dear-congress-it-s-no-longer-ok-to-not-know-how-the-internet-works-5886b6cbc860fd45c9f2dfe3"&gt;It’s no longer OK to not know how the internet
works.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, he wrote that in 2011, and addressed at the U.S. Congress, but
here we are, with our European representatives still needing that
reminder 8 years on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They even tried the oldest trick in the book: once all of Europe
started screaming about Article 13, they renumbered. So &lt;strong&gt;what used to
be Article 13 is now Article 17.&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t get confused; this is just a
ploy by people who print out emails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now luckily, the backers of Article 17 are opposed by a good bunch of
people who are clued in, and have pledged to strike this Directive
down in the EP on Tuesday. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OK. So what do I do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="https://www.change.org/p/european-parliament-stop-the-censorship-machinery-save-the-internet"&gt;sign a change.org
petition&lt;/a&gt;. It
already has 5 million supporters, and there will likely be many
more. But supporting that petition &lt;strong&gt;is not enough.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check out your own MEPs for their status at &lt;a href="https://pledge2019.eu/"&gt;Pledge
2019&lt;/a&gt;. And you can lean on them: Pledge 2019
lets you call the people whose job it is to represent &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; in the
EP, and if they haven’t pledged to reject the Directive in its current
form, &lt;strong&gt;you can let them know&lt;/strong&gt; (in no uncertain terms) &lt;strong&gt;that you
won’t be voting for them or their party in the upcoming &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2019_European_Parliament_election"&gt;EP
elections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, there’s &lt;a href="https://saveyourinternet.eu/act/"&gt;Save Your
Internet&lt;/a&gt;. The primary spin your
pro-upload filter reps are trying to put on the discussion is that
the legislation isn’t opposed by an appreciable number of real people,
and that only astroturfing bots want this law struck down. You can
&lt;strong&gt;write an email, send a letter&lt;/strong&gt; (yes, a letter, as in, snail mail), or
&lt;strong&gt;call them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, &lt;a href="https://savetheinternet.info/demos"&gt;Save The Internet&lt;/a&gt;
(yes, everyone’s, not just yours). March 23 is a day of pan-European
protest against Article 17. &lt;strong&gt;Find a rally and go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Politics"></category></entry></feed>