<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>xahteiwi.eu - Recipe</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/feeds/tag/recipe.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://xahteiwi.eu/</id><updated>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Torrtija de las señoritas Tatin</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2024/04/14/torrtija-de-las-senoritas-tatin/" rel="alternate"/><published>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2024-04-14:/blog/2024/04/14/torrtija-de-las-senoritas-tatin/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A dessert I made up.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a dessert that’s an excellent use for some stale bread and an apple that’s lost its crunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’m the first person to come up with this, but I did make it up by myself so if there’s someone else to credit, I wouldn’t know whom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The dessert decribed in this recipe, shown on a white plate" class="img-fluid" src="/images/torrtija.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call this a torrtija because it looks like a cross of a &lt;a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torrija"&gt;torrija&lt;/a&gt; (usually called “French toast” in English, though the French call it pain perdu or “lost bread”; go figure) with a &lt;a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tortilla_de_patatas"&gt;tortilla española&lt;/a&gt;.
And the whole mashup looks something like a &lt;a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarte_Tatin"&gt;Tarte des Demoiselles Tatin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amounts are for 4 dessert servings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 stale bread roll or brioche bun (pretty much anything based on wheat flour will do)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 eggs, whole&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100 ml milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50g butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon granulated sugar (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 large apple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Equipment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 medium-size bowl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cooking knife and board&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whisk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small skillet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whisk the eggs and milk together in the bowl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cut the bread into pieces, roughly 2×2×2 cm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toss the bread into the bowl and mix thoroughly. Set the bowl aside for 15-20 minutes so the bread soaks in the egg wash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, peel and core the apple. Cut it in half and then cut into thin slices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the bread is done soaking, melt the butter in the pan on medium heat. Optionally, sprinkle the sugar on the bottom of the pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lay the apple slices on the bottom of the pan, covering it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a large spoon or your clean bare hands, cover the apple slices with the bread/egg mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put a lid on the pan, and cook on low to medium heat for about 10 minutes. The steam from the apples will cook the mixture almost through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If necessary, gently loosen the pan’s contents from the pan using a spatula. Try not to break it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover the pan with an upside-down plate, press down on it with one hand while holding the panhandle in the other, and flip it so the plate, now right way up, ends up on the bottom. Set the plate down. You should now be able to lift off the pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either serve the dessert on one communal plate for everyone to tuck in, or cut it into 4 slices and serve on small plates. Optionally, add a scoop of ice cream or a dollop of whipped cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nutrition facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No warranty of any kind on these. Values are per serving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Calories (kcal)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;204&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturated fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total carbohydrates (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sugars (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protein (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><category term="blog"/><category term="Food"/><category term="Recipe"/></entry><entry><title>Lievito madre</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2024/02/25/lievito-madre/" rel="alternate"/><published>2024-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2024-02-25:/blog/2024/02/25/lievito-madre/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My take on Italy&amp;rsquo;s take on sourdough.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was recently asked (on Mastodon) how I prepare my lievito madre, and how I make pizza from it.
The answer takes a few more characters than my instance’s post limit, so I might as well put it here.
Now, I’m not Italian, I’m just a baking nerd, so please take whatever you read here with a pinch of salt and don’t get into an argument with your nonna about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you haven’t heard, &lt;a href="https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lievito_madre"&gt;lievito madre&lt;/a&gt; is simply the Italian take on sourdough.
The fun bit about it is that isn’t sour at all, and you can thus use it for all sorts of baked goods including sweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making lievito madre is not difficult, if you have access to wholemeal wheat or spelt flour.
But it does take a bit of patience.
Actually, a fair bit of patience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how I go about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bootstrapping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bootstrap a starter, you mix 60g of wholemeal flour with 30g of water and 5g of honey.&lt;sup id="fnref:honey"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:honey"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Mixed, it turns into a squishy ball.
Dab some olive oil on your palms and roll the ball between them, so that a thin film of oil covers the ball.
Put that ball into a glass jar and close the lid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nourishment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows now is a matter of some debate.
Some say that throughout the cycle of feeding the fresh starter, it should be kept refrigerated, which means the whole process takes 6-8 weeks.
I think you’re perfectly fine developing your starter at room temperature, and only refrigerate it later.
This tends to get you a pretty potent starter within about half that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, until your starter has developed some leavening power, you repeat the following process every day or two:
You take 30g from your developing starter and dissolve it in 30g of water, to which you add another 5g of honey.
Then, you add 60g of wholemeal flour and work it all into a ball again, covering it with another thin layer of olive oil.
You discard the rest of your starter.&lt;sup id="fnref:compost"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:compost"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After about a week or so, you’ll notice that the starter will approximately double in volume in about 24 hours at room temperature.
At that point, your culture is well developed and is no longer at risk of collapse, and will only require feeding.
If you’re going to bake mostly with white flour, you may at this stage want to also switch to feeding your starter with that.
So, on your next feeding cycle, you simply replace the wholemeal with white flour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few more repetitions of that, your starter will probably reliably double in volume in 24 hours at room temperature.
But you’re not quite done yet, because you want your starter to be potent enough to do the same while refrigerated.
So, you keep the same feeding pattern, but after every replenishment of your starter you now return it to the fridge at 6 to 8°C.
Eventually, your starter will have enough leavening capacity that it will triple to quadruple in volume in 24 hours at that temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Baking arithmetic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you can start baking.
What might you want to bake?
Pizza, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My standard quantities for pizza dough are as follows.
(These are per adult person; multiply as needed.
Children under 10 count like half an adult.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;125g flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20g activated sourdough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75ml water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4g salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there’s a little arithmetic to be done here, for the purposes of preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose I am baking pizza for 10 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means I will need 200g of sourdough, and at any time I’ll have about 120g in my jar.
So the night before I make pizza, I’ll take what’s in my jar, and put it in bowl, dissolve it in 55g of water and add 55g of flour.
Then, I let it sit overnight in a covered bowl until it’s nice and bubbly.
Next morning, I now have 230g of activated sourdough.
Of this I take 30g, mix it with 30g of water and 60g of white flour, and that’s my starter for next time.
It goes into the jar, and back into the fridge.
(It takes less than 24 hours to be ready for baking again.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaining 200g sourdough get whisked into 750ml of tepid water, and then mixed and kneaded with 1,250g of flour and 40g of salt. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This big ball of dough again gets a thin layer of olive oil so it’s easier to get in an out of the bowl, and is then allowed to rise at room temperature for another 3-4 hours.
(Maybe stretch and fold every hour or so, but I consider this less than strictly necessary.)
Then split into 10 portions of about 225g each, roll them in flour, and off we go with pizza.
Or &lt;a href="https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calzone"&gt;calzone&lt;/a&gt;, if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:honey"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am told that the honey serves two purposes: one, its sweetness takes some of the edge off the otherwise tangy sourdough, so it’s not really “sour” at all anymore. Two, something something enzymes in honey. I need to nerd out with a beekeeper about this at some point. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:honey" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:compost"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a garden, put the dumped-out starter in your compost pile. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:compost" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"/><category term="Recipe"/></entry><entry><title>Sweet &amp; savoury stir fry</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2022/05/08/sweet-savoury-stir-fry/" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2022-05-08:/blog/2022/05/08/sweet-savoury-stir-fry/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Easy lunch. With meat, or vegan.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is inspired by a dish that goes by “Mongolian beef” in parts of
the U.S., but I opted for the generic title since it’s neither
Mongolian, nor does it require beef. It works with any red meat, but
you can also leave the meat out altogether, at which point this
becomes a vegan dish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I normally serve this with jasmine or basmati rice. I have yet to try
it with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Udon"&gt;udon&lt;/a&gt;, which I am
guessing should work well too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amounts are for 4 servings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meat (optional):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 400g of red meat (beef flank steak, or leg of lamb)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 tbsp soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tbsp rice vinegar (or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaoxing_wine"&gt;Shaoxing
  wine&lt;/a&gt;, for a finer
  flavor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tbsp sesame oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-4 tbsp cornstarch or potato starch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4-5 tbsp peanut oil (for frying)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vegetables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 tbsp peanut oil (for frying)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 cloves garlic, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1-2 red bell peppers, cut into 2cm squares&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 hot chili pepper, seeds removed (alternatively a jalapeño pepper,
  if you like it milder), chopped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;180g (drained) bamboo shoots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5-6 scallions (spring onions), cut diagonally into 2-3cm pieces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sauce:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 tbsp granulated sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 tbsp soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 tbsp &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoisin_sauce"&gt;hoisin sauce&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 tbsp sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tbsp cornstarch or potato starch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tbsp rice vinegar (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Equipment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 small bowl (for sauce)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 medium-size bowl (for meat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cooking knife and board&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whisk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large skillet or wok&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare the sauce: whisk sugar, soy sauce, hoisin sauce, sesame
   seeds, and optionally rice vinegar together in a small bowl and set
   aside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re including the meat: prepare the marinade by whisking all
   liquid ingredients together in a medium bowl. Cut the meat into
   very thin strips and put them in the bowl. Marinate for at least 20
   minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toss the meat in the cornstarch or potato starch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heat peanut oil in the skillet or wok on high heat. Fry the meat in
   batches until the starch turns golden brown, about 3 minutes or so
   per batch, keeping heat on high. Put fried meat aside in a bowl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vegetable fry: heat peanut oil in wok or skillet on high
   heat. Sauté garlic until fragrant but not brown. Add bell peppers,
   chili pepper, and bamboo shoots. Continue frying on high heat for
   about a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the cut scallions, mix thoroughly. Cover skillet or wok with a
   lid, and cook vegetables for about 5 minutes in their own
   steam. Taste the scallions. If they’ve lost their onion punch and
   developed a slightly sweet taste but still retain some crunch,
   they’re perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If going for the meat option, return the fried meat to the wok or
   skillet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour the sauce prepared in step 1 over everthing, mix thoroughly,
   and keep cooking for another 30-60 seconds until sauce thickens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nutrition facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No warranty of any kind on these. Values are per serving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With meat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Calories (kcal)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;561&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;34.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturated fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total carbohydrates (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sugars (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protein (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;32.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without meat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Calories (kcal)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;223&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturated fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total carbohydrates (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sugars (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protein (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><category term="blog"/><category term="Food"/><category term="Recipe"/></entry><entry><title>Salacious Salad and Omelette</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2020/01/01/salacious-salad-and-omelette/" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2020-01-01:/blog/2020/01/01/salacious-salad-and-omelette/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A breakfast experiment that turned out well.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometime last year I came across a post on
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/food/"&gt;/r/food&lt;/a&gt; that I seem to be unable to
dig up. However, I recall that it had an infographic asserting that
for a salad to be perfect, it had to have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;something tangy,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;something sweet,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;something crunchy,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some protein (egg or meat),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some dairy (yoghurt or cheese).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I goofed around preparing breakfast one Sunday morning, and out
came this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amounts are per person. Multiply as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salad:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fistful of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocket_leaves"&gt;rocket
  leaves&lt;/a&gt; (arugula).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some grapes, the smaller the better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few cherry tomatoes. Best fresh off the vine in the middle of
  summer, even better if you can mix red, yellow, and purple
  varieties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few basil leaves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A small amount of your favorite cold cut, say a thin slice or two of
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosciutto"&gt;prosciutto crudo&lt;/a&gt; or
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bresaola"&gt;bresaola&lt;/a&gt; (or
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%BCndnerfleisch"&gt;Bündnerfleisch&lt;/a&gt;,
  if you want to get super fancy).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few thin slices of Parmigiano or Grana Padano. Cutting them off
  the piece with a potato peeler works really well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinch of black sesame seeds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vinaigrette:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon balsamic vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinch of salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few turns of freshly ground black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Half a teaspoon of mustard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Half a teaspoon of honey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dash of something spicy, if you’re into that sort of thing. Sambal
  oelek or sriracha sauce will work just fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 teaspoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omelette:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinch of salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Butter (for frying)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Equipment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 medium-size bowl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 small bowls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whisk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small frying pan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare the tomatoes: using a properly sharp kitchen knife, cut
   them into halves, quarters, or slices. Chuck them into a small bowl
   and sprinkle them rather liberally with salt and black
   pepper. Stack the basil leaves on top of each other and roll them
   up like tobacco leaves for a cigar, then cut the rolls into slices
   as thinly as you can. Throw the thin basil strands into the bowl,
   add some olive oil, and mix thoroughly using a spoon or your
   hands. Let the bowl sit on the countertop for five minutes or so,
   so that the tomatoes start oozing a bit of juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make the vinaigrette: in a wide-enough bowl, put in salt, pepper,
   mustard, honey, and balsamic vinegar, and optionally the spicy
   condiment. Whisk to mix nicely, then add olive oil and whisk
   vigorously for 30-60 seconds. The goal is to get an opaque
   emulsion, with the mustard and honey acting as natural
   &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emulsion#Emulsifiers"&gt;emulsifiers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw the rocket leaves and grapes into the vinaigrette bowl and
   mix thoroughly with (cleanly washed) hands. Let sit for a few
   minutes so that the vinaigrette can infuse the leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crack egg into a small bowl, beat thoroughly with the whisk so the
   mixture is homogenous. Add a bit of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your serving plate, pieces of meat, cheese shavings, and
   black sesame are close by (if you’re a
   &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mise_en_place"&gt;mise-en-place&lt;/a&gt;
   enthusiast, you’ve likely done this already) — once the omelette is
   ready, you want to serve things up quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heat up some butter in the small pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour the beaten egg in and cook your omelet. It will be very thin
   so this should take only a minute, perhaps two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw the omelet on the plate (don’t fold it) and then start
   stacking: rocket and grapes in vinaigrette at the bottom, then
   tomatoes in olive oil and basil, meat, cheese shavings finally
   sesame on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nutrition facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No warranty of any kind on these. Values are per serving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Calories (kcal)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;343&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturated fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total carbohydrates (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sugars (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protein (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><category term="blog"/><category term="Food"/><category term="Recipe"/></entry><entry><title>Exceptional Pan Pizza</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2019/12/30/exceptional-pan-pizza/" rel="alternate"/><published>2019-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2019-12-30:/blog/2019/12/30/exceptional-pan-pizza/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My go-to recipe for pan pizza. Works best in a castiron pan, but really any large pan will do.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve found this to be the pan pizza to end all pan pizzas. It’s my
standard pizza dough recipe, plus some inspiration from &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/uYxB4QBlrx4"&gt;this
video&lt;/a&gt;. The trick with seasoning the pan
is an absolute kicker and makes the crust taste oodles better than
without that seasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amounts are for one 26 cm pan that will likely feed 4 adults. Make
several to accommodate a larger crowd, or very hungry people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crust:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200g plain spelt flour&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150g wholemeal spelt flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150ml warm water&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10g fresh yeast (alternatively 7 grams dry yeast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;½ teaspoon honey (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7g salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;good splash of olive oil, about 1-2 tablespoons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sauce:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200g peeled and chopped canned tomatoes (alternatively a similar
  preparation from homegrown produce)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinch of salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon of olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toppings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100g cheese (mozzarella is canonical, but coarsely grated mild young
  Gouda works surprisingly well and you should give it a shot if you
  have it available)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spicy sausage, bell peppers, mushrooms, ham, whatever you fancy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pan seasoning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Splash of olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tablespoon of cornstarch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinch of salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oregano&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Equipment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One large, thick-bottomed pan with a lid. Can be a cast iron
  skillet, or a non-stick pan, or a thick enamelled frying pan which
  is what I use. What’s important is that the bottom is at least 1cm
  thick, and that the handle can stand being under your oven
  broiler/grill for about 5 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stovetop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oven with broiler/grill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optional:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand mixer or kitchen appliance with a dough hook. If
  unavailable, your hands will work just fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare a poolish: dissolve the yeast (and honey, if you like) in
   half of the warm water, add flour until the mixture is something
   like porridge. Put in a warm spot&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and let rise until the volume has
   doubled (15-30 minutes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add salt and poolish to the remainder of the flour in a bowl, knead
   and add enough water to make a homogeneous dough. Might take the
   full remaining 150ml, or less, depending on flour. Pour olive oil
   into bowl and and work some in, leaving the sides of the bowl
   nicely greased. Chuck bowl back into warm place and let rise for
   another 15-20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While dough rises, season the pan. Pour in olive oil, add
   cornstarch, and rub the mixture with your fingers over the whole
   inside of the pan — both the bottom and the walls.  Sprinkle salt,
   pepper, and oregano into the pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gently spread the dough into a flat round piece roughly the
   diameter of the bottom of the pan. You can use a rolling pin for
   this, but if you do, make sure to grease the rolling pin and
   countertop with olive oil, rather than dusting them with flour like
   you’re perhaps used to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let the dough rise one more time, about 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare the sauce. Simply mix chopped tomatoes with a good pinch of
   salt and some olive oil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spread the sauce &lt;em&gt;all across the dough&lt;/em&gt;, covering the whole
   diameter of the pan. Do not leave any uncovered crust on the
   perimeter. Repeat with cheese and finally, toppings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn burner on medium heat, put the pan on (cover it with a lid),
   and cook for approximately 8-10 minutes. The trapped steam will
   cook the sauce and toppings on top, while the bottom of the pan
   bakes the crust. Preheat your broiler to high heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the cheese on top has started to melt, throw the pan under the
   broiler/grill for about 3 minutes until the cheese gets nice
   patches of golden brown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn pizza out on a round pizza plate. It should easily come off
    the bottom of the pan, though the sides might require some
    scraping if cheese has melted and run down the sides. Cut into
    slices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dig in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nutrition facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No warranty of any kind on these. Values are per serving, counting one
serving as one-quarter of the whole pizza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table table-striped"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Calories (kcal)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;479&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Saturated fat (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total carbohydrates (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sugars (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protein (g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you’ve never baked with spelt flour before: tastes about
like wheat, but takes on less water. You can modify this recipe to
use wheat flour, in which case you’ll need about 375ml of
water. Also, while a wheat dough normally benefits from a long or
slow rise, I’ve found that not to be true for spelt. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re from the U.S.: yes I know, we Europeans are a bit
weird in that we customarily give some quantities by weight,
others by volume. You’d &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; it’d be straightforward that we do
solids by weight and liquids by volume, but it isn’t. (Some
recipes specify sugar by weight, for example, others say use
so-and-so-many tablespoons of sugar.) &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My oven has a leavening mode in which I can let a dough rise at
approximately 39°C and near 100% humidity, which is glorious, but
this is in no way a requirement. I’ve let dough rise in a bowl
placed on the floor (we have floor heating), on the running
laundry dryer, or out on the countertop. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"/><category term="Food"/><category term="Recipe"/></entry></feed>