<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>xahteiwi.eu - Work</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/feeds/tag/work.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://xahteiwi.eu/</id><updated>2022-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Uncertainty, industrious compliance, and the illusion of control</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2022/09/29/industrious-compliance/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2022-09-29:/blog/2022/09/29/industrious-compliance/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why are so many managers obsessed with faux certainty in situations when objectively, there can&amp;rsquo;t be any?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If I had visited you from the future six months ago, and given you
today’s headlines to read, you would probably have dismissed me as a
lunatic. And you’d probably say the same to someone who dropped in on
you today and read you the headlines from six months out. And if
conversely you tried to sit down tonight and write the headlines for
March 29, 2023, you’ll probably notice on the day that your predictions
were nowhere near actual events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have no idea what the world, or even your life, will look like
just six months from now. Make it five years or ten, and you won’t have
the faintest shimmer of a clue. There is no certainty about your
future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are three approaches to deal with this kind of uncertainty:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fatalism. The idea that whatever happens will happen, you have no
   control over it, and therefore any attempt to wield any influence
   over your own life is doomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Control. The idea that you can achieve certainty in your life by
   planning everything and leaving nothing to chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creativity. The idea that, although some events in your life (and
   the world) are beyond your influence, you will have the ideas
   needed to make the best of the twists and turns, good and bad, that
   life throws at you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In comparing these, I’d maintain that fatalism is a terrible strategy
for life, and that far superior to sticking to the illusion of control
is an approach favouring creativity — “the process of having original
ideas that have value,” according to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken_Robinson_(educationalist)"&gt;Sir Ken
Robinson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, almost exactly the same considerations apply to the medium-term
future of a corporation. Nobody really knows what the future
holds. There is no certainty. The market can go either way, interest
rates can explode shattering your financing, you might close on an
unexpected opportunity that sends your business flying. In principle,
corporations could make the same considerations that apply to people,
and strive to foster creativity left, right, and centre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am routinely dismayed, though, by the fact that the approach heavily
favoured in management is one of control, to absurd ends. I think it’s
obviously ludicrous to expect an engineering manager to “plan” what
their team will be working on 5 quarters from now, or a sales person
to “project” product sales next July. There are close to a million
things that could influence either outcome, and the person would have
to do the work equivalent to that of meteorologist predicting maritime
weather patterns for container ships, weeks and months out. Almost
nobody in business has the data, the time, the staff, and the budget
to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So managers turn to metrics and KPIs and OKRs and whatever the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three-letter_acronym"&gt;TLA&lt;/a&gt; du jour may
be, in a frantic quest to achieve some degree of certainty — a process
which, &lt;a href="https://www.morebeyond.co.za/how-organisational-ocd-is-stamping-out-innovation/"&gt;as others have pointed
out&lt;/a&gt;,
suffocates the creativity that’s &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; needed to address a
constantly changing environment. The idea is that if you collect all
the metrics and do all the statistics and measure everything (in other
words, if you follow some “process” perfectly), you’ll succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is so obviously non-sensical that the question becomes, &lt;em&gt;why the
hell does anyone think that this works?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have a hypothesis on why that is so. I attribute it to an
institution that practically every manager has gone through, indeed,
one that practically &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; has gone through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That institution is school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about yours, but I can say one thing about my own school
education: &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of my schooling can be summarized in just a few
sentences. Specifically, here’s what school taught me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here is a set of rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply these rules, and you will succeed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply the rules &lt;em&gt;perfectly,&lt;/em&gt; and you will excel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That applied no matter the subject. It was as true for maths as it was
for foreign language education, and for writing essays in history
class. Here’s how it’s done; do it this way and you’ll succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it happens, I was good at applying rules. I succeeded in creative
writing even when my writing wasn’t at all creative: I could spell, I
had good grammar, my writing had the expected structure, I understood
punctuation. As long as my writing was error-free, I made A’s (or
rather, 1’s, in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grading_systems_by_country#Austria"&gt;the school system I
inhabited&lt;/a&gt;). My
schoolmates might have written far better stories, but if in a couple
of pages they had three grammar errors and a few misplaced commas and
a couple of spelling glitches, they’d make C’s (3’s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there’s nothing wrong with giving children a set of rules for
solving a problem, and then rewarding them for applying those rules
correctly.  The problem is with the idea that applying the rules
&lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; is where excellence lies. That the difference between
doing something well, and doing something &lt;em&gt;exceptionally&lt;/em&gt; well, is
simply in the more perfect application of the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That couldn’t be farther from the truth. What distinguishes good
results from excellent ones is either that the excellent ones follow
the rules very well &lt;em&gt;and then add&lt;/em&gt; a personal creative touch, or that
they deliberately bend or reject conventions and are great
nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets worse. The people that school rewards the most — the ones it
considers the overachievers, the cream of the crop — are the ones who
can most perfectly follow the rules &lt;em&gt;everywhere.&lt;/em&gt; We call them
straight-A students. I was one of them. There is absolutely no way
that any one child could have straight A’s, if in school report cards
we applied an understanding of excellence that included
creativity. You cannot possibly be equally and exceptionally creative
in maths, science, languages, history, and all the other subjects you
take. &lt;em&gt;Straight&lt;/em&gt; A’s is what you get solely from industrious
compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, in business, we are stuck between a rock and a hard
place. There is a whole generation of people under 35 who have gone
through this kind of schooling, but are increasingly disillusioned by
it — having understood that all their rules-compliance in school and
at university is not a guarantee for economic prosperity or even
financial security, and further that they can scarcely expect loyalty
from their company if the going gets rough, even if they follow &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
the rules like a straight-A student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those same people are being managed by upper-level managers in
their late 40s and 50s who not only &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; achieved some degree of
financial stability, but who do believe that it was their education
that prepared them for it — and that as long as they continue to
meticulously apply a set of rules, everything will be fine and they
get to expect a promotion. And when given a new rule book — say,
some new management fad imposed by a person of authority, akin to
their erstwhile teacher — all they need to do is apply &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; rules
well, and it all will work for them, too. And the more industrious
compliance they apply to the rules in the book, the more likely it is
that results will not only be good, but excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if that rulebook includes collecting metrics everywhere and doing
misguided statistics on them, it will result in an inordinate amount
of busywork that kills the creativity that organizations &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
need to succeed. And likely drive away the people that could
contribute exactly that kind of creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, this problem will rectify itself by those managers
retiring. But in the interim, maybe a few of us could ditch our school
approach to work and collaboration, and engage our brains to produce
the original ideas that we &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Something interesting happened at work the other week...</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2022/07/16/something-interesting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2022-07-16:/blog/2022/07/16/something-interesting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My company&amp;rsquo;s CEO recently put out a well-written email update instead of calling an all-hands meeting. It was excellent.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am sure that many of you have been summoned to your fair share of
quarterly, end-of-half-year, or end-of-year updates which were held by
way of a company meeting. You probably didn’t like them too much,
maybe even dreaded the thought of 45 minutes (or longer! 😱) of Death
By PowerPoint. But perhaps you didn’t mind turning up because hey, at
least it was free coffee and donuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic rolled around, many organizations turned that
quarterly all-hands summons into a quarterly all-hands &lt;em&gt;virtual&lt;/em&gt;
summons, in the shape of a video call. Now you had to supply your own
self-funded donuts, and probably didn’t like the idea of staring into
a camera for 45 minutes straight (or longer! 😖🔨). Worse still, I
hear that some of you might be have been subjected to virtual
&lt;em&gt;pre-recorded&lt;/em&gt; events, where you could watch an executive pontificate
from a script, with no interactivity whatsoever. Something, I imagine,
that is approximately as engaging as watching a wannabe investment
advisor on a YouTube channel with 6 subscribers, 4 of them relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, our CEO Jim (who, to his credit, previously ran these
events in a reasonably engaging fashion) did something different. At
the end of our second quarter, and a few days before going on annual
leave, he sat down and wrote an email. As in, he actually &lt;em&gt;sat down&lt;/em&gt;
and wrote an email. It had structure, it had a format, it had clear
messaging, it was to the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What was in the message?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m obviously not going to go into the detailed content of the
email, but here’s what stood out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The message started with an intro that clearly settled the reader’s
  expectations: this is what I’m writing about; this is what you’ll be
  reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It clearly delineated that some of the items discussed were going to
  be somewhat negative (as in, worthy of improvement); many others
  were positive. It also clearly established that the negatives were
  coming first, and the positives thereafter.&lt;sup id="fnref:negatives-first"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:negatives-first"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It used paragraphs, which were clearly separated by topic. As you
  read, you knew exactly where one thought concluded and the next one
  started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It conveyed an obviously personal viewpoint: Jim was giving his own
  perspective on things, rather than writing like a detached
  omniscient narrator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was very evident that Jim hadn’t just bashed out the message and
  sent it off in a hurry, but that some careful re-reading and editing
  went into it. I have no idea if he did this by himself or asked
  someone else to go over it with him, but &lt;em&gt;that does not matter:&lt;/em&gt;
  what matters is that he edited, not whether he was his own
  editor.&lt;sup id="fnref:editor"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:editor"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What else is good about this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of all, the whole thing was a remarkable exercise in
efficiency. Jim put his thoughts into &lt;em&gt;precisely&lt;/em&gt; 1,500
words.&lt;sup id="fnref:precision"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:precision"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As I’ve &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/27/this-meeting-should-have-been-an-email/"&gt;pointed out
elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;,
information you can express in 1,500 concisely written words is at the
top end of what you can convey in a 60-minute verbal meeting — but
when put in writing, it takes a fluent English speaker only about
6 minutes to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does this compare to the conventional meeting-based approach?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had Jim prepared slides and a speech for an all-hands meeting, it
  would have taken him at least two hours, plus the hour of conducting
  the meeting. He probably spent the same total of three hours writing
  out, rereading, and editing his message. So the total effort &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;
  had to spend on his email was about the same he would have needed to
  spend on the preparation and the conduct of a meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For everyone else, that is the other 98% of the company, reading the
  email took &lt;strong&gt;one-tenth&lt;/strong&gt; of the time that participating in a meeting
  conveying the same information would have taken. Jim gave back 90%
  of the productivity that would have been spent in a meeting, to 98%
  of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Makes sense, doesn’t it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes it eminently does. So, next time you consider summoning your whole
company to an all-hands meeting or video call, try to be a little more
like Jim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:negatives-first"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an excellent move on two counts: first,
readers naturally perceive what comes last as being emphasised. By
getting the negatives out of the way first, the positives stick in
people’s minds more strongly. Second, it establishes that once you
get to the positives, there is no further downer coming to
sucker-punch you. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:negatives-first" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:editor"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trusted editor is a gift from god (if you believe in such
things). I can highly recommend asking someone you enjoy working
with to lend you an extra pair of eyes to go over what you
write. I was mutual editors with
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/elenalindq"&gt;Elena Lindqvist&lt;/a&gt; for two years;
it was glorious. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:editor" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:precision"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am told this exact round-number precision was
coincidence. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:precision" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category></entry><entry><title>Entropy, management, and xkcd 927</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2022/05/07/entropy/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2022-05-07:/blog/2022/05/07/entropy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a manager, don’t try to negotiate with the laws of physics.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/927/"&gt;xkcd 927&lt;/a&gt; is a modern internet classic that is
frequently brought up in conversations to remind people that a proposal
that they’re making will, while being intended to simplify things,
actually make them more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people quote that strip to satirize or even ridicule the idea of
introducing a “15th standard”, as if the natural order of things was
simplification. Such people are frequently baffled by the amount of
cruft and clutter that accumulates over time in an organization they
work in, and some of them embark on a constant — perhaps career-long —
quest of “streamlining,” “process optimization,” or “reducing
technical debt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are one such person, please get ready for some bad news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as we know, there are three fundamental theories that,
combined, explain the universe as we know it: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_relativity"&gt;general
relativity&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_mechanics"&gt;quantum mechanics&lt;/a&gt;,
and
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thermodynamics"&gt;thermodynamics&lt;/a&gt;. Thermodynamics
has a famous &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_law_of_thermodynamics"&gt;Second
Law&lt;/a&gt; that
can be stated in various ways — in one modern and simplified form, we
say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total entropy of a system never decreases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Entropy,” in this context, is &lt;a href="https://openstax.org/books/physics/pages/12-3-second-law-of-thermodynamics-entropy"&gt;essentially the degree to which the
system is
disorderly&lt;/a&gt;.
In effect, the Second Law states that any system can stay just as
orderly as it is now, or it can become more disorderly, but in can
never again become as orderly as it once was. &lt;strong&gt;The normal state of
the world is that things keep getting more and more disorderly.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are multiple classic examples of this: you can mix two paints in
a bucket but cannot unmix them, you can open a container of gas in a
vacuum chamber and the gas will disperse but never go back into the
container, you can scramble and cook and egg but never return it to
its original protein structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the growth in entropy isn’t noticeable: you can of course
pick up your cluttered desk and put everything neatly away in boxes or
drawers (or the trash), and your office will look nice and clean and
uncluttered thereafter. But, in the process you will have turned so
much of your body’s energy into heat that the overall disorder in the
“system” (consisting of the things in your office, the room, you, all
the gas molecules in the air, and so forth) will have gone up quite
considerably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I realize that not all laws of physics can be directly applied on
a macro scale, that is, to organizations, families, or societies. For
example, you’ll have to go through various mind-bends to imagine your
life as a path through gazillions of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Many-worlds_interpretation"&gt;Everettian many-worlds
bifurcations&lt;/a&gt;.
But I’d posit that the constant growth of entropy is indeed rather
fundamental — after all, growth in entropy is one of our best
definitions of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrow_of_time#Thermodynamic_arrow_of_time"&gt;passage of
time&lt;/a&gt;.
Escaping the growth of entropy is literally just as impossible as
stopping time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does that mean for each of us, individually? It means, bluntly
speaking, that our lives get objectively and perpetually messier over
time. I don’t know if you’re in a better or worse place than you were
10 or 20 years ago in your life, but I’m pretty sure that you’re in a
more &lt;em&gt;complicated&lt;/em&gt; place now. And many of us might probably &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to
go back to our less-complicated life from back then, but alas,
backwards time travel (and hence entropy reduction, read: “a more
orderly life”) is not an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now as long as you’re just trying (and failing) to rewind disorder in
your own life, then — as long as you live and work alone — that will
probably not have a harmful effect on anyone. But it gets tricky when
you’re applying the same thinking to living with a spouse, or in a
family. Good luck trying to rewind your life with teenage offspring,
for example, to the presumably simpler time when they were three month
old babies that slept most of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let’s also talk about how this affects your work in a management
position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a manager, it is your job to slow the growth of disorder
in your part of the organization.&lt;/strong&gt; You won’t be able to &lt;em&gt;reduce&lt;/em&gt;
disorder, and any attempt to do so pits you against a most fundamental
law of physics. (Laws of physics are like terrorists: you shouldn’t
attempt to negotiate with them.) However, many managers are exactly
the opposite: they are entropy accelerators; they &lt;em&gt;speed up&lt;/em&gt; the
growth of disorder in the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can do better than that.&lt;sup id="fnref:hadfield"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:hadfield"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Here are a few suggestions you
can apply when dealing with your management peers, so you can act as
your organization’s entropy decelerator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody wants to replace multiple existing things with one new
  thing (the original xkcd 927 scenario): the only circumstance under
  which you should agree to this is when you already know &lt;em&gt;for
  certain&lt;/em&gt; that the existing things must go away, within a manageable
  timeframe. For example, the software solutions that your company has
  been buying from one vendor have had such a massive price hike that
  they now break the budget, or the legal ramifications of continuing
  to use them have become untenable. That’s when you have an option of
  possibly replacing two (or three) things with one. Under all other
  circumstances, you can hope to replace one thing with one other, at
  best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody wants to solve a communications issue by adding more
  channels to your company chat, more categories to your issue
  tracker, more whatever? That’s your cue to stop that dead in its
  tracks. Opening more lanes of communication never simplifies
  anything; it always makes things more complicated. Those new chat
  channels? Tit for tat. They want three new ones, so they must retire
  three. No, not two. Three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody wants to “open up team communications”, or “flatten the
  organization”, so that everyone’s &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2022/01/16/flat-org-scaling/"&gt;complete
  graph&lt;/a&gt; has way more edges?
  That’s when you educate them about ${n(n-1)}\over 2$, and what
  quadratic growth means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you notice how &lt;strong&gt;a lot of these involve saying “no” to someone,&lt;/strong&gt;
and that that may place you at odds with the the well-meaning
proponent? Congratulations on your realization that leadership is not
a popularity contest among your management colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word of caution though: even if you fight this good fight — and
trust me, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a good fight — you will &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; occasionally look
back at when you started working in your organization, and realize
that despite all your efforts it’s a messier place than when you
started. Not just the whole organization, but maybe even your own team
or whatever your little corner of the corporate world is. The part
where &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; are responsible for your part of the mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is especially true if you are just in the middle of leaving an
organization (or a role therein), and are reflecting on the impact of
your tenure: you might fall for the thought of “I tried really hard,
but things still are messier than when I got here.” They always will
be. The point is not to compare today’s degree of disorder to that
when you started. The point is to compare how disorderly it is now, to
how disorderly it would have been if you hadn’t been there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:hadfield"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a positive contribution to a group in a leadership
role is frequently — and somewhat counter-intuitively — achieved
by simply focusing on not making things worse for
everyone. Canadian astronaut and former
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Space_Station"&gt;ISS&lt;/a&gt;
commander &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Hadfield"&gt;Chris
Hadfield&lt;/a&gt; calls this
approach “aiming to be a zero” and dedicates a whole chapter in
his excellent &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18170143-an-astronaut-s-guide-to-life-on-earth"&gt;Astronaut’s Guide to Life on
Earth&lt;/a&gt;
to this idea. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:hadfield" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>The Review Review</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/./blog/2022/01/29/review-review/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2022-01-29:/./blog/2022/01/29/review-review/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Musings on source code management, code review, testing, deployment, and collaboration culture.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to share a few thoughts on something I consider a rather
important topic in our industry: code review and CI/CD tools, and how
they relate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that I’m talking about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;source code management:&lt;/strong&gt; where we store our code, and how we
  manage access to it;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;code review:&lt;/strong&gt; how we coordinate changes to our code;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;testing and gating:&lt;/strong&gt; how we make sure that those changes don’t
  break anything;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;deployment:&lt;/strong&gt; how we push changes and updates out to the consumers
  of our code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case it’s not obvious, that means I’m talking about a large
fraction of the software engineering cycle. Not all of it; the part
involving “fooling around” (&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/11/21/creativity/"&gt;creative play&lt;/a&gt;)
is perhaps excluded — but substantially everything where people can be
said to be “developing” in a software engineering organization is
encompassed in these things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there’s a few things that follow from that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, whatever tools we use in order to accomplish these four things,
they simultaneously influence and &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; influenced by our
collaboration culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s ludicrous to presume that tools and culture are independent of
each other, or to categorically declare that tools must be made to fit
processes, not the other way around. That’s not how people
work. Culture and tools always have an influence on each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the scope of these things is continually expanding as the
field evolves. To illustrate, a few years ago a CI/CD platform could
get away with supporting automated unit tests and kicking off an
Ansible playbook to deploy things to VMs. Today, what we expect out of
a continuous deployment pipeline includes support for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a package registry (for Python packages or Node.js modules, to give
  just two examples),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a container image registry (for Docker/Podman/OCI containers),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a secret store,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the ability to deploy to a Kubernetes cluster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s just a few examples. I might be forgetting others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, this is a classic example of where we must apply &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/EbLh7rZ3rhU"&gt;systems
thinking&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/em&gt; since substantially
everything the organization does is connected to the toolchain, we
&lt;strong&gt;cannot make changes to one part of the system without considering
the consequences for the system as a whole.&lt;/strong&gt; That is not to say that
we cannot make incremental changes, just that we can’t pretend that
anything in the system stands alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate what I mean, consider the example of an automotive
engineer implementing a design change for an engine. If the design
change makes the engine so much more efficient that it means a range
extension by 10% then that’s excellent. But if in the process the
designer has made it impossible to connect the engine to its battery
(or the fuel line, if we’re talking about obsolescent technology),
then installing the new engine doesn’t just not improve anything — it
renders the vehicle immobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Responsibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- Note --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what does that mean about responsibility? Who is ultimately in
charge of the system consisting of source code management and review
tools, and your CI/CD pipeline? The answer is hopefully a no-brainer:
since everything I talk about &lt;em&gt;including&lt;/em&gt; your organizational culture
encompasses substantially all of your engineering organization, the
responsibility rests with whoever is in charge of your engineering
organization (in most companies, that’s often the CTO). And if you’re
a software technology company so your &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;/em&gt; enterprise is
substantially a software engineering organization, it’s your CEO’s or
MD’s responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, that person may delegate some of the &lt;em&gt;tasks&lt;/em&gt; and details of
running your source code management and code review and CI/CD
platform, but &lt;em&gt;responsibility&lt;/em&gt; stays with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that responsibility requires both an understanding &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2019/04/21/non-technical/"&gt;of the
technology itself&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; an understanding
of how it interacts with your engineering culture. A &lt;em&gt;profound&lt;/em&gt;
understanding. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’d go so far as to say if you head up a software engineering
organization and you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have a profound understanding of this
toolchain and its mutual influence on your culture, you should find
another job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you work &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; a software engineering organization and the
person in charge lacks precisely that profound understanding, you
should &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; find another job, because you deserve better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So having said all that, we can start talking about tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’m going to talk about three of them, all of which I use in some
professional capacity on an at-least-weekly basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- .slide: data-timing="20" --&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;GitHub&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is the toolchain that — I think — a majority of open
source developers will be most familiar with: GitHub, whose
collaboration model is based on the &lt;em&gt;Pull Request&lt;/em&gt; (PR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the GitHub PR model was strongly influenced by the distributed
development model of the Linux kernel. The kernel project is what Git
was originally written for, so naturally it is also where the original
convention for pull requests emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In kernel development, during a kernel merge window, subsystem
maintainers fix up a publicly accessible Git tree for Linus to pull
from. They then send a message that follows a conventional format to
the &lt;code&gt;linux-kernel&lt;/code&gt; mailing list (the LKML) outlining the purpose of
the changes they want merged. This email contains a summary of the
changes, and then an enumeration of each commit to be merged. (There’s
a &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; subcommand, &lt;code&gt;git request-pull&lt;/code&gt;, to format such a message.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The review then proceeds in an email exchange on LKML. Once Linus is
happy with the change, he pulls from the subsystem maintainer’s branch
and informs them that their changes have merged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual subsystem maintainers replicate this model, perhaps with
small modifications, for contributions to the subsystems they are
responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;GitHub Pull Requests (PRs)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub replicates some features of the kernel’s model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The collaboration model is generally, “fork and pull”. Individuals
  maintain their own forks of an upstream codebase, and then send pull
  requests when they are ready to review. (However, the review process
  then uses a web interface, rather than a mailing list — in
  principle, a GitHub reviewer can do a complete review within the
  GitHub web interface and source code browser and would never even
  need to check out the repository locally.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each PR generally consists of &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; commits, which however are
  expected to closely relate and serve a common purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That common purpose is enumerated in a summary at the top of the
  pull request. GitHub calls this the PR description.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submitters can mark a PR as a draft, with which they indicate that
  the PR is not ready to be merged yet. When drafts &lt;a href="https://github.blog/2019-02-14-introducing-draft-pull-requests/"&gt;became
  available&lt;/a&gt;
  in 2019, they replaced an emerging convention in which PR
  descriptions would be prefixed by &lt;code&gt;WIP&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;(work in progress)&lt;/em&gt; or
  &lt;code&gt;DNM&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;(do not merge)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub PRs can be &lt;em&gt;approved,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;rejected&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;commented on&lt;/em&gt; by
maintainers or other contributors, and an approval can be made a
mandatory requirement for merging, but by default GitHub will let
anyone merge the PR who has write permissions to the repository that
the PR targets. This includes the possibility for a maintainer to
merge the contributor’s remote branch to their own local checkout, and
then pushing the merged branch to he target repo of the PR. Such an
event will automatically close the PR and mark it as merged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;GitHub Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub has, for a long time, allowed maintainers to require that PRs
pass automated testing. However, until rather recently, it relied on
them to run (or interface with) a separate testing infrastructure
outside of GitHub to do that. Typical examples for this included
CircleCI, or Travis, or Jenkins. It was only &lt;a href="https://github.blog/2019-08-08-github-actions-now-supports-ci-cd/"&gt;in
2019&lt;/a&gt;
that GitHub announced automated testing via GitHub Actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing however, GitHub Actions workflows are in
widespread use for CI/CD, &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; it is still quite common for
GitHub-hosted projects to allow maintainers to circumvent CI/CD tests
and merge directly. When this happens, it often creates a rather
unpleasant situation in which CI/CD testing is only run for
contributions by “outsiders” or “newbies”, whereas maintainers get to
break things with impunity. This means that issues are often not
detected until a casual contributor sends a PR, at which point the
test breaks and leave the contributor confused (and sometimes lead to
the change not even being considered because, well, “it makes the
tests break.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that comes bundled with GitHub (and GitHub workflow
actions) is the ability to maintain your own package registry &lt;a href="https://docs.github.com/en/packages/managing-github-packages-using-github-actions-workflows/publishing-and-installing-a-package-with-github-actions"&gt;and
push artifacts to it from your
workflow&lt;/a&gt;. Interestingly,
at the time of writing, GitHub’s definition of “packages” includes
container images, Ruby gems, and npm modules &lt;a href="https://docs.github.com/en/packages/working-with-a-github-packages-registry"&gt;among
others&lt;/a&gt;,
but presently does not include Python modules — although you do, of
course, have the option to &lt;a href="https://github.com/marketplace/actions/pypi-publish"&gt;push your packages to PyPI from your
workflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;GitLab&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equivalent to the GitHub &lt;em&gt;pull request (PR)&lt;/em&gt; is the GitLab &lt;em&gt;merge
request (MR)&lt;/em&gt;. In principle, a GitLab MR is quite similar to a GitHub
PR, albeit with a few noticeable differences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The “fork and pull” model is less prevalent on GitLab. Instead, it
  is far more common for collaborators to work on one project, and
  then create topic branches within that project for each set of
  changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the project repo is shared, this facilitates collaboration on
  a single changeset by multiple people: if two or more people wish to
  collaborate on a change, they simply push additional squash or fixup
  commits on the topic branch. They can &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; agree to force-push
  amended commits to the topic branch, in which the GitLab web
  interface will helpfully point out differences between individual
  &lt;em&gt;versions&lt;/em&gt; of a commit (something that GitHub presently cannot do in
  a PR).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As in a GitHub PR, a GitLab MR is generally expected to include one
  or more commits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also as in a GitHub PR, an MR is expected to contain a summary that
  outlines its purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitLab MRs have a Draft status just like GitHub PRs do, and they
  were introduced about the same time in both products, but GitLab had
  a preceding feature called work-in-progress MRs (WIP MRs). GitLab
  has the handy feature that MRs are &lt;em&gt;automatically&lt;/em&gt; marked as drafts
  once any commit with &lt;code&gt;squash:&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;fixup:&lt;/code&gt; in the commit message
  ends up in the topic branch — GitLab rightfully infers that the
  branch still needs a squash rebase prior to merge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitLab MRs can be reviewed in full using the web interface alone:
  the review interface and the source code browser are closely
  integrated, just like in GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;GitLab CI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CI/CD has been an intrinsic part of the GitLab review
experience for years, since GitLab includes full CI integration via
the &lt;code&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; configuration file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since GitLab CI has been around for quite a while, and it has a
multitude of ways to be used, it “feels” more intrinsic to the review
process than GitHub Actions do, which to me still leave an impression
of being bolted on. In addition, GitLab CI comes with multiple options
of using the CI &lt;em&gt;runner:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use &lt;em&gt;shared runners,&lt;/em&gt; which GitLab operates for you. These
  are Docker containers that GitLab spins up on your behalf in the
  cloud, and which you share with other GitLab subscription customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can also host your own runners. You can do that in Docker
  containers, in Kubernetes clusters, in virtual machines, and even on
  bare metal. The runners need no incoming network connectivity; they
  simply connect to a service on your GitLab host and then poll
  whether jobs wait for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can also specify runners that are exclusive to a project, or to
  a group or subgroup of projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitLab also comes with a &lt;a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/packages/package_registry/"&gt;package
registry&lt;/a&gt;,
to which you can push packages from CI pipelines. This differs from
GitHub in such a way that it &lt;a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/packages/package_registry/#supported-package-managers"&gt;includes more package different
formats&lt;/a&gt;,
including a private PyPI workalike for Python packages. In addition,
there’s also a separate &lt;a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/packages/container_registry/"&gt;container
registry&lt;/a&gt;
for container images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Gerrit/Zuul&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it feels a bit awkward to call this one “Gerrit/Zuul” when I’ve
called the others just “GitHub” and “GitLab” respectively, and tacitly
included the corresponding CI integrations (GitHub Actions and GitLab
CI, respectively) in them. There are a couple of reasons for that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zuul is a CI/CD framework that is, in principle, not tied to Gerrit,
  whereas GitHub Actions only apply to GitHub, and GitLab CI only to
  GitLab. Gerrit/Zuul is a particular combination that was largely
  popularized by the OpenStack community, which is why a lot of people
  who are or were part of that community intuitively associate Gerrit
  with Zuul and vice versa.
  &lt;!-- It should be noted that Zuul was not the original CI/CD framework in
  the OpenStack community. It was *developed* (and adopted) by that
  community when it found that it was outgrowing the boundaries of its
  original CI/CD platform (Jenkins). --&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, Gerrit is not tied to a specific CI/CD framework. It’s
  perfectly feasible to run code reviews in Gerrit and use a different
  CI/CD pipeline (or even none at all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Gerrit/Zuul does differ quite notably from GitHub and GitLab,
whose features often map quite closely to each other, and I’d like to
highlight some of those differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gerrit reviews&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gerrit review process differs in a few crucial points from the one
we know from GitHub and GitLab:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t ask someone to pull from a branch or a fork or
  yours. Instead, you run &lt;code&gt;git review&lt;/code&gt; and Gerrit will &lt;em&gt;make a branch
  for you.&lt;/em&gt; Everything else flows from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike a GitHub PR and GitLab MR, which both typically contain a
  series of commits to be taken as a whole, a Gerrit &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; is
  really just that: one change. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which, of course, also means that we don’t need a separate summary
  for the change: the summary is the commit message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s still possible to submit a series of commits in the course of a
  Gerrit review. However, Gerrit simply sees those as a series of
  changes that all depend on one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dependencies between changes can also be expressed explicitly, by
  including appropriate keywords in commit messages. Crucially, these
  dependencies &lt;em&gt;can cross project boundaries.&lt;/em&gt; That is to say, a
  change in one Git repository can depend on a change in &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; Git
  repository, so long as they both use the same Gerrit instance for
  review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And we also have the equivalent of a Draft PR/MR; in Gerrit that’s
  called a work-in-progress change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this, when used in combination with CI such as Zuul, a
Gerrit-reviewed project generally expects CI tests to pass &lt;em&gt;on every
commit,&lt;/em&gt; without exceptions. This is in contrast to many GitHub or
GitLab managed projects, which typically only expect the head commit
of the topic branch associated with a PR/MR to pass CI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Gerrit/Zuul managed projects, it’s also Zuul that merges the
commit. This is also in contrast to projects that live in GitHub or
GitLab: in those, the pipeline run results are generally advisory in
nature, and a successful pipeline run must still be confirmed by a
human clicking a &lt;em&gt;Merge&lt;/em&gt; button (or running a &lt;code&gt;git merge&lt;/code&gt; command
locally, and then pushing to the repository). In addition, even a
failing CI run can generally be overridden by a “core committer” who
has the ability to merge the PR/MR anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Gerrit/Zuul project typically has no such shortcuts, meaning the
&lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; way to get changes into the repo is to pass both peer review,
and the CI pipeline. In my experience, this tends to create a climate
of leadership by example, which has a beneficial effect on both
experienced developers (“seniors” in a corporate setting) and
newcomers (“juniors”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Speculative merging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one other property that Gerrit/Zuul has that sets it apart
from other review/CI toolchains: &lt;em&gt;speculative merging.&lt;/em&gt; This involves
the &lt;a href="https://zuul-ci.org/docs/zuul/3.10.2/user/gating.html#testing-in-parallel"&gt;parallel execution of CI jobs for interdependent
changes&lt;/a&gt;. With
speculative merging, even complex, long-running CI/CD pipelines don’t
hold up the development process — and this massively enhances project
scalability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;No direct repo browser integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, in Gerrit/Zuul there is no close integration with repository
browsing. Gerrit does include the
&lt;a href="https://gerrit.googlesource.com/gitiles/"&gt;Gitiles&lt;/a&gt; plugin for the
purpose, but its user experience is rudimentary at best. A popular
alternative is to deploy Gerrit with &lt;a href="https://gitea.io/en-us/"&gt;Gitea&lt;/a&gt;,
but again, that’s not built-in and your trusted Gerrit/Zuul admin has
to set it up for you. In addition, while source code browsing in
GitHub and GitLab is tightly integrated with project permissions, and
that is also true for Gitiles, there is a certain amount of
administrative duplication to make your Gerrit repository and project
permissions apply to Gitea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;No built-in package registries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another difference in the Gerrit/Zuul stack when compared to
GitHub and GitLab, and that is its absence of built-in package
registries. Zuul has ready-to-use &lt;em&gt;jobs&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;a href="https://zuul-ci.org/docs/zuul-jobs/docker-image.html"&gt;pushing to a container
registry&lt;/a&gt;, or to
&lt;a href="https://zuul-ci.org/docs/zuul-jobs/python-jobs.html#job-python-upload-pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;,
but you do have to either push to upstream public registries, or build
your own. Zuul does not come bundled with multitenant private
registries the way GitHub and GitLab do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Administrative complexity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In view of the above, there’s another thing that you might want to
consider, which in my humble opinion is an important reason why the
Gerrit/Zuul combination has less uptake than it deserves on its
technical merits. And this may sound overly dramatic, but: people like
to be in charge of their own actions, and software developers are
people. And here’s an issue with Zuul: there are quite a few things a
developer can do on their own in GitHub Actions or GitLab CI that
they’d need to ask an admin’s help for in Zuul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a relatively standard workflow of building a private
container image, pushing it to your own registry, and then rolling out
that image to a Kubernetes deployment, is something you can do in
GitHub or GitLab as a project owner. With Zuul, you’ll need an admin
at least to set up and manage your container registry. Rerunning a
pipeline, a simple click of a button or API call in GitHub or GitLab,
is something you trigger via a Gerrit keyword (typically &lt;code&gt;recheck&lt;/code&gt;)
for Zuul — but only on the pipelines where &lt;a href="https://zuul-ci.org/docs/zuul/3.11.0/admin/drivers/gerrit.html#reference-pipelines-configuration"&gt;your admin has defined
that
trigger&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;So, which one’s best?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you want to know which one of these &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; should choose (or
advocate for)? That’s surprisingly difficult to answer, and greatly
depends on your priorities. And I’ll give you this from four angles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to &lt;em&gt;scalability&lt;/em&gt; — the ability to adapt to massive
  organizational sizes, and/or rapid project growth, or an obscenely
  large number or projects within an organization — the Gerrit/Zuul
  combination wins hands down &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt; you have a competent, responsive,
  and dedicated crew to manage it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it’s about &lt;em&gt;getting started quickly&lt;/em&gt; — helping a project get
  off the ground with a good, usable, easily manageable review and
  fully integrated CI/CD structure — you can’t beat GitLab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of &lt;em&gt;beneficial effect on your development culture,&lt;/em&gt;
  Gerrit/Zuul again probably scores best. If you have a team that’s
  great at reviews and commit and CI and doesn’t cut corners, or you
  want to build a team like that, Gerrit/Zuul can really help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when it’s about &lt;em&gt;giving developers the lowest barrier to entry&lt;/em&gt;
  — meaning using tools that they’re most likely already familiar with
  — GitHub is your platform of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="CI"></category><category term="Gerrit"></category><category term="GitLab"></category><category term="GitHub"></category><category term="Zuul"></category></entry><entry><title>Scaling the flat organization</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2022/01/16/flat-org-scaling/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2022-01-16:/blog/2022/01/16/flat-org-scaling/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“We need a flat organizational structure in order to scale.” Or do we, really?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There’s a common trope in management that goes something like “in
order to better scale the organization as we grow, we need to keep it
flat.” The thrust of the argument is that as the organization grows to
meet customer and demand growth (and with it, growth in head count),
additional levels of corporate hierarchy stifle that growth, and
should thus be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any knowledge-driven organization this is wrong, and just &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;
wrong it is can be proven, numerically, with simple high school level
maths. And in this context, “knowledge-driven organization”
encompasses any technology company, any software engineering outfit,
any technology services provider — in short, any organization that
makes its money off the brains of its people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s establish a few self-evident facts about knowledge-driven
organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The people who actually “make things happen” are the ones with no
   direct reports. The frontend designers, the infrastructure
   engineers, the backend specialists, the data analysts. Their
   managers (and &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; managers, and everyone else all the way up to
   the CEO) are charged with aggregating information, making
   decisions, removing obstacles to productivity, and perhaps
   providing some form of vision and guidance. But it’s individual,
   non-managerial contributors of all specializations that actually
   &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In doing so, engineers work best in small teams with a great degree
   of autonomy. They will usually benefit from close working
   relationships with a small group of people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A manager’s role is thus twofold: remove any obstacles that stand
   in the way of the team accomplishing its goals, and act as an
   interface to other parts of the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, let’s consider a hypothetical small company that is
currently structured in teams of 5. There’s always 4 people reporting
to one manager. Currently, that company is made up as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the CEO/founder, Alex (1 person),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 team leads (4 people),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 employees on each team, all of whom report to the respective team
  lead (in total, 16 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, 21 people in all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Management theory calls the number of reports per manager in an
organization the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Span_of_control"&gt;&lt;em&gt;span of
control&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t like
that term a great deal. For one thing, at four syllables it’s a bit of
a mouthful, particularly if it needs to mentioned frequently. But more
importantly, it’s not an accurate reflection of reality: in a
knowledge-driven organization (like any technology or engineering
company), it’s ludicrous to think that a manager “controls” their
reports like puppets or robots. So, I’ll use a different term for the
remainder of this article: I’m going to call the number of reports per
manager the &lt;strong&gt;width&lt;/strong&gt; of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I’ll use the term &lt;strong&gt;depth&lt;/strong&gt; for the number of hierarchy levels
that the company has. A sole proprietorship has a depth of zero. A
company with a founder-CEO and a few employees, but no other managers,
has a depth of 1. Alex’ company, with one level of management
reporting to Alex, and everyone else reporting to one of those
managers, currently has a depth of 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we can say that Alex’ company is currently &lt;em&gt;narrow&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;shallow&lt;/em&gt; —
it has small teams, and few management levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the company has just closed a major funding round and several big
customer deals, putting them on a solid growth trajectory. So, Alex
expects the company to double in headcount on an annual basis for the
foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question is: is it better for the organization to stick to the
current width, and add depth as it grows, or should Alex increase its
width, so that it can accomodate more people while retaining a
shallower depth?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, as the company scales, should it become &lt;em&gt;deeper&lt;/em&gt; while
staying &lt;em&gt;narrow&lt;/em&gt;, or should it grow &lt;em&gt;wider&lt;/em&gt; while staying &lt;em&gt;shallow?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fast-forward five years&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To look at that, Alex mentally fast-forwards five years under the
currently assumed growth model. After five years of doubling in
headcount, the company now has $21 \cdot 2^5 = 672$ employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this scenario, everyone in the company works still works in a
5-person team, out of which one person is the leader. So every leader
has 4 people that report to them. Let’s look at one employee, Sam. Sam
works in a team with Joe, Jane, Harry and Ruth, and Ruth is the team
lead. Let’s say her title is simply, “Manager”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruth now has at most 3 peers of her own, and reports to someone who
goes by “Senior Manager,” putting her in another team of no more than
5 at her management level. That Senior Manager has at most 3 peers again, all
of whom report to a Director. A Director also, together with a maximum
of 3 other Directors, reports to a VP, and the 4 VPs work together
under Alex, who is still the CEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ll tell you that for 672 people, you’ll not nearly have filled
all those 5-person teams. But try to intuitively guess, without doing
the math, what organizational size this structure would
accommodate. That is to say, with every person in the company being at
most 5 hops away from the CEO, and everyone working in a group of 5,
what’s the maximum company size this model can handle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is 1,365.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s quickly break that down and see how we can plug other numbers in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A gentle bit of maths, part I: team size and hierarchy levels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say we take company’s &lt;em&gt;width&lt;/em&gt;, that is the number of people working
together in any group, &lt;em&gt;excluding&lt;/em&gt; the leader, as $x$. In our example,
that’s $4$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, any team’s size (which we’ll call $n$, for reasons we’ll get to
in a jiffy) is of course $x+1=5$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of people any Senior Manager is reponsible for is $(x+1)x +
1 = x^2+x+1 = 21$ (that is, their Manager’s teams, and themselves).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of people any Director is responsible for is $((x+1)x+1)x+1
= x^3+x^2+x+1 = 85$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see where this is going. For any additional level of &lt;em&gt;depth&lt;/em&gt;, we
simply need to add another power of $x$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course $1 = x^0$ — at the zeroth depth level there’s one
single person: the CEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we can express the number of people in an organization with a width
of $x$ and a depth of $y$ as
$$x^0 + x^1 + x^2 + … + x^y$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or, more briefly:&lt;sup id="fnref:i"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:i"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; $$\sum_{i=0}^{y} x^{i}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that, in turn, &lt;a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i2d=true&amp;amp;i=Sum%5BPower%5Bx%2Cn%5D%2C%7Bn%2C0%2Cy%7D%5D"&gt;happens to work out
to&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:indeterminate"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:indeterminate"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
$${x^{y+1}-1} \over {x-1}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plug in the numbers for $x=4$ and $y=5$, and we get 1,365. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A gentle bit of maths, part II: communications in complete graphs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what’s our scaling constraint in a knowledge organization? The
number of people you need to constantly be in touch with in order to
accomplish your goals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Sam, those people are principally your Sam’s teammates team
colleagues, including their manager, Ruth. That’s 4 people. However,
it’s not enough for Sam to understand what &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; is exchanging with
Jane, Joe, Harry, and Ruth; it’s also imperative for him to understand
what &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; communicate about. So, Sam needs to keep himself
appraisedof what Ruth told Harry, or what information Jane gave to
Joe, and how Joe and Harry are coordinating their latest change
(etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that &lt;strong&gt;within a team, communications are a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_graph"&gt;complete
graph&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. And for a
complete graph, the number of &lt;em&gt;edges&lt;/em&gt; is given by $${n(n-1)}\over 2$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case, $n$ is our team size (including the leader), thus
$x+1$ (the reports plus the leader). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we can rewrite the complete-graph formula as: 
$${{(x+1)(x+1-1)} \over 2} = {{x(x+1)} \over 2}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in order for the team to be well informed of everyone’s
actions at all times, a 5-person team must keep track of 10
communications links between people. That’s absolutely doable, though
we must keep in mind that the number of links does not grow linearly
with the number of people in direct communications which each other,
but it grows proportionally to the &lt;em&gt;square&lt;/em&gt; of that number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam’s manager Ruth, of course, works on &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; 5-person teams: Sam’s,
and Ruth’s team of fellow Managers reporting to a Senior Manager. That
means Ruth needs to constantly keep in touch with the people on her
team (including Sam), and also understand what everyone on her team of
Managers is doing. Thus, she keeps track of 20 communications
links. This is also true for her Senior Manager, that Senior Manager’s
Director, and that Director’s VP. It’s only at the very top that the
CEO has the luxury of directly managing only 4 VPs.&lt;sup id="fnref:c-suite"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:c-suite"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;This should be flatter! Or should it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, suppose someone tells Alex that in this growth plan the
organization is much too hierarchical, and the organization must thus
lose some of its projected hierarchy levels — that is, reduce its
depth. Of course, the only way to do that while still being able to
manage the same headcount growth is to make the company wider — in
other words, have more people report to one manager than previously
planned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Alex, being a good CEO, opens some spread sheet software and
creates this handy table that simply plugs in values for $x$ and $y$,
with $x$ (width) in columns and $y$ (depth) in rows.&lt;sup id="fnref:table"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:table"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table-striped table"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;9&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;11&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;133&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;85&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;259&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;400&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;585&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;820&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;121&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;341&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;781&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,801&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4,681&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7,381&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16,105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;364&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,365&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,906&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,331&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19,608&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37,449&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;66,430&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;177,156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;127&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,093&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,461&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19,531&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;55,987&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;137,257&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;299,593&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;597,871&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,948,717&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;255&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,280&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21,845&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;97,656&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;335,923&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;960,800&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,396,745&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,380,840&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21,435,888&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;511&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,841&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;87,381&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;488,281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,015,539&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6,725,601&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19,173,961&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48,427,561&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;235,794,769&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29,524&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;349,525&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,441,406&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12,093,235&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;47,079,208&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;153,391,689&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;435,848,050&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,111,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,593,742,460&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,047&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;88,573&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,398,101&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12,207,031&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72,559,411&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;329,554,457&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,227,133,513&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,922,632,451&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11,111,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28,531,167,061&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our previous five-year plan, Alex can just look up the cell
matching $x=4$, $y=5$ and finds our known outcome, a maximum head
count of 1,365.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Alex looks at what it takes to flatten the organization by
eliminating one hierarchy level, or by two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to reduce depth by 1, we simply go up one row (thus,
  $y=4$) and find the value for $x$ that just accommodates 1,365
  people or more. Alex sees that that’s $x=6$, which can accommodate
  1,555 people. That is, increase the width by 2: reorganize from
  teams of 5 to teams of 7. Alex could also pick $x=5$, that is
  increase the width by only 1, which would land the company at a
  maximum head count of 781. That is well below what $x=4$ can handle,
  but it still lands Alex north of the original growth target of 672.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to reduce depth by 2, we go up two rows ($y=3$) and do
  the same. We end up at $x=11$, which means to increase width by 7:
  reorganize from teams of 5 to teams of 12. Thus, we land at a
  maximum of 1,464 people, slightly exceeding the headcount we’re able
  to accommodate if we keep growing with the current structure. We
  could also do $x=10$ or $x=9$, landing us at maxima well below that
  (1,111 or 820), but still north of 672.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what does that mean in terms of communication channels each person
has to maintain?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, what we want to keep in mind is the number of edges in a
complete graph connecting $n$ (that is, $x+1$) points. For regular
employees, we know that that’s $${x(x+1)}\over 2$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for any manager, who is effectively on two teams of size $x+1$
simultaneously, that’s $$2 \cdot {{x(x+1)}\over 2} = x(x+1)$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to reduce depth by 1 and go from $x=4$ to
  $x=5$, every non-manager employee now needs to be aware of 15
  communications links (instead of 10), every manager, of 30 (instead
  of 20).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If instead we go from $x=4$ to $x=6$, every non-manager employee now
  needs to be aware of 21 communications links, every manager, of 42.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s a least a 50% increase, or even a doubling, of
communications complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the elimination of two hierarchy levels (a depth reduction by
  2), we’ll need to move from $x=4$ to at least $x=8$. At that point,
  every regular employee has at least 36 communications links on their
  teams to deal with; every manager deals with 72.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If instead we go to $x=9$, every non-manager employee now needs to
  be aware of 45 communications links, every manager, of 90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for $x=10$, every non-manager employee now needs to
  be aware of 55 communications links, every manager, of 110.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point Alex realizes that &lt;strong&gt;making the company wide and
shallow, instead of narrow and deep, is painfully expensive in
communication cost.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But what about all those managers we won’t have to pay?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A well-meaning advisor interrupts Alex in the middle of planning. He
interjects that Alex is missing a point, namely all the managers that
the company will now no longer need, and the cost savings thus
generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Alex looks at the table again (width in columns, depth in rows):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table-striped table"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;9&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;11&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;133&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;85&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;259&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;400&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;585&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;820&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;121&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;341&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;781&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,801&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4,681&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7,381&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16,105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;364&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,365&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,906&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,331&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19,608&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37,449&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;66,430&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;177,156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;127&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,093&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,461&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19,531&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;55,987&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;137,257&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;299,593&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;597,871&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,948,717&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;255&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,280&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21,845&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;97,656&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;335,923&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;960,800&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,396,745&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,380,840&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21,435,888&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;511&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9,841&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;87,381&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;488,281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,015,539&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6,725,601&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19,173,961&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48,427,561&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;235,794,769&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29,524&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;349,525&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,441,406&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12,093,235&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;47,079,208&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;153,391,689&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;435,848,050&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,111,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,593,742,460&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,047&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;88,573&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,398,101&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12,207,031&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72,559,411&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;329,554,457&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,227,133,513&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,922,632,451&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11,111,111,111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28,531,167,061&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s handy here is that Alex can look at any one table cell, and the
cell &lt;em&gt;directly above it&lt;/em&gt; will contain the total number of managers
(that is, people who have direct reports) for the same width. So,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for $x=4$, $y=5$ (our original scenario allowing the company to grow
  to 1,365 people), Alex would have to hire and pay a total of 341
  managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for $x=6$, $y=4$ (the scenario that eliminates one level, and can
  accommodate 1,555 people), Alex’ company will need 259
  managers. That’s 82 fewer managers, or a reduction by about 24%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for $x=5$, $y=4$ (the scenario that eliminates one level, but
  accommodates only 781 people), Alex’ company will need 156
  managers. That’s 185 fewer managers, or a reduction by about 54%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for $x=11$, $y=3$ (the scenario that eliminates two levels, and can
  accommodate 1,464 people), the company will need 133
  managers. That’s 208 fewer managers, or a reduction by about 61%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for $x=10$, $y=3$ (the scenario that eliminates two levels, but
  accommodates only 1,111 people), the company will need 111
  managers. That’s 230 fewer managers, or a reduction by about 67%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for $x=9$, $y=3$ (the scenario that eliminates two levels, but
  accommodates only 820 people), the company will need 91
  managers. That’s 250 fewer managers, or a reduction by about 73%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A gentle bit of maths, part III: how much of our company will be managers?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It so happens that we can generalize this. If Alex looks at our table
again, but considers the number of managers proportional to the number
of people in the company, a pattern quickly emerges (again, width
is in columns, depth is in rows):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table-striped table"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;9&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;11&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.33%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.33%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;42.86%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30.77%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23.81%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.35%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.04%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.33%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.99%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.91%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.02%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;46.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;32.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24.71%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.87%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.60%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.48%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.10%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.99%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.08%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48.39%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.06%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24.93%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.97%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.66%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49.21%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.24%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24.98%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.99%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.66%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49.61%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.30%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49.80%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.32%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49.90%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.33%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49.95%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.33%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49.98%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33.33%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.00%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.09%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll see that at a depth of 1, the share of managers is obviously $1
\over {x+1}$, but then as we increase in depth it quickly trends
toward:&lt;sup id="fnref:reciprocal"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:reciprocal"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  $$1 \over x$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of managers in Alex’ company is roughly the reciprocal of
the company’s width. In other words, the number of managers is
inversely proportional to width.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the cost of communications is directly proportional to
the &lt;em&gt;square&lt;/em&gt; of the width.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point Alex realizes that &lt;strong&gt;while there are indeed savings to
be made by the elimination of management in a wide-and-shallow
company, they cannot possibly balance the added communication cost.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words: the cost in communications inefficiency grows much
faster with width, so much so that it will eat up Alex’ company’s
manager payroll savings several times over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;In summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “flat” (wide) organization scales poorly. Its growth in
communication cost far outpaces its savings in payroll cost. And it
scales progressively worse, the “flatter” (wider) it gets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:i"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summation#Capital-sigma_notation"&gt;capital-sigma summation
formula&lt;/a&gt;,
$i$ doesn’t mean anything other than it being a counter. The
formula is pronounced, in English, as “sum of $x$ to the $i$, from
$i$ equals zero to $y$” (in other words, add up all whole-number
powers of $x$, from $x^0$ to $x^y$). &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:i" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:indeterminate"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might notice that this expression is
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indeterminate_form"&gt;indeterminate&lt;/a&gt;
for $x = 1$. Now I’d say the idea of a hierarchical company made
up of one-on-one teams (every manager has one report, who in turn
is the manager of one report, and so on) is extremely unrealistic.
But just for completeness’ sake, we can apply &lt;a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i2d=true&amp;amp;i=Limit%5BDivide%5BPower%5Bx%2Cy%2B1%5D-1%2Cx-1%5D%2Cx-%3E1%5D"&gt;a
limit&lt;/a&gt;
to show that 
$$\lim_{x \to 1} {{x^{y+1}-1} \over {x-1}} = {y + 1}$$ 
In other words, such an organization could accommodate a
number of people that is equal to its depth plus 1. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:indeterminate" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:c-suite"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This why they might also be able to appoint a CFO, CSO,
CTO or whatever other C-suite functions are appropriate for the
organization. So in the scenario we might end up with a handful
more people than 1,365 for the C-suite and perhaps some number of
staff in their offices. But for the purposes of this discussion
those don’t make a big difference, so we’ll disregard them for
now. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:c-suite" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:table"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to compare the bottom rows and rightmost
columns of this table to Wikipedia’s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_largest_employers"&gt;list of largest
employers&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:table" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:reciprocal"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious, that is because the share of
managers in relation to the total number of people in the company
is 
$${\sum_{i=0}^{y-1} x^{i}} \over {\sum_{i=0}^{y} x^{i}}$$
That works out to be $${x^y-1} \over {x^{y+1}-1}$$
Which, for $y=1$, is
$${{x-1} \over {x^2-1}} = {{x-1} \over {(x+1)\cdot(x-1)}} = {1 \over {x+1}}$$
And for larger values of $y$, both $x^y$ and
$x^{y+1}$ become so large that the $-1$ part barely matters, so
it’s effectively: 
$${{x^y-1} \over {x^{y+1}-1}} \approx {x^y \over x^{y+1}} = {1 \over x}$$
In slightly more formal terms, we can consider $1 \over x$ the 
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limit_(mathematics)"&gt;limit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; of the
expression as $y$ goes to infinity:
$$\lim_{y \to \infty} {{x^y-1} \over {x^{y+1}-1}} = {1 \over x}$$ &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:reciprocal" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Voice messages</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/12/05/voice-messages/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-12-05:/blog/2021/12/05/voice-messages/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Apparently, some people think you should replace professional textual communications with voice messaging. Here’s why I think that that’s a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As of late, I’ve noticed that when people share one of my articles on
asynchronous communications on Twitter (particularly any from the
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/"&gt;Getting out of Meeting
Hell&lt;/a&gt; series, or the one on
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/27/this-meeting-should-have-been-an-email/"&gt;meetings that should have been an
email&lt;/a&gt;), there’s
a reply from a brand account that likes to plug/advertise their
service. That service recommends that synchronous meetings be replaced
by “asynchronous meetings” based on voice messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d like to point out that I consider that an utterly terrible idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Voice is slow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, voice messages suffer from the exact same drawback that
meetings do: they are incredibly slow. Most of us speak at a rate of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speech_tempo"&gt;approximately 4 syllables per
second&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:speech-tempo"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:speech-tempo"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In
English, that translates to about 120-140 words per minute. That means
that as a listener, you &lt;em&gt;absorb&lt;/em&gt; the content of a voice message at the
same rate. You &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; make that a little more efficient by increasing
playback speed, but that’s only feasible to about a 25% speed
increase, which lands you around 150 words per minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, unless you are dyslexic (I’ll get to that in a bit) you
can &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; at 240 words per minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, conveying a certain amount of information by voice
takes nearly twice as long as doing the same in writing. And that’s if
your verbal expression is &lt;em&gt;perfect,&lt;/em&gt; which it never is — any voice
message will come with its fair share of filler words (“uh”, “um”,
“y’know”) and incomplete sentences. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add to that the occasional slurred word or phrase, or idioms
unfamiliar to the recipient of the message. If you come across
something that’s unclear while reading, it takes you fractions of a
second to re-read a sentence, and maybe a few seconds to re-read from
the beginning of a paragraph. But in the listening case, it may take
you upward of a minute to go back and re-listen to a passage you
missed or didn’t understand. (Anyone who both reads books and listens
to audiobooks will relate to this.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Voice is more difficult to follow and retrieve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, voice messages are usually much more difficult to understand
for a recipient listening in their second or third language,
particularly if the other person is a native speaker using an accent
that is unfamiliar to them — say, a French person listening to heavily
Scots-accented English or a pronounced Australian twang. Written
messages might still have their ambiguities — as an example, the word
“doubt” meaning “question”, a common substitution in Indian English,
frequently confuses non-Indian English speakers — but those are &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt;
fewer and easier to resolve for a reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, until speech recognition is perfect and automatic
transcription is thus exquisitely faithful, your voice messages aren’t
searchable. You could say that they’re practically
half-off-the-record. Good luck trying to come back to an important bit
of information that someone conveyed via a voice message that you have
only a vague recollection of. Or, worse, trying to establish the
&lt;em&gt;context&lt;/em&gt; in which a decision was made, and having to piece it
together from multiple voice messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Voice doesn’t convey as much nuance as you think&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the notion that you ought to be using voice messages to add
“nuance” when you can’t convey such nuance in your writing strikes me
as patently ludicrous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you need to convey emotion or feeling or nuance to a greater
extent than you would be able to in writing, that is &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; a
situation in which you should meet with a person face-to-face,
one-on-one, and where that doesn’t permit itself, get on a video
call. At that point, when a written message won’t cut it, a voice
message absolutely won’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One good use?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there may be one useful use of voice messages that I can think
of: they may work for people with dyslexia, for whom consuming a lot
of writing &lt;a href="https://a11yrules.com/podcast/kevin-mar-molinero-talks-about-dyscalculia-and-copy-pasting/"&gt;may cause cognitive
overload&lt;/a&gt;. In
that case, voice messages might be a workable alternative. If so, then
that would make the option to communicate via voice message a very
valid accessibility consideration. That said, I’ve talked to people
who are dyslexic and who said that voice messages are not an adequate
substitute for interactive verbal communication to them — but that’s
of course highly anecdotal, and shouldn’t dismiss the idea outright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However: even if voice messages are a good thing for people with
dyslexia, though, I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that as screen readers continuously
improve, generating speech from text may a be preferable
option. That’s because it retains the searchability advantage for
everyone, and the efficiency advantage for non-dyslexics, while also
accomodating people with dyslexia. But, I want to re-emphasize that
that’s just a hunch, and I may well be completely wrong. If you’re
dyslexic and have thoughts on this, I’d love to hear from you! Please
find me on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/xahteiwi"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/@xahteiwi"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:speech-tempo"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun useless fact: the rate of 4 syllables per second
is practically universal across spoken languages. How many &lt;em&gt;words&lt;/em&gt;
a native speaker of a particular language speaks in a minute
depends largely on the average number of syllables per word in
that language. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:speech-tempo" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category><category term="Accessibility"></category></entry><entry><title>Creativity: How we lost it, why that’s bad, and how we get it back</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/11/21/creativity/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-11-21:/blog/2021/11/21/creativity/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A summary of how I think we ended up where we are right now, and what we can do to get moving again.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Right now, it’s easy to open a news site and come to the conclusion
that the world as we know it is well and truly fucked. It doesn’t
matter if you’re looking at Covid response, or inaction on climate
change, or corruption, or communications surveillance: it increasingly
looks like we are being governed and managed overwhelmingly by
dunderheads just bumbling along, equipped with less than the most
basic empathy, and lacking the mental faculties required to understand
exponential growth or conditional probability or even percentages. And
people — &lt;em&gt;intelligent&lt;/em&gt; people — are seriously pondering the situation
with utter befuddlement: how the hell did we get here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The German writer &lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maximilian_Buddenbohm"&gt;Max
Buddenbohm&lt;/a&gt;
recently asked his followers a question to that effect &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Buddenbohm/status/1460124921993084929"&gt;on
Twitter&lt;/a&gt;,
which I am taking the liberty to translate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have a reflected opinion on why everything is so poorly
organized, as in at its core? Historically or sociologically, what’s
the real principal reason? How did this happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s perhaps a bit amusing and stereotypically German to complain
of &lt;span class="fraktur"&gt;ſchlechte Organiſation!&lt;/span&gt; in
the middle of a pandemic and global climate cataclysm, but the
sentiment behind the question is sound: it looks as though at every
twist and turn, those empowered to make any kind of decision make the
wrong one, or none at all, or — the worst — aren’t even able to come
up with sensible &lt;em&gt;options&lt;/em&gt; between which to choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have a hypothesis: I think the issue at the core of why
everything appears to be going down the tubes is that &lt;strong&gt;we have
systematically drummed creativity out of people,&lt;/strong&gt; for at least fifty
years. And as a result, we collectively have no idea how we can get
ourselves out of a rut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me swiftly explain what I mean by “creativity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wonderful &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken_Robinson_(educationalist)"&gt;Sir Ken
Robinson&lt;/a&gt;,
who left us much too soon in 2020, described creativity as “the
process of having original ideas that have value.” And in arguing for
the value of creativity, we don’t need to get all hippy-touchy-feely:
creativity — and &lt;em&gt;teaching and learning&lt;/em&gt; creativity — is a simple
economic necessity that is also essential to our survival as a
species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have no idea what our world will look like ten years — or even
ten &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; — from now, then how the hell is any “hard skill” we
acquire today &lt;em&gt;guaranteed&lt;/em&gt; to be useful in future challenges? The
paramount faculty we need to acquire, train, and nurture is the
ability to come up with flexible, intelligent, &lt;em&gt;creative&lt;/em&gt; solutions to
the problems we’ll encounter tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this we haven’t been doing. From an early age onwards, generation
after generation has been schooled in “the right way” to do things.
And since “the right way” exists only for things we already know, we
are now ensnared in a trap called conformity that is no good at all in
the present situation where so many of us are confronted with things we
haven’t a clue about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate what I mean, allow me to offer an anecdote from my own
personal family experience. When my son, who is now nearly an adult,
was a nine-year-old pupil in his fourth year of primary schooling, he
started to be tasked with writing little stories — it would be an
exaggeration to call them “essays” at that point — in school. And,
given the fact that he was quite an imaginative kid, the first couple
of stories he wrote were truly charming and delightful. But after a
few weeks, something strange happened: his stories were getting rather
bland and boring, and were hardly a reflection of his vivid
imagination anymore. So as his parents, we gently queried about this
mysterious phenomenon — and he was quite happy and forthcoming to
explain the reason. He had observed, he informed us, that the fellow
pupils of his that had got good marks and the teacher’s appreciation
on the first stories they had written were the ones that had turned in
the writing with the fewest spelling and grammar mistakes. And
apparently he resolved then and there to henceforth only turn in
stories that were composed of sentences strung together from words he
already knew how to spell, using constructions that he was already
familiar with — and that he was thus unlikely to stuff up. Of course
that made &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; the stories about as exciting as watching paint
dry, but it kept the teacher happy and thus, off his back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I can attest that this very much goes for my own schooling as
well. It doesn’t matter if we’re talking about my German classes or
English classes or French classes, “correctness” always prevailed over
originality or wit or creativity. I don’t mean to insinuate that
clever writing should get you a free pass to absolutely butcher your
spelling and grammar, but then on the other hand perfect orthography
and punctuation did always make up for abject boredom, and that’s not
quite right either. And this wasn’t restricted to just language
classes: in maths exams there was no extra credit to be had for
arriving at the correct solution of a problem in a novel or
unconventional way. Nay, such brazen nonconformity would net you
either a reprimand from the teacher for not showing the correct &lt;em&gt;path&lt;/em&gt;
to the solution, or at least a snide remark of the “oh you think
you’re very clever don’t you, now sit down and behave” type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My English and French and German teachers appear to have been unaware
of &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; fact related to their institutional correctness
obsession. Consider this: people who actually make a living from
writing — no matter if it’s fiction or non-fiction — tend to work with
&lt;em&gt;editors,&lt;/em&gt; people whose calling it is to not only correct issues with
orthography or punctuation, but also to helpfully point out plot holes
and suggest the occasional rewrite of dialogue or rearrangement of
chapters. Editors are highly respected by writers and instrumental to
the success of a book but yet, strangely, these people’s names are
normally not printed in bold letters across the book cover, and they
also don’t appear in best seller lists. If my language teachers had
been correct, editors should be celebrity superstars! And they should
hold far greater prestige than the silly authors who only come up with
the storylines but regularly struggle with the placement of a
semicolon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the problem with the idea that errors are awful, and the fact that
that idea is being hammered into our heads from an early age, is that
this has a devastating effect on our creative imagination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to say that being wrong is the same thing as being
creative. What we do know is: if you’re not prepared to be wrong,
you’ll never come up with anything original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Ken Robinson, “&lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/sir_ken_robinson_do_schools_kill_creativity"&gt;Do schools kill
creativity?&lt;/a&gt;”
(2006)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you want people to be boring and dull and utterly devoid of
originality, then foster a culture where being error-free is
paramount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the business world, some tend to look down on others who have a
tenuous relationship with spelling and grammar and punctuation,
chiding such deficiencies as “unprofessional.” But at the same time,
it’s commonly accepted to be dragged into a meeting and then forced to
listen to someone drone on for an hour in a narcotic monologue
consisting of the recitation of thirty-four wall-of-text slides with
precisely seven bullet points each, in a ferocious assault on
everyone’s attention and consciousness that gives an overdose of
Valium a run for its money. How, pray tell, is it ever “professional”
to steal people’s precious lifetime by boring them out of their
fucking minds? And yet, this is somehow acceptable behavior in the
world of business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me add another bit of anecdotal first-hand experience: a few years
ago when I was making most of my living as a travelling technical
consultant, I was often brought in to help a team of engineers chart a
path for solving a particular problem using one of the technologies I
knew a little bit about. And in doing so, some decisions frequently
boiled down to two choices, which I was always happy to lay out in
detail: here is option A, it comes with these advantages and
disadvantages, and here’s option B, it comes with &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; advantages
and disadvantages. And I would explain to my client that it is now
their &lt;em&gt;business&lt;/em&gt; decision to determine whether the pros of A outweigh
the pros of B &lt;em&gt;for their business,&lt;/em&gt; and whether or not they would be
able to live with the cons of whatever option they chose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And inevitably, the reactions to this nearly always fell into one of
two categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first category was gratitude for me having laid out the options
clearly and distilled the pros and cons of each, informed by my
technical expertise on the matter and my understanding of their
situation. And the business decision was either completely obvious to
them, or they appreciated having a good &lt;em&gt;basis&lt;/em&gt; on which to make a
decision, which they resolved to make in the following days or weeks,
presumably after some more empirical, experimental evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the second category was complete confusion on a person’s face,
followed by the exasperated question, “so what do you recommend?” Or,
worse, “what’s the right way?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can probably guess which category of answers was more likely to
come from managers — or “leaders”, as such people like to be called
in a &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2019/04/21/non-technical/"&gt;gross exaggeration of their
capabilities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now imagine someone having gone through a conventional primary and
secondary education, then continued on to university and from there
into business or the law, or maybe the academic Ph.D. track, while in
parallel having risen through the ranks of that cult of rigidity and
conformism called a political party — and ultimately entering
public office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that note, another illustrative anecdote. Not from myself or my
family but still close to home: you may remember how early in the
Covid-19 pandemic in February 2020, the Tyrolean ski resort of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ischgl#COVID-19_pandemic_hotspot"&gt;Ischgl&lt;/a&gt;
became Central Europe’s &lt;a href="https://www.euractiv.com/section/coronavirus/news/ischgl-oesterreichisches-skiparadies-als-corona-hotspot/"&gt;first major infection
hotspot&lt;/a&gt;,
directly linked to at least 600 cases in Austria and more than twice
as many across Europe. (At the time, 1,800 confirmed Covid cases
seemed like a lot. As I write this, we have about 10 times as
many. &lt;em&gt;Per day.&lt;/em&gt;) The universal understanding of the majority of
observers at the time — and today — was that the situation on the
ground had been horribly botched, and that egregious mistakes were
made that greatly facilitated the spread of Covid-19 across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official in charge of public health in the provincial cabinet then
&lt;a href="https://www.derstandard.at/story/2000115833853/alles-richtig-gemacht-entlarvendes-interview-mit-tirolergesundheitslandesrat-tilg-in-der"&gt;went on national news a couple of weeks
later&lt;/a&gt;
to discuss the events. And, despite the repeated questions from the
exasperated interviewer, voiced with increasing levels of disbelief,
the official kept insisting that the authorities had “done everything
right” and were not to be faulted at all for their actions — and
inactions — in this public health emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I don’t even think that this was just hubris or an attempted
cover-up. Rather, it’s a symptom of the exact problem I’m trying to
describe. If you’re applying only &lt;em&gt;what you already know&lt;/em&gt; to a
situation that’s never been here before, you’re failing horribly at
dealing with that situation. But if you’ve been conditioned that
applying “the correct solution” is all you’ll ever have to do in life
to succeed, you eventually end up genuinely believing that that’s
enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s how, in the greatest crisis that humanity has faced in
peacetime in over a century, what we’re stuck with are leaders who,
for the most part, have been so thoroughly molded by the perpetual
vicious cycle of conformism that they now operate with the
decisiveness and agility of a herd of mammoths deep-frozen in
permafrost. They are just shockingly ill-equipped to deal with a
global health crisis affecting a closely interconnected
civilization. And the ones that actually used creative ways to &lt;em&gt;get&lt;/em&gt;
to power turn out to be sociopathic one-trick cronies that could not
apply their skills to something useful if their life depended on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks as though &lt;em&gt;systematically,&lt;/em&gt; those who have the &lt;em&gt;power&lt;/em&gt; to
make decisions, at all levels — in business, politics, anywhere —
frequently lack the intellectual, emotional, and empathetic
&lt;strong&gt;creative&lt;/strong&gt; capabilities required to make those decisions. This is
not to say that exceptions to this rule don’t exist — I’m lucky enough
to live in a town where officials from the mayor on down have been
exceptionally creative, empathetic, &lt;em&gt;and successful&lt;/em&gt; in their Covid
response, for example — but I would argue that the rule does stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it would be entirely fair to counter my arguments with the
observation that surely, in the say 1950s or 1930s or 1910s schooling
and education were still more rigid than they are today, and certainly
did not allow for &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; creative freedom than they do now. And that
is certainly true, but there is something that children (at least
those lucky enough to &lt;em&gt;go&lt;/em&gt; to school, I am aware that for those who
spent their childhood toiling in the fields or coal mines it was an
entirely different story) had during their schooling in those days
that is a precious rarity today: time and space to let their mind
play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Cleese writes in his &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/50719532-creativity"&gt;excellent book on
creativity&lt;/a&gt;
that &lt;em&gt;mental play&lt;/em&gt; — the ability to let your mind wander and thereby
become open to developing new ideas — is a key element of the creative
process. And this is by no means limited to music or literature or the
arts; some of the examples he lists of mental playfulness leading to
groundbreaking new ideas are from the world of science. Now, it is
essential to be able to keep our mind in that state of playfulness for
some time, because it takes a little while for new ideas to pop into
our head. And so, Cleese observes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest killer of creativity is interruption. It pulls your
mind away from what you want to be thinking about. […] It might be
an interruption from outside, like someone coming over and talking
to you, or an email popping up in your inbox. Or it may come from
inside, as when you suddenly remember something you’ve forgotten to
do, or worry that time is running out, or that you don’t think
you’re clever enough to solve whatever problem it is you’re trying
to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— John Cleese, “Creativity: A Short and Cheerful Guide” (2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is the bit that’s incredibly difficult to achieve for most
people born after about 1970, and many born earlier too. That includes
any child alive today, but also their parents and many of their
grandparents. We are &lt;em&gt;constantly&lt;/em&gt; dealing with outside interruptions,
many of them coming from a device we carry in our pockets all day. We
have to fight for our uninterrupted mental play time. A child in the
1950s might just run off to play with friends for the afternoon, and
return home for supper. Without a text from a parent or a snapchat
message from the school bully rudely interrupting halfway
through. It’s perhaps no coincidence that some of those 1950s children
ended up being
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Aaron"&gt;26-year-olds&lt;/a&gt; who could
figure out powering up a disabled spacecraft while it’s on a
free-return trajectory around the Moon, saving the life of a three-man
crew in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s more evidence that even in the world of engineering, allowing
your mind to let go for a bit can lead to creative breakthroughs: &lt;a href="https://appel.nasa.gov/2010/09/20/jim-crocker-on-systems-engineering/"&gt;Jim
Crocker&lt;/a&gt;
was the Ball Aerospace engineer who solved the problem of how exactly
the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corrective_Optics_Space_Telescope_Axial_Replacement"&gt;corrective
optics&lt;/a&gt;
on the Hubble Space Telescope should be installed — obviously not a
scenario that anyone accounted for in Hubble’s design.  The ingenious
idea that ended up saving Hubble from being a multibillion dollar
boondoggle &lt;a href="https://www.ball.com/aerospace/newsroom/features/genius-at-work"&gt;came to him in the
shower&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, in offices in which we worked with maybe one other colleague in
the room, we had stretches of time where the other person was off
running an errand in town or taking a meeting in a conference
room. And you could close the door and put up a “do not disturb” sign
and do some uninterrupted thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the year 2000, most of that started to change, dramatically.
Open-plan offices, which of course were allegedly introduced to
“facilitate cooperation,” eliminated any room for uninterrupted mental
play at work. Emails replaced typed and printed memos, office workers
transitioned from workstations to laptops. Pagers and cell phones
started to buzz people at home. Around 2010 we progressed to smart
phones, tablets and other portable devices that had the ability to
ping us out of playful thought with an audible notification at any
time of day. &lt;em&gt;Knowledge work became interrupt-driven&lt;/em&gt; — a sentence
that in itself should make anyone shudder that knows anything about
knowledge work at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it’s no surprise that people who rose to corporate leadership
after being imprinted by an interrupt-driven lifestyle — that is,
people now in their 50s — think that such a thing is &lt;em&gt;normal,&lt;/em&gt; and try
to impress the same thing on their subordinates. That’s how you get to
Slack-driven companies. That’s how you end up in a culture where
people are proud of getting back to any email within 30 minutes (or
less), and expecting the same from everyone. That’s how you end up
with managers who take being signed into a chat (and thereby
&lt;em&gt;constantly&lt;/em&gt; listening for interruptions) as a measure of being
“active”, so much so that they &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pleia2/status/1456629767743016966"&gt;end up tracking metrics for
it&lt;/a&gt;, and of
course also &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/11/14/meaningless-metrics-treacherous-targets/"&gt;making it a
target&lt;/a&gt; they
call “engagement” or some other abomination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations that do that are at risk of constantly shutting down
creativity, problem-solving, and innovation. What they’re good for is
developing efficient cookie-cutter techniques for optimizing solutions
for &lt;em&gt;yesterday’s&lt;/em&gt; issues. What we need &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; — in a global pandemic,
and in the roiling climate crisis that’ll make this pandemic look like
a walk in the park — is people and organizations equipped with the
mindset for the issues of &lt;em&gt;tomorrow.&lt;/em&gt; And a first imperative for
making that happen is to &lt;strong&gt;let people think.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is everything all doom and gloom? I’d say it isn’t, and there are
indeed some things that make me hopeful. Some of those are related to
a changed approach to creativity in education, some, to a changing
approach to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in my country as of a few years ago it is indeed such
that creativity and originality are accorded at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; merit in
marking and grading standards. And this is at the secondary school
level, traditionally one of the most rigid and unchanging branches of
education where I live. Much more still is happening at the primary
and preschool level, where I see &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more emphasis on thinking,
creative play, and innovation in my younger kids’ education than I did
in my older ones’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, there’s the big push towards asynchronous distributed work —
where obviously the &lt;em&gt;asynchronous&lt;/em&gt; part is the bit that matters. Sure,
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/23/make-my-company-distributed/"&gt;companies suffering from &lt;em&gt;offissification&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
still exist, but for a while, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dodo"&gt;so did
dodos&lt;/a&gt;. But an ever-increasing
share of humanity is beginning to understand what it’s like when
you’re no longer shackled to seventeen Slack channels you constantly
need to watch, when you can take a walk in the middle of the day
because you know it’s OK to push something off for an hour to clear
your head and come up with an idea, and when instead of spending an
hour in a meeting &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/27/this-meeting-should-have-been-an-email/"&gt;you can spend 5 minutes reading a memo and use the
other 55 minutes for
thinking&lt;/a&gt;.  And
that’s where things get interesting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Meaningless Metrics, Treacherous Targets</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/11/14/meaningless-metrics-treacherous-targets/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-11-14:/blog/2021/11/14/meaningless-metrics-treacherous-targets/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A quick introduction to Goodhart, Strathern, Campbell, Yankelovich, and McNamara.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common feature of organizations in the software technology industry
(but certainly not &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; in that industry) is their fixation on
metrics, measurements, and quantifiers. I understand that this is
frequently done and advocated for in the spirit of making management
more objective, less arbitrary, more scientific, and perhaps
fairer. But since they say that the road to hell is often paved with
good intentions, here’s a quick summary of what we know about about
the undesirable side effects of such an approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goodhart’s Law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;British economist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Goodhart"&gt;Charles
Goodhart&lt;/a&gt; wrote in
1975, in an article about British monetary policy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any observed statistical regularity will tend to collapse once
pressure is placed upon it for control purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Charles Goodhart, “Problems of Monetary Management: the
U.K. Experience” (1975)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a mouthful of somewhat niche technical jargon, but let me try
to paraphrase it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You collect some data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You crunch the numbers using statistics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You observe a pattern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You distill a value (a “statistical regularity”) from it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone decides that that value should change: it is too high or too
  low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone — an individual or a group — is tasked with bringing that
  value up or down, and then keeping it high or low, or rising or
  falling, or above or below a particular threshold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That value now is no longer a useful statistical indicator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; knew as &lt;em&gt;Goodhart’s Law&lt;/em&gt; if you’d heard about it
prior to reading this article is a generalization by anthropologist
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marilyn_Strathern"&gt;Marilyn Strathern&lt;/a&gt;,
also from the UK:&lt;sup id="fnref:why-goodhart"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:why-goodhart"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Marilyn Strathern, “&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/ImprovingRatingsAuditInTheBritishUniversitySystem"&gt;‘Improving ratings’: audit in the British
University
system&lt;/a&gt;”
(1997)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is that so? It’s because once you make the measure a target that
has an influence on people (for example, meeting it gets them a bonus,
failing at it gets them a demotion), you have wired them to improve
&lt;em&gt;the measure,&lt;/em&gt; and not necessarily to improve the underlying
conditions that the measure originally arose from. Therefore, they
might opt for gaming the measure, because that gets them to their goal
(a promotion, for example) more quickly and at less effort to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, even keeping the option of fudging the numbers aside:
when faced with a choice between doing something that might have a
negative effect on the measure and something else that might have a
negative effect on something &lt;em&gt;other than&lt;/em&gt; the measure, people will
tend to choose the latter. This may lead to situations where people
&lt;em&gt;avoid&lt;/em&gt; an activity with &lt;em&gt;significant&lt;/em&gt; inherent value, just to avoid
depressing a measurement — a concept known as &lt;em&gt;creaming.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:creaming"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:creaming"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a hospital may be interested in measuring individual
surgeons’ intraoperative death rates: the percentage of a surgeon’s
patients that die in the middle of surgery. On its face, this metric
could help weed out bad surgeons. If a particular surgeon is an
outlier and has &lt;em&gt;way more&lt;/em&gt; patients dying on their operating table
than their peers, it’s possible that that surgeon might be doing
something wrong: they could be incompetent, or frequently intoxicated,
or even be a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dr._Death"&gt;Dr. Death&lt;/a&gt; type
serial killer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets tricky, though, when in the interest of transparency the
hospital doesn’t just fire or retrain incompetent surgeons which it
identifies based on such statistics, but when it “publishes” the
patient mortality data. (I use quotes here because this does not
necessarily mean sharing it with the general public, but perhaps
sharing it with all of the surgical staff.) At that stage, an
individual surgeon’s &lt;em&gt;rank&lt;/em&gt; in the statistics will become at least a
matter of pride, status, and prestige, even if it’s not otherwise
rewarded in any way, nor seen as a precondition for continued
employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, then, will incentivize surgeons to &lt;em&gt;avoid&lt;/em&gt; taking on risky
surgeries where there is a significant chance of the patient dying
mid-surgery — surgeries typically &lt;em&gt;attempted&lt;/em&gt; in the first place to
save the patient’s life, in the course of an immediate major
emergency. Thus, Dr. Alpher who only ever treats torn knee ligaments
might look better in the ranking than Dr. Bethe the polytrauma
specialist, or Dr. Gamow the neurosurgeon who specializes in
particularly challenging malignant brain tumor removal. If there is a
non-negligeable risk of intraoperative death for a particular brain
cancer patient and such an event would be bad for Dr. Gamow’s ranking,
then Dr. Gamow might have an incentive to declare that patient
inoperable — and as a result the patient would &lt;em&gt;certainly&lt;/em&gt; die, just
not in surgery.&lt;sup id="fnref:tyranny"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:tyranny"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Campbell’s Law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although less well known than Goodhart’s law, Campbell’s law is
closely related and, in my humble opinion, just as important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_T._Campbell"&gt;Donald
T. Campbell&lt;/a&gt;, a
U.S.-based social scientist, wrote in 1976, on the subject of
standardized testing in education:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more any quantitative social indicator is used for social
decision-making, the more subject it will be to corruption pressures
and the more apt it will be to distort and corrupt the social
processes it is intended to monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Achievement tests may well be valuable indicators of general school
achievement under conditions of normal teaching aimed at general
competence. But when test scores become the goal of the teaching
process, they both lose their value as indicators of educational
status and distort the educational process in undesirable ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Donald T. Campbell, “Assessing the impact of planned social
change” (1976)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you conduct a one-time evaluation of student
achievement across many students in multiple schools, then the fact
that the test is standardized might help in achieving comparable
results. However, as soon as you make the tests a repeat occurrence,
and tie students’ test results to school funding allocations, teacher
salaries, or even just school prestige, you’re undermining their
original purpose: teachers will now spend a significant portion of
their time and effort to ensure that students &lt;em&gt;score well on the
test&lt;/em&gt;, rather than build the competence that the test was originally
designed to measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an example of allocating resources (teacher and student time
and effort) to an activity with no inherent value (taking a
standardized test) just to improve a measurement (the test score). And
since the resources are finite, spending them on the activity with no
inherent value (test-taking) makes less of them available to the
inherently valuable activity the indicator is intended to assess
(teaching and learning). This is the “corruption and distortion”
Campbell talks about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The McNamara Fallacy, and the Yankelovich Ladder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closely related to Goodhart’s, Strathern’s and Campbell’s observations
is something called the McNamara Fallacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_McNamara"&gt;Robert McNamara&lt;/a&gt;,
U.S. Secretary of Defense during much of the Vietnam war, infamously
believed that he could scientifically measure the progress of the war
by quantitative indicators alone. One of his favourites was &lt;em&gt;body
count,&lt;/em&gt; the number of enemy personnel killed, in comparison to
friendly casualties. The rationale appears to have been, whatever
other factors (qualitative or quantitative) are in play, whichever
side kills more of the other wins the war. Indeed he seems to have
been inclined towards ignoring all non-quantitative indicators of how
the war was going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An anecdote
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McNamara_fallacy#The_Vietnam_War"&gt;told&lt;/a&gt;
by U.S. Air Force general &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Lansdale"&gt;Edward
Lansdale&lt;/a&gt; alleges that
he (Lansdale) pointed out to McNamara in a briefing that McNamara,
when assessing the progress of the war, failed to take into account
the feelings of the common rural Vietnamese people. McNamara then
allegedly wrote an item saying “feelings of the Vietnamese people” on
his list of things to keep track of in pencil, pondered it for a
moment, and then erased it — reasoning to Lansdale that feelings
cannot be measured, thus must not be important.&lt;sup id="fnref:lansdale"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:lansdale"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is step 3 on a progressive scale social scientist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Yankelovich"&gt;Daniel
Yankelovich&lt;/a&gt;
described a few years later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to measure whatever can be easily measured. This
  is OK as far as it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second step is to disregard that which can’t be easily
  measured or to give it an arbitrary quantitative value. This is
  artificial and misleading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third step is to presume that what can’t be measured easily
  really isn’t important. This is blindness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth step is to say that what can’t be easily measured
  really doesn’t exist. This is suicide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Daniel Yankelovich, “Corporate Priorities: A continuing study of
the new demands on business” (1972).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it’s somewhat remarkable just how often businesses and
organizations fall into this trap, fifty years later. They might not
end up at step 4, but falling for step 2 or 3 is bad enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An applied example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s now turn to an example from our industry. Something that’s so
important, evidently, that it has given rise to a whole discipline in
our field: &lt;em&gt;site reliability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s perhaps a bit amusing that although you can find myriads of
articles describing what &lt;em&gt;site reliability engineering&lt;/em&gt; (SRE) is, a
definition of “site reliability” lives only in a small footnote of the
&lt;a href="https://sre.google/sre-book/preface/#id-gA2u2Iyh4"&gt;Google SRE Book&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our purposes, reliability is “The probability that [a system]
will perform a required function without failure under stated
conditions for a stated period of time”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Betsy Beyer, Chris Jones, Jennifer Petoff, Niall Murphy, “Site
Reliability Engineering: How Google Runs Production Systems”
(2017)&lt;sup id="fnref:oconnor"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:oconnor"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, at least there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a definition, which is good. Now I think it’s
reasonable to say that the following two statements &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; site
reliability are probably true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with SRE reflecting a holistic approach to engineering,
   trying to unify a multitude of considerations, site reliability is
   not something we can judge by a single, numerical, universal, and
   useful metric. You can’t measure a single “site reliability score”,
   and then compare hundreds of platforms based on that.&lt;sup id="fnref:score"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:score"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever site reliability &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; as a whole, it certainly &lt;em&gt;includes&lt;/em&gt;
   a site’s ability to process your data and not mangle it. So, if you
   upload your data into a platform, you want to be able to do
   something useful with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SRE tends to rely on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://sre.google/sre-book/service-level-objectives/#indicators-o8seIAcZ"&gt;service level
indicators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
(SLIs) to measure compliance with service level agreements (SLAs),
manage error budgets, and generally keep track of what shape the
site/platform is in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let’s compare two indicators that differ greatly in their
measurability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Availability&lt;/em&gt; is exceptionally easy to measure for, say, a REST
   API. You send a request with a defined payload, you measure the
   time it takes to serve your request, you check the status code, you
   check whether the response contains what you expect, and you record
   a data point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Durability&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more difficult to measure at any given point
   in time. Effectively, to properly take a data point for durability
   at the same time as getting one for availability, you’d have to
   read back some data you wrote, say, a year ago, and check its
   content against something like a known hash.&lt;sup id="fnref:hash"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:hash"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;And also&lt;/em&gt; write some
   data now, travel a year into the future, read it back at that
   point, travel back into the present,&lt;sup id="fnref:timetravel"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:timetravel"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and record your
   data point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now before I continue I’d like to inject another thought to the issue
of data durability: not every platform is a storage solution. In other
words, you don’t always have the option of reading your data back
verbatim. Say for example you’re feeding an inordinate number of data
points into a platform that ingests and aggregates them. You may not
even be interested in the original data some months or years down the
road, so it might be acceptable (and even necessary, as dictated by
cost concerns) to discard the original data immediately after it has
been processed. And that rules out the possibility (or necessity) to
ever read it back exactly as it went in. But you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be interested
in the statistics that you generate based on the aggregated data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now suppose there is a subtle bug in the &lt;em&gt;implementation&lt;/em&gt; of the
aggregation algorithm. As in, the algorithm itself is perfectly fine,
but there’s a flaw in the implementation. That, too, may render part
of your data unusable or outright invalid, violating data integrity
and durability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the tricky part here is that availability is easy to
measure. &lt;a href="https://www.theregister.com/2018/07/19/data_durability_statements/"&gt;Data durability
isn’t&lt;/a&gt;. Therefore,
availability lends itself to becoming a target (hello, Professor
Strathern), and durability tends to be seen as difficult to measure
and hence less important (hello, Secretary McNamara).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, if you find yourself in charge of a system that you &lt;em&gt;suspect&lt;/em&gt;
has started to corrupt a significant fraction of customer data, data
which customers are pouring into it at an alarming rate, what do you
do?  You’re not sure whether there’s actual corruption yet. The proper
thing to do, if it’s impossible to rule out or fix the data corruption
problem immediately,&lt;sup id="fnref:immediately"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:immediately"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is probably to stop intake, and
also ensure that no requests are served that may touch potentially
corrupted data — that is, shut the service down even before you’ve
ascertained corruption. But if you suspect that your next bonus payout
or promotion may rely on you meeting your availability goals, and you
know you’re already shaving it close with your availability error
budget, would you really be inclined to do that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“You can’t manage what you don’t measure”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a popular saying in management circles that takes one of the
following forms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“If you can’t measure it, you can’t manage it.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“You can’t manage what you don’t measure.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“You can’t manage what you &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; measure.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whichever variant you discuss, it is commonly attributed to either
Austrian-American management thinker &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Drucker"&gt;Peter
Drucker&lt;/a&gt;, or to American
engineer and statistician &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W._Edwards_Deming"&gt;William Edwards
Deming&lt;/a&gt;. Drucker is
seen by many as highly influential in management theory, Deming
developed groundbreaking sampling techniques used on the massive scale
of the United States census. So either of them would be an authority
on management and measurement, lending high credibility to the
statement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s just a small problem: neither of them appears to ever have
said or written anything to that effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closest that &lt;a href="https://deming.org/myth-if-you-cant-measure-it-you-cant-manage-it/"&gt;one of them, Deming, ever
wrote&lt;/a&gt;
was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is wrong to suppose that if you can’t measure it, you can’t
manage it — a costly myth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—  W. Edwards Deming, “The New Economics for Industry, Government,
Education” (1993)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you didn’t notice, the point this makes is &lt;em&gt;the exact
opposite&lt;/em&gt; of the popular version of the quote. It’s so wrong that it
comes close to the corruption of the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger"&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt; lament, “non
vitæ sed scholæ discimus”, “we learn not for life but for school,” of
which you surely learned the inverse… in school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metrics-obsessed managers often take the misquote for gospel. So much
so that they frequently see issues where a qualitative approach is
obviously necessary, and they still try to apply quantification. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My standard example for this are employee satisfaction surveys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what leadership should be interested in learning from
those surveys is how good people feel about working in the
company. There are a number of factors that contribute to this: are
they overloaded, well utilized, or bored? Are people treating each
other with respect and kindness, or malice and contempt? Does everyone
feel that they are doing something meaningful, or do they all hate
their work and are solely in for the money? All these things are
inherently qualitative. And the company could do a great job by hiring
a person trained in sociology or psychology, who sits down with people
for confidential qualitative interviews, and then prepares a
research report with findings and recommendations that management can
act on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no, we have to measure. Make everyone take an online survey where
they rate everything on a scale of 1 to 5. Do you know what that is?
Exactly, step 2 on the Yankelovich ladder. Give that what can’t easily
be measured an arbitrary quantitative value — because that’s what it
is, arbitrary. People from different cultures won’t agree even on what
&lt;a href="https://measuringu.com/scales-cultural-effects/"&gt;a simple 5-step scale really
means&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And depending on &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; version of the faux quote they adhere to, a
manager may even be farther up the ladder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they say “you can’t manage what you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; measure” (with the
  translation being “I won’t concern myself with anything for which I
  don’t have quantitative data”): that’s step 3, blindness, that which
  isn’t measured isn’t important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they insist that “you can’t manage what you &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; measure”
  (with the translation being “I won’t concern myself with anything
  that isn’t quantifiable”): that’s step 4 (suicide), that which isn’t
  measured doesn’t exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So, what now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every article and book on bad metrics ends on a positive note, giving
you suggestions for “good” metrics: for example, make them hard to
game, make sure they are defined by competent experts, ensure that
they are in line with inherent ideas of respectability and
professionalism. Honestly, I’ve yet to come across a metric that ticks
all these boxes.&lt;sup id="fnref:game"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:game"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I am aware that if you are running a platform under an existing
SLA, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be running under some metrics of questionable utility
that you cannot get rid of — just because they happen to be industry
standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, instead of expanding metrics obsession to your entire
organization by introducing ever more counterproductive metrics, I
want to propose a different approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever you measure, make the &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; cost of a measurement
   negligeable.&lt;sup id="fnref:marginal"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:marginal"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The cost of adding a new metric should be
   practically zero. The moment someone has to repeatedly spend time
   on collecting and compiling the data, they can’t spend that time on
   doing productive work (and Campbell says hi), so you want to avoid
   that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This effectively means that all the systems you care about
   (machines, services, applications) should generate collectable data
   points, everywhere, all the time.&lt;sup id="fnref:privacy"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:privacy"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; And you probably won’t be
   collecting metrics from anything else. In other words, you are
   &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; measuring that which is easily measurable, and you keep
   aware that there a lot of things you don’t measure that are just as
   important. You stay on step one of the Yankelovich ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’d propose you make the data thus ingested available throughout
   your organization, in machine-readable form and using standardized
   APIs. You want people to actually &lt;em&gt;discover&lt;/em&gt; things from your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage people to use real, scientific, statistical methods to
   figure out statistical regularities (“indicators”). Offer
   statistics training to people who are interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once someone identifies a statistical regularity, encourage them to
   form an opinion of whether it would be beneficial for it to go up
   or down, formulate a hypothesis on what change to your system would
   have the desired effect, and conduct an experiment. If the
   experiment has no effect, roll back the change and proceed with the
   next hypothesis. If it has an adverse effect, roll back and try the
   opposite. If it has the desired effect, keep the change. Move on to
   discovering the next regularity. Resist the urge to make the
   discovery a target. (Otherwise, Strathern will drop
   by.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Constantly observe and identify things that are important, but not
   measurable. Apply qualitative analysis, emotion, and
   empathy. (Otherwise, McNamara will introduce himself.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is there anything inherently wrong with measuring or measurements?
Nope. But making them targets, introducing arbitrary quantifiers, and
ignoring everything else is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:why-goodhart"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason the condensed version is called
“Goodhart’s Law” and not “Strathern’s Law” is apparently due to a
coinage by British researcher Keith Hoskin, who wrote a year prior
to Strathern, in a paper she cited:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Goodhart’s Law” — that every measure which becomes a target becomes
a bad measure — is inexorably, if ruefully, becoming recognized as
one of the overriding laws of our time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Keith Hoskin, “The ‘awful idea of accountability’: inscribing
people into the measurement of objects” (1996)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:why-goodhart" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:creaming"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think that term sounds a bit odd, I’d agree. I
guess it comes from the idea of milking a cow and then skimming
only the cream, discarding the rest. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:creaming" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:tyranny"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surgery statistics example of creaming is paraphrased
from Jerry Z. Muller, “&lt;a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691174952/the-tyranny-of-metrics"&gt;The Tyranny of
Metrics&lt;/a&gt;”
(2018). &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:tyranny" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:lansdale"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lansdale/McNamara anecdote is paraphrased from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McNamara_fallacy"&gt;the
Wikipedia article on the McNamara
Fallacy&lt;/a&gt;, which in
turn cites Rufus Phillips and Richard Holbrooke, “Why Vietnam
Matters: An Eyewitness Account of Lessons Not Learned” (2008) as
its source. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:lansdale" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:oconnor"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that the SRE book is itself quoting a
definition of reliability found in Patrick P. O’Connor &amp;amp; Andre
Kleyner, “Practical Reliability Engineering” (2012). &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:oconnor" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:score"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The irony is not lost on me that by the definition quoted in
the SRE book, such a score absolutely &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; exist if its
definition of reliability were adequate: it claims to be a
probability. Probabilities go from 0 to 1. That would make site
reliability a dimensionless quantity between 0 and 1, end of
story. But it goes without saying that such a score would be “an
arbitrary quantitative value”, which would put it on step 2 of the
Yankelovich ladder. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:score" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:hash"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That hash would have to be separately stored &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; the
system. If the hash is stored &lt;em&gt;alongside&lt;/em&gt; the data whose
integrity it’s meant to protect, then it only guards against
unintentional data corruption, but not against deliberate
manipulation. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:hash" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:timetravel"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish to point out that the only bit that’s impossible
here is the backwards time travel. The forwards time travel is
fine, we all travel forwards in time all the time, just at a
constant rate of one second per second. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:timetravel" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:immediately"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve run into a few issues of suspected silent data
corruption in my career and I’ve &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been in the situation
where a reliable fix was available immediately. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:immediately" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:game"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, pretty much any real-world metric fails the
“hard to game” test. Said &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/lukasgrossar/status/1267830321057107969"&gt;Lukas Grossar on
Twitter&lt;/a&gt;:
“It always amazes me that people don’t believe that slapping a KPI
onto something won’t lead to people gaming that KPI. We’re
engineers for God sake, making broken stuff work in our favor is
basically our job description.” &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:game" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:privacy"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that this requires strong privacy guarantees for
your users/customers. Effectively, just don’t collect data that’s
none of your business. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:privacy" title="Jump back to footnote 11 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:marginal"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emphasis on marginal. It’s obvious that the &lt;em&gt;fixed&lt;/em&gt;
cost of building and maintaining an instrumentation platform and
metric system is nonzero. But once you’ve got it set up, the cost
of &lt;em&gt;adding a new metric&lt;/em&gt; should be substantially zero. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:marginal" title="Jump back to footnote 12 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Warnock’s Dilemma, Objections, and Acknowledgements</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/30/warnock-dilemma/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-10-30:/blog/2021/10/30/warnock-dilemma/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Warnock’s Dilemma” is a classic feature of distributed, asynchronous, online communications. You can’t avoid it, you can’t work around it, but you can deal with it with two simple changes to your communicative behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;People skeptical of distributed, asynchronous, written communications
sometimes make they understandable objection that it is often
difficult to interpret the reactions, specifically the &lt;em&gt;absence of&lt;/em&gt;
reactions, to written online communications. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasoning goes like this: if you inform someone of something in a
face-to-face conversation, there is practically no way for them &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
to provide some sort of feedback. Even if the recipient of a verbal
message doesn’t say a word, they usually exhibit some unconscious,
nonverbal reaction, which can carry a whole load of information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person might smile, light up, and become actively engaged,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they might express surprise (pleasant or unpleasant),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they may show signs of dismay or annoyance, or even anger,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they might just stare or wander off, indicating disconnection or
  indifference,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or anything in between.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In online, textual communications, people obviously &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; exhibit all
those reactions, sitting at their desk, lounging on their couch,
walking with their phone — it’s just that the sender of the message
usually never gets to see them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, a face-to-face conversation is a one-to-one communication
mode that we direct our undivided attention to. In contrast, textual
online communications are often many-to-many, and we usually get many
more parallel inputs than we do when we’re speaking to a colleague or
acquaintance or friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that while in a face-to-face conversation we’re &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt;
answering, or at least showing our reaction to what was said, in online
textual communications we must &lt;em&gt;pick and choose&lt;/em&gt; what to react to, and
what to just absorb without providing any kind of feedback to the
message sender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Warnock’s Dilemma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In online communities this has been known since at least 2000, when
Bryan Warnock
&lt;a href="https://www.nntp.perl.org/group/perl.bootstrap/2000/08/msg1127.html"&gt;formulated&lt;/a&gt;
it as “the ostrich theory”, although it eventually &lt;a href="https://www.nntp.perl.org/group/perl.perl6.internals/2001/02/msg2562.html"&gt;was
named&lt;/a&gt;
“Warnock’s Dilemma”&lt;sup id="fnref:pentalemma"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:pentalemma"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; by Dave Mitchell. Writing about
mailing list posts without replies, Bryan wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with no response is that there are five possible
interpretations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) The post is correct, well-written information that needs no
follow-up commentary.  There’s nothing more to say except “Yeah,
what he said.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) The post is complete and utter nonsense, and no one wants to
waste the energy or bandwidth to even point this out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) No one read the post, for whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4) No one understood the post, but won’t ask for clarification, for
whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5) No one cares about the post, for whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Bryan Warnock, “&lt;a href="https://www.nntp.perl.org/group/perl.bootstrap/2000/08/msg1127.html"&gt;Re: RFCs: two proposals for
change&lt;/a&gt;”,
perl.bootstrap mailing list, 2000-08-07&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In asynchronous and distributed work communications, we have much the
same issue. The beautifully crafted &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/27/this-meeting-should-have-been-an-email/"&gt;five-paragraph
briefing&lt;/a&gt; that
you sent out this morning may have been considered manna from heaven
by your recipients (if you’re a manager, your recipients are usually
your direct reports), and they immediately sprung into action
energized by your electrifying leadership. Or maybe nobody understood
a word of the unintelligible drivel you concocted, but out of respect
or courtesy they are very hesitant to point this out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in my humble opinion, there are two very simple things you can do
as a manager to address Warnock’s Dilemma in your distributed team:
making it a habit to specifically encourage objections, and
establishing a culture of acknowledgements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Encouraging objections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The habit I have developed to encourage objections is to not merely
ask the recipients of a message to raise questions if they have them,
but to ask them to poke holes in whatever I’ve been writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To that end, I have standing phrases that I use, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Do you think that sounds reasonable?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Did I overlook something important?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Can you think of a better way to do this?” (Better than my
  suggestion, that is.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I’m pretty sure I’m missing something here, can you pitch in?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Am I way out in left field with this?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“How nuts of an idea is this?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might use a variation on one or several of these phrases at the end
of an email, but also in the comments section of a wiki page (or in
individual inline comments), or even in the reply thread of an issue
tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This serves multiple purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are many individual areas of knowledge where someone on my
   team is more of an expert than I am. Obviously, I want those
   people’s ideas on the table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It establishes the notion that nobody’s opinions or suggestions on
   technical matters are sacrosanct, and we want to do &lt;em&gt;the right
   thing&lt;/em&gt; in any situation, not follow the hippo.&lt;sup id="fnref:hippo"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:hippo"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It encourages others to ask for feedback in the same manner,
   whenever they float ideas or suggestions of their own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It establishes that there’s nothing wrong with being wrong from
   time to time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, on to acknowledgements, that is, what to do when you have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;
objections on something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a general rule that I use: &lt;strong&gt;all communications should be
acknowledged.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, really. Anything my team sends me, I try to reply
to with at least “ack” or “OK”, but frequently it’s something like
“great, thanks!” — it costs nothing to be kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, for everything I send &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; my team I can count on getting
the same kind of reply back. There’s something I need to pass on from
higher up? Or just something I want everyone to know? Out goes an
email, in come a few “ack” replies over the next few hours. I don’t
even have to specifically ask anyone for acknowledgement anymore, it
just happens.&lt;sup id="fnref:guidelines"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:guidelines"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this context, we deliberately use &lt;em&gt;written&lt;/em&gt; acknowledgements — as
in, somebody actually &lt;em&gt;types&lt;/em&gt; something, even if it’s just the two
letters “OK”. I find Like buttons or thumbs-up or email “read
receipts” (anyone remember those?) oddly perfunctory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has a nice side effect, in combination with encouraging
objections: someone who — while knowing that objections are always
encouraged — acknowledges an idea, opinion, or plan, &lt;em&gt;actually makes
it clear that they are on board with it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:pentalemma"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To his credit, Dave points out in the same
message that “dilemma” is technically inappropriate as the problem
described includes five choices, not two. It’s properly a
&lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pentalemma"&gt;pentalemma&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:pentalemma" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:hippo"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HiPPO: the Highest-Paid Person’s Opinion. Following the
hippo is when you value ideas and opinions by seniority of their
originator, not by correctness or factual merit. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:hippo" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:guidelines"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve also codified this in my team’s communications
guidelines. You don’t have something like that? Write them. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:guidelines" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>This Meeting Should Have Been an Email</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/27/this-meeting-should-have-been-an-email/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-10-27:/blog/2021/10/27/this-meeting-should-have-been-an-email/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you believe that it’s just a silly joke or an overused trope, please read this.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fellow managers, there is an ongoing trope in just about any software
technology or knowledge based organization (and probably others, too)
that goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This meeting should have been an email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s such a well-established meme at this point that you &lt;a href="https://www.redbubble.com/shop/i+survived+another+meeting+that+should+have+been+an+email+mugs"&gt;can buy mugs
saying
so&lt;/a&gt;. Or
&lt;a href="https://www.etsy.com/au/listing/737148259/i-survived-another-meeting-that-could"&gt;cross-stitched “award
certificates”&lt;/a&gt;,
or
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/pics/comments/8z31wz/office_participation/"&gt;ribbons&lt;/a&gt;. And
yet, many of you appear to dismiss it as a nerdy joke, and refuse to
take the sentiment behind it seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this even though you may &lt;em&gt;agree&lt;/em&gt; that your organization has too
many meetings.  Even that &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; are in too many meetings. But you’re
convinced that sadly, sadly you can’t cancel &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; meeting. Or that
one. Or the quarterly financials update. Or the update about the
shakeup in the CTO office. Or the meeting explaining at &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; level
what the CEO just communicated to everyone via a video message or an
email of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can do it. I’m here to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“Email” means any structured, written communication that allows for feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s set one thing straight to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standing phrase is “this meeting should have been an email”
because that’s catchy. But that’s not to say that you actually need to
write an email message. What it really means is that to communicate
whatever it is that you’re trying to get across, you use a medium that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uses written expression,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allows you to formulate complex thoughts and reasoning in writing,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allows people to comment and share feedback, in writing,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ideally allows for that feedback to subsequently be worked back into
   the original writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll see that particularly considering item #4, email isn’t even the
best option available at your disposal. Instead, you can look at the
following, additional options, all of which will probably be available
to you in some form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a shared flow-text document, like a &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/a/users/answer/9310248?hl=en#6.3"&gt;Google Doc&lt;/a&gt;, a collaboratively edited
  &lt;a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/collaborate-on-word-documents-with-real-time-co-authoring-7dd3040c-3f30-4fdd-bab0-8586492a1f1d"&gt;Office 365 Word
  document&lt;/a&gt;,
  or a &lt;a href="https://nextcloud.com/blog/nextcloud-introduces-collaborative-rich-text-editor/"&gt;Nextcloud
  Text&lt;/a&gt;
  document,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a page in your organization’s wiki, like
  &lt;a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/MediaWiki"&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt; or
  &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/confluence"&gt;Confluence&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or even a barebones shared text editor, like
  &lt;a href="https://etherpad.org/"&gt;Etherpad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all of these are good.&lt;sup id="fnref:chat"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:chat"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All of them are better than a meeting. With
near certainty at least one of them is available at your disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meetings burn people’s time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings are gigantic time consumers. And the productivity gains from
switching to well-structured written communications are &lt;strong&gt;enormous&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate, allow me to offer some first-hand experience. When I’m
being called to attend a meeting, my colleagues will attest to the
fact that I am a meticulous note-taker. I write meetings up in our
corporate wiki, and I record notes, rather than producing a verbatim
transcript. But I can guarantee you that I will write down every point
that the attendees make that’s worth remembering or referring back
to. This includes some key points that I do record word-for-word. I’ve
been in meetings with 20 attendees of 1 hour in length. My meeting
notes &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; go over 2,000 words for such a meeting, and usually
they’re more like 1,000 words. So that means that for a meeting that
burns 20 person-hours &lt;em&gt;just to attend&lt;/em&gt; (that is, not including meeting
prep), what actually gets said can be summarized in 2,000 words, tops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, consider that &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0749596X19300786"&gt;the average silent reading rate for English
speakers&lt;/a&gt;
is approximately 240 words per minute. So people can read a 2,000-word
summary in under 9 minutes, a 1,000 word one in about 4. In other
words, by conveying the information in writing rather than orally, you
can eliminate five-sixths to fourteen-fifteenths of that useless
overhead. Or put differently, &lt;strong&gt;replacing an hourlong meeting with a
well-written briefing gives each and every person 6 to 15 times more
productivity.&lt;/strong&gt; And that’s not even counting the benefits of
eliminating the meeting as a forced synchronization point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But writing things up means more work for me!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may argue that although you understand that putting together a
well-written briefing (instead of calling a meeting) saves everyone
&lt;em&gt;else&lt;/em&gt; time, it takes up more of &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me observe this: If you’ve been convening and chairing meetings of
an hour, and you haven’t been spending &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; as much time preparing
for that meeting yourself, then I’m sorry to break it you but you may
not have been a very conscientious meeting chair all along. In fact,
you may have be been rather disrespectful of other people’s time, and
now is a very good time for you to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If however you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; been a conscientious meeting chair and every
one-hour meeting did, in aggregate, consume about one hour of meeting
prep (including scheduling, collecting information, and preparing it
so you have it all ready to go), then rejoice: the onerous
scheduling-and-roping-everyone-in bit is gone, so that saves up a
sizable chunk of &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; time, and you can punch out 1,000 to 2,000
words in 30-45 minutes. So, &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; work for you. Admittedly, not as
dramatically so for you (the writer) as for your erstwhile attendees
(now readers), but still pretty substantial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Not to mention the fact that &lt;em&gt;team&lt;/em&gt; productivity gains in the
order-of-magnitude range, see above, should make your heart jump with
joy.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OK but how? I don’t know where to start!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;I’ve written about this
before&lt;/a&gt;, but I’d
like to come back to this again: if you’re looking for guidelines on
structuring your writing for what you would otherwise communicate in
your meetings, look at the 5-paragraph briefing format, adapted from
the NATO &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_paragraph_order"&gt;5-paragraph field
order&lt;/a&gt;. If you
make it your habit to at least &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about this format, chances are
that your briefing will be pretty damn comprehensive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Objective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s break these down in a little detail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Situation is about what position we’re in, and &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; we set out
   to do what we want to do. You can break this down into three
   sub-points, like the customer’s situation, the situation of your
   own company, any extra help that is available, and the current
   market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Objective is &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; we want to achieve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan is &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; we want to achieve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistics is about what budget and resources are available, and how
   we can use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communications is about how we’ll be coordinating among ourselves
   and with others in order to achieve our goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you want to give not a full briefing, but a simple update,
such as because circumstances have changed. In that case, you may only
include the first three items, and the changes that apply to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s good practice to &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; include these three (that is,
situation, objective, and plan): to &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; it may be clear and obvious
that since the situation has changed, a slight modification of the
plan (or the objective!) is necessary. To others, it might not. So
just always include the current situation, the current objectives, and
the current plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also apply this to a problem statement, where it’s just as
useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is what we’re currently dealing with, and how I see it (that’s
   the &lt;em&gt;situation&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here’s why it’s a problem, and why it needs to be fixed (that’s an
   &lt;em&gt;objective&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is my suggestion for how it could be fixed (that’s a &lt;em&gt;plan&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And finally, some poetry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as my final writing tip for improving communications and
eliminating needless meetings, I want to leave you with some
poetry. These lines that just so happen to serve as a perfect mnemonic
for professional briefings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep six honest serving-men:&lt;br/&gt;
(They taught me all I knew)&lt;br/&gt;
Their names are What and Where and When&lt;br/&gt;
And How and Why and Who.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Rudyard Kipling, The Elephant’s Child, 1902&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strive for all your professional writing to answer most or all of
&lt;em&gt;what,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;where,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;when,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;how,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;why,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;who,&lt;/em&gt; and watch your need
for meetings evaporate like morning dew in glistening sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:chat"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that interactive chat (like Slack) is not in this
list. It fails the “formulate complex thoughts and reasoning”
test. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:chat" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Please, Make My Company Distributed!</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/23/make-my-company-distributed/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-10-23:/blog/2021/10/23/make-my-company-distributed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Turning an organization into one that works in a distributed and asynchronous fashion is far from trivial.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;No, We Won’t Have a Video Call for
That&lt;/a&gt;, which
covered how productive distributed teams operate, and the &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/"&gt;Getting out
of Meeting Hell&lt;/a&gt; series,
which focused on how &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; as an individual can get to being a member
of a functional distributed team, let’s zoom out a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s discuss a slightly larger, organizational picture, just in case
you ask yourself this question: “&lt;strong&gt;Why isn’t my organization
distributed and asynchronous?&lt;/strong&gt; And, as companies &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28833394"&gt;bleed talent right
and left&lt;/a&gt; because
competent people run for the competition that &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; get distributed
work right, why don’t they wake up and &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; like that?  &lt;strong&gt;Can
someone please make my company more distributed and asynchronous?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For additional context, let me interject the following observations
from &lt;a href="https://blog.koehntopp.info/"&gt;Kris Köhntopp&lt;/a&gt;, who posted them
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1451497494303711234"&gt;in German on
Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (I am
taking the liberty to translate here; emphasis mine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s funny is that [what matters to being successful as a
distributed company] are all learnable skills — written
communications, sensible meeting prep and follow-up, correct
definition of objectives and tasks, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s a craft.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it appears that organizations prefer to bleed their teams dry by
attrition, rather than to learn, or to hire people that can help
teams to write things down, professionally maintain a wiki, and
teach and drive communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/isotopp/status/1451508098779258889"&gt;further
downthread&lt;/a&gt;,
Kris says (again, my translation and emphasis):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all definitely feasible, after all there’s remote-first
companies of substantial size and they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They must have &lt;strong&gt;built&lt;/strong&gt; themselves somehow, they didn’t get to
where they are by pure chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with all of that (obviously), but things are complicated. So
let’s drill into this a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building is easy. Changing is hard.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve founded and bootstrapped a distributed company, and I’ve also
been involved in making a localized company more distributed. Take my
word for it: founding was daunting and scary and stressful, but in
terms of shaping structure and communications — even if you have to
figure it out as you go, as I did with my cofounders&lt;sup id="fnref:invent"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:invent"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; — it’s &lt;em&gt;easy.&lt;/em&gt;
Changing the communication structure of an established company is
&lt;em&gt;hard.&lt;/em&gt; And slow. Even if you have full support from the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you’re in an organization that wasn’t distributed from the
get-go, do not compare it to one that was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, do not compare it to one that is two years ahead of yours in
reshaping itself in a distributed and asynchronous manner. Also, if
your company went distributed kicking and screaming at the start of
the pandemic, do not compare it to one where the top leadership made a
conscious decision to be more “remote friendly” or “remote first” or
whatever their preferred term is, long before the pandemic hit. These
organizations are ahead of yours. Their change may be happening just
as slowly as yours, they just started the race earlier and are a
couple of laps ahead of you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But your company hasn’t even &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt; the change to distributed and
async work? You spent the last nearly two years in unfettered meeting
hell?  Your bosses think you’ll now go “back to normal”, because an
office is the only “normal” they know? &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/01/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-employees/"&gt;You know what to
do.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hiring people to help: aye, there’s the rub.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now on to the idea of hiring people to help. There’s two ways to look
at that: hiring people as employed &lt;strong&gt;managers&lt;/strong&gt; to work and lead in
the organization in a distributed and async fashion, or hiring people
as management &lt;strong&gt;consultants&lt;/strong&gt; to guide and advise the company in the
distributed and async transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Please note: the idea of hiring only &lt;em&gt;regular employees&lt;/em&gt; that drive a
distributed and async change “from within” — against the resistance or
inertia of established management — is ludicrous, unethical, and
unworkable.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hiring distie managers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make it a priority to hire managers geared toward distributed and
asynchronous work, then if they’re worth their salt I can guarantee you
that one of the first things that they’ll ask in their first interview
is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What’s &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; line manager’s (director’s, VP’s, etc) distributed and
async work experience? How about my lateral peers’?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if the truthful answer is “they’re new to this,” it’s quite likely
that your prospective new management colleague will politely end the
conversation. Their skills are in high demand; they have plenty of
options to go elsewhere. Why should sign they up for a job that’s
going to come with a ton of needless friction?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, that consideration applies in all management positions,
all the way to the top. So for this to work, in an organization
currently hellbent on localized-synchronized work (I use
&lt;em&gt;offissification&lt;/em&gt; for that state of affairs), it would need at least
its entire
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporate_title#Senior_management"&gt;C-suite&lt;/a&gt;
to come around first. And it would then &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; need to replace at
least one-third of its current managers at all levels, to have any
chance of attracting fresh blood in management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that this isn’t exactly easy to do, plus it’ll probably
take longer than you have the patience to put up with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hiring management consultants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that leaves the option of hiring people that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; part of the
organization but are brought in to advise, ideally on all management
levels. These people are called management consultants. And you should
understand that they are commonly &lt;em&gt;loathed&lt;/em&gt; by mid-level line
managers. But let’s leave that aside for now. Let’s assume that you
want to consider the possibility of a management consultant whose
communication skills and empathy and talent are so outstanding that
they are absolutely not hated by anybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, please put yourself in that consultant’s shoes. Before they get
anywhere near you, they would have spent countless hours in — you
guessed it — &lt;em&gt;meetings&lt;/em&gt; with the CEO, with top-level management,
possibly with department heads, to get &lt;em&gt;buy-in&lt;/em&gt;. And then, they embark
on a multi-month project where they must use the style of work
currently prevalent in your company, because that’s the only way to
even approach people. So they spend more time in — are you with me —
&lt;em&gt;meetings&lt;/em&gt; to convince and educate people. Oh, and they probably need
to bill by the day or by the hour, in some arbitrary increment that
your bean counters dictate, because otherwise they can’t get
paid. Async work, on your own time and schedule, much?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that means that under most circumstances, such a project will
either involve a person who’s actually perfectly fine with localized
and synchronous work, and for this kind of project that’s &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt;
not a person you’d want to hire. Or else they’re miserably
unproductive throughout the project, and that doesn’t exactly bode
well for their health &lt;em&gt;nor&lt;/em&gt; your project. (Which means a person
understanding this probably will never start such a consultancy in the
first place.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I want to mention that I suppose from the perspective of a
consultant, there is one way to square this circle: charge exorbitant
rates. If you can make a killing working two days a month, and you
actually &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; work just two days of meeting hell per month and take
the rest of your time off to recuperate, then that might actually
work. But then it’s less likely — not impossible, but less likely —
that your company will retain their services. Because unlike a
consultant that you bring in to chop heads, monetary gains (that is,
return on investment for the consultant’s fees) are much more
difficult to put in numbers when you’re “only” making everyone’s life
better, and attracting better employees, increasing productivity,
building better products, attracting more customers, and hence making
a bigger profit are mere knock-on effects from that.&lt;sup id="fnref:rational"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:rational"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So, how do things change, then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s my rather firm belief that these things change by evolution, not
on an organizational scale but on one of market and society. &lt;strong&gt;Many of
the companies still stuck in the office mindset will not change,&lt;/strong&gt; at
least not dramatically. They will continue to bleed talent, not
attract much fresh blood, and face fierce competition from companies
that do better and attract good people. Some will undergo a slow and
sometimes painful transition and some will succeed at it. Some will
fail and go under, or become irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But expecting dramatic, sudden change at a large organization is just
not realistic. And if you’re stuck in one that’s still pretending that
this’ll all blow over, your best option is probably to make a change
for yourself, than to try to wait for one in your organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:invent"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that we &lt;em&gt;invented&lt;/em&gt; anything, just that
we had to figure out how to make things work for ourselves that
already worked for others. Distributed
companies existed well before my cofounders and I started a
company in 2011. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MySQL_AB"&gt;MySQL
AB&lt;/a&gt; (incidentally, Kris
Köhntopp’s former employer) established those practices in the
2000-2005 time frame. There is an excellent &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/2xmEgtRhw7o"&gt;November 2011
talk&lt;/a&gt; from ex-MySQL CEO Mårten
Mickos, in which he runs through the entire history of MySQL as an
independent company, until its acquisition by Sun in 2008. &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/2xmEgtRhw7o?t=1653"&gt;Around
the 27-minute mark&lt;/a&gt;, he
starts talking about work in a distributed company. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:invent" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:rational"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;even if&lt;/em&gt; there is a demonstrable expected positive
&lt;em&gt;monetary&lt;/em&gt; effect, meaning in terms of numbers it’s an absolute
no-brainer, you should consider that top management &lt;em&gt;are people,&lt;/em&gt;
and people don’t always act rationally. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:rational" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>No, We Won’t Have a Video Call for That: The Companion Pieces</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that-the-companion-pieces/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-10-23:/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that-the-companion-pieces/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;The original article&lt;/a&gt; continues to prompt a
lot of thoughts and discussions, so I’ve written a a couple of
follow-up pieces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/"&gt;Getting out of Meeting
   Hell&lt;/a&gt; is a
   short series about getting from a distributed workplace that
   attempts to duplicate the synchronous nature of an office by
   sticking everyone …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;The original article&lt;/a&gt; continues to prompt a
lot of thoughts and discussions, so I’ve written a a couple of
follow-up pieces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/"&gt;Getting out of Meeting
   Hell&lt;/a&gt; is a
   short series about getting from a distributed workplace that
   attempts to duplicate the synchronous nature of an office by
   sticking everyone into video meetings all the time — with usually
   disastrous results — to one that successfully adopts an
   asynchronous way of working. It has suggestions for employees,
   mid-level managers, and executives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/23/make-my-company-distributed/"&gt;Please, make my company
   distributed!&lt;/a&gt;
   takes a broader view on changing organizations so that they become
   better suited for a distributed and asynchronous style of work, and
   why that’s a lot harder than most people think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category><category term="Conference"></category><category term="Communications"></category><category term="Work"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting out of Meeting Hell: As a top-level executive</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/03/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-executives/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-10-03:/blog/2021/10/03/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-executives/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short series on transitioning to distributed work and asynchronous collaboration. This article is on what you can do if you are stuck in meeting hell as a top-level executive, such as a CEO, Managing Director, or Executive Director.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please have a look at the
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/"&gt;introduction&lt;/a&gt; for
background, for applicable disclaimers, and for information about
the specific environments this series talks about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part of this series is for you if you are a chief executive
officer, a managing director, executive director, or whatever else the
top-level role in your organization may be. This means that you have
people who report to you, but you don’t report to anyone in the
day-to-day operations of the company — even though you may, of course,
be answerable to your board of directors or your investors, or some
oversight body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you realize that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a lot of your company spends a lot of time in useless meetings,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they’re often forced to sit through 90 minutes of staring into
  cameras when they could instead have spent 5 minutes reading an email,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people’s productivity suffers badly because they are constantly
  being interrupted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is badly affecting you, personally, as well. So for the
benefit of yourself and everyone else in the organization, you want to
change things toward being less interrupt-driven, less synchronous,
more productive, and healthier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ve got &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; bad news for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In contrast to your employees at any level, it is much harder for
   you to pull the &lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt; option than it is for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In contrast to most of your mid-level managers, no matter how hard
   you try, you may &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; escape being in a lot of meetings, and
   being in a lot of &lt;em&gt;unpleasant&lt;/em&gt; meetings to boot. Chances are, whenever
   stuff is exploding, boiling up, or otherwise going bonkers, you’ll
   be roped in to calm things down, make a decision, or soothe a
   high-profile customer who is conniptiously trying to convince you
   that your SLA is akin to the Constitution and that an engineer
   guilty of causing a violation ought to hang for treason.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, and this is the good news to balance the bad, if you manage to
pull the &lt;em&gt;rest&lt;/em&gt; of the company out of meeting hell, life is going to
get way better for &lt;em&gt;you,&lt;/em&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, obviously, there’ll be a lot for you to &lt;strong&gt;Learn&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’ve never
led an organization that was distributed and asynchronous by default,
there’s a lot to unpack, understand, and overcome when it comes to
turning one that &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt;, into one that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But your most important role at the top of the organization is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lead.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And by that I mean lead by example, and also lead by policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few ways you can lead by example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write. Particularly when you want to communicate something to the
  whole company. All-hands video streams? &lt;em&gt;[stage whisper]&lt;/em&gt; Everyone
  hates those. Meeting invites saying “we’ll anounce something
  important”? Just write an email &lt;em&gt;saying the important thing,&lt;/em&gt; and
  then ask people to send you questions by a deadline. And publicly
  commit &lt;em&gt;yourself&lt;/em&gt; to a deadline by which they can expect answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take no shortcuts. If you’re setting up communications rules for
  everyone, live by them yourself. &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/16/rules-are-rules/"&gt;There’s a bad, hidden cost in
  skirting around them.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a point of always giving context when pinging someone in chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quit calling people without warning — you can’t convey the &lt;em&gt;context&lt;/em&gt;
  of the call without them answering. A cold call is the ultimate
  &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/No_naked_pings"&gt;naked ping&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, cut back on synchronous, realtime communications. They
  always interrupt people, and &lt;a href="https://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/"&gt;interruptions are
  expensive&lt;/a&gt;. Think
  about how much money you’ll lose from someone &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; having a
  brilliant idea because you pinged them about some technicality in
  the company chat while they were deeply immersed in a complex
  problem. (Also, think about how much money you might &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; already
  lost that way.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insist on agendas being drawn up and meeting notes being kept (and
  both &lt;em&gt;circulated&lt;/em&gt; to anyone who needs the information) for every
  meeting you are asked to attend. Write an agenda for every meeting
  you call or chair. If you have a group that meets regularly, appoint a
  different person from the group as a scribe each time. Do not ask a
  person to volunteer. (If you do, chances are that one person in the
  group will be typecast as the scribe for all such meetings. I call
  such an unfortunate person a &lt;em&gt;scrapegoat.&lt;/em&gt; You don’t want
  scrapegoats.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, here are ways you can lead by policy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hire professional writers. (In the software industry, tech writers
  come to mind.) Not because you want &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; people to be
  scrapegoats, but because professional writers can massively move
  your organization forward in efficiency of written expression,
  document organization, and clarity of communications. Make them a
  hiring priority. Pay them handsomely — good tech writers can make
  good money freelancing; you’ll need to make them a pretty compelling
  offer to consider giving up some of that freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ram a stake in the ground making clear to everyone you will not
  tolerate corporate surveillance or invasions of privacy. Any attempt
  to introduce an “always on camera” policy should be grounds for
  reprimanding the manager that instigated it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insist on the procurement of tools that take distributed,
  asynchronous work into account. A video conferencing system that
  values surveillance over privacy is not one your company should
  throw money at. A hiring platform that requires specifying an
  “office location” for every role, and has no provisions for remote
  positions, isn’t either. Neither is a chat platform hosted by a
  company whose sole chance at long-term success is to pull &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
  corporate communications into synchronous chat. Yes, these judgments
  require technical expertise. If this is something you don’t have
  because you consider yourself a “non-technical” person, &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2019/04/21/non-technical/"&gt;I have
  something to read for you&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another thing that you &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be inclined toward doing:
declaring meeting-free days, as in making it a policy that no meetings
are to be scheduled on Wednesdays. I think of that as very much a
stop-gap measure that’s often done out of sheer despair. Sure, you
want your people to have meeting-free days, but you actually want them
to have &lt;em&gt;meeting days,&lt;/em&gt; with meetingless days being the norm, rather
than the exception. I think you’re better off gradually replacing your
meeting-addicted managers with ones that are accustomed to distributed
and asynchronous work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, and this may be a bitter pill to swallow: getting to
distributed and asynchronous is infinitely harder if you have built a
“flat” organization. If every one of your managers has 20-30 direct
reports, they will feel utterly overwhelmed at the thought of staying
in asynchronous communication with every one of them, not to mention
the fact that it’s damn near impossible for them to convince that many
people at one time to adopt a new way of collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the many, many ways in which &lt;a href="https://getlighthouse.com/blog/flat-organizational-structure-fails/"&gt;flat organizations fail
to
scale&lt;/a&gt;,
but this gives you the opportunity to fix two issues at the same
time. If you’ve got one manager that’s actively promoting meeting hell
that is currently making life miserable for 20 people, you can split
that team up into 4, and hire 3 team leads that know how to work
asynchronously and distributed (or promote people who have that sort
of experience and want to step up). Then, in the one remaining team
with the unreformed meeting addict, things can go three ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The one “traditional” team sees how things go in the other teams,
  and they quickly coax their team lead into doing things the new way, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they all ask to be transferred, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(the worst-case scenario) the one meeting-addicted manager continues
  to annoy everyone, and they all leave. That’s bad, and a failure of
  judgment (that manager should probably have been let go first), but
  losing 4 good people, as difficult as that might be, is probably
  “better” than losing 20.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final thought, &lt;em&gt;please&lt;/em&gt; take a moment to put yourself in other
people’s shoes, and understand what options &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; have with being
stuck in meeting hell. Whether it’s your &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/02/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-managers/"&gt;line
managers&lt;/a&gt; or your
regular
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/01/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-employees/"&gt;employees&lt;/a&gt;, they
both have the option to just chuck in their notice and leave, and
leave they will, if they’re sufficiently deep in meeting hell. They
have plenty of opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So lead by example, and lead by policy. Do things right, but more
importantly do the right things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article concludes the series — for now. I am guessing that
people reading this will have opinions, air their grievances, and
share feedback. Those usually give me good thinking material to
dwell on, so I’ll probably have an additional installment based on
reader feedback at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting out of Meeting Hell: As a mid-level manager</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/02/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-managers/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-10-02:/blog/2021/10/02/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-managers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short series on transitioning to distributed work and asynchronous collaboration. This article is on what you can do if you are stuck in meeting hell as a mid-level manager.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please have a look at the
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/"&gt;introduction&lt;/a&gt; for
background, for applicable disclaimers, and for information about
the specific environments this series talks about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part of this series is for you if you are a manager at any level
of your organization &lt;em&gt;except the very top.&lt;/em&gt; In other words, you have
reports, but you also report to someone. And as such you may be stuck
in meeting hell in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With your own team, that is to say, yourself and the people
   reporting to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With your management peers, in other words, the people that manage
   other teams and report to the same director, VP, or whatever other
   fancy titles your company might use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’ll cover both of those angles, but before I do, I should note
that you, of course, have one option to improve your personal
situation that is &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/01/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-employees/"&gt;also available to your
reports&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;strong&gt;Leave.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s not the only option you have, and it may not be your
&lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; option, but an option it is. And, for your personal
development, taking on a management role in a company that does
distributed work and asynchronous communications right might be an
excellent career move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a conscientious manager and you feel a sense of
responsibility and obligation to your team, and this makes you
hesitate to consider the option to leave, then that reflects nobly on
your character but know this: that responsibility is contigent on
everyone’s employment in one organization, and it ends the day your
employment contract (or theirs) terminates. That may sound harsh, but
that’s the breaks of the game, and you shouldn’t let that hold you up,
if leaving is the objectively most sensible option for you. There’s no
use burning out over an exaggerated sense of duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I’d posit that you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; leave your company if it
employs or promotes employee surveillance, keeps voodoo “meeting
engagement metrics”, or engages in otherwise harmful or toxic
behavior. I’d argue that in those cases you should also make sure your
direct reports know why you’re leaving, to the extent that your
contractual obligations allow you to tell them.&lt;sup id="fnref:non-disparagement"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:non-disparagement"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you’ve chosen &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to leave your current organization,
and you want to actually do the hard work for making work
&lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; for yourself and your distributed team, here is your
paramount obligation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learn.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there’s anything that the coronavirus pandemic has shown about
organizations making the (admittedly abrupt) transition from localized
to distributed work, it’s this: it’s a challenge for managers much
more than for non-manager employees. You have to make a conscious
effort to learn how distributed work works, and how you manage a
distributed team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, chances are that you won’t be limited to watching talks or
listening to podcasts or reading articles (you might have &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;read this
one&lt;/a&gt; before you
landed here). Instead, it’s not unlikely that if you’re doing software
or technology development, some of the people on your team are already
well versed in distributed collaboration and asynchronous
communications. Yes, I am of course talking about open source
contributors. It absolutely does not matter &lt;em&gt;what kind&lt;/em&gt; of open source
software some on your team have worked or helped out on, or whether
it’s in any way related to the products your company builds. Everyone
who’s ever landed a pull request probably has had to learn more about
distributed, async communications than any office dweller did who
never has. Find those people. Talk to them. Learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll also have peers in the industry, outside your company. Managers
who’ve already done the work. They can’t do the &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; for you,
but they can you show a few tricks of the trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’ll give you one, straight away: in a company stuck in Meeting
Hell, you change things for your team first, and don’t even think
about people at or above your level.  I would not advise taking your
ideas up the chain without the confidence of knowing that what you are
suggesting works in &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; team. Mid-level management is unfortunately
often full of “great idea, but it’ll never work here” or “that might
sound nice, but I’m afraid it doesn’t fit our culture.” You want to
run silent, run deep (if you permit me a strained metaphor). When your
team lands its first great big success, &lt;em&gt;that’s&lt;/em&gt; when you casually
want to drop something like “we did this on one meeting a week.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how can you get there? Here are a few ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliminate daily standups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limit yourself to one scheduled team meeting a week. Keep it to
  approximately one hour, give or take a few minutes. Schedule it near
  the start of the work week (meaning, in most countries, on Monday).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have an agenda for your team meeting (and &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; other meetings) that
  is available in a collaboratively editable document,
  cross-referencing all open tasks. Have this agenda in a place where
  everyone can find it, and have it ready no later than 15 minutes
  prior to the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the meeting, transform the agenda into your meeting
  notes. This is something a collaboratively editable document (like a
  wiki page or Google Doc) makes easy. Appoint a responsible
  note-taker or scribe, whose job it is to compile the meeting notes,
  edit minor glitches and errors, and then let you know the notes are
  ready for consumption. You may decide that &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; who is in the
  meeting can co-edit the notes, and this can be very beneficial to
  make sure that even the quiet voices are heard. But it’s the
  scribe’s responsibility to bring them into good shape, and it’s your
  responsibility as the team lead to make sure they’re truthful and
  accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spend the first 15-20 minutes of the weekly meeting on non-work
  topics. Ask something like “how was your weekend” or “how are things
  going in your part of the world” or anything else that you can think
  of that helps you feel the mood of your team. These things don’t go
  on the meeting record. Always accept when people don’t want to give
  an answer. They may have many reasons, none of which are necessarily
  your business. Trust that they’ll share whatever they’re comfortable
  sharing, even if some weeks that’s nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to keep each other appraised of your relative progress and
  status via a simple, central coordination facility, such as a
  virtual Kanban board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to &lt;a href="https://2018.pycon-au.org/talks/41002-writing-to-be-understood/"&gt;write to be
  understood&lt;/a&gt;,
  and encourage your team to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not attempt to get back to people “immediately”, and do not
  expect people to get back to you promptly. A reasonable default
  expectation for reply times is 24 hours. If you need an answer
  faster, you can always send an email (or better still, a comment on
  a card or ticket) with a request like “if I could get this by 1600
  UTC today, that’d be excellent.” Bonus points if you add &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you
  need that information quickly, as in “… so I can put this together
  with Kim’s performance data and make a decision on which load
  balancing strategy we’ll use, which Alex needs to know by tomorrow.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Establish a convention for marking things as urgent, when
  needed. The word &lt;em&gt;URGENT&lt;/em&gt;, included in capital letters in an email
  subject or a chat message, usually works well. &lt;em&gt;Only&lt;/em&gt; use this if
  things are on fire.&lt;sup id="fnref:not-urgent-by-default"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:not-urgent-by-default"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Never&lt;/em&gt; use the urgency
  marker just by itself. (That’s a &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/No_naked_pings"&gt;naked
  ping&lt;/a&gt; on steroids.)
  Also, when someone legitimately uses the marker in communication
  with &lt;em&gt;you,&lt;/em&gt; honour it. When someone uses it for something other than
  a legitimate reason, take them to task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get used to referring back to written communication, such as ticket
  comments or the record of a meeting, weeks or months later. This is
  not “pulling out the receipts” or “quoting chapter and verse” at
  someone. It simply serves to establish that yes, we have a written
  record of just about everything, and there is no need to keep these
  things stored in our heads under a banner saying “must not forget”
  (the latter being a major contributor to personal stress).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t attempt to hide your own mistakes and misjudgements. They’re
  on the record. That makes them a learning opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually establish firm communication rules with your team. Many of
  these won’t need to be autocratically decreed, because they just
  make sense and people tend to intuitively agree on them (like the
  just-mentioned &lt;em&gt;URGENT&lt;/em&gt; marker and the circumstances under which to
  use them). Then, make sure you &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/16/rules-are-rules/"&gt;stick to
  them&lt;/a&gt;. Stick to them yourself, and
  correct others who break them.&lt;sup id="fnref:asshole-filter"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:asshole-filter"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, &lt;em&gt;let your team know&lt;/em&gt; that you’re working on getting them
&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; out of meeting hell. Don’t sugarcoat things if you’re struggling
while swimming against the company tide, at least temporarily. If they
know you’re actively striving to make their work situation better, more
productive &lt;em&gt;and healthier&lt;/em&gt; it may well make the difference between
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/01/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-employees/"&gt;them leaving&lt;/a&gt; and
staying on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, keep an eye on corporate policy and the messages you get from
company leadership. If they’re obviously stuck in 1995, you might as
well go and update your CV. If the people at the top do &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/03/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-executives/"&gt;make an
effort to implement distributed and async friendly
policies&lt;/a&gt;,
however, then things may not change overnight, but there’s hope that
change they will, and your effort will not be for naught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:non-disparagement"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way: if your non-disparagement clause is
so harsh that you can’t talk about &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; negative in the
company, then that’s probably an awful company to begin with. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:non-disparagement" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:not-urgent-by-default"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the convention of the &lt;em&gt;URGENT&lt;/em&gt;
marker also establishes the convention that things are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
urgent by default. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:not-urgent-by-default" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:asshole-filter"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to enforce sensible collaboration rules may
  result in the inadvertent creation of an &lt;a href="https://siderea.livejournal.com/1230660.html"&gt;asshole
  filter&lt;/a&gt;. “Oh but I
  can’t enforce that rule on Bob, because Bob thinks rules aren’t for
  him but he’s brilliant!” — No. &lt;a href="https://www.brendangregg.com/blog/2017-11-13/brilliant-jerks.html"&gt;Don’t tolerate brilliant
  jerks&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:asshole-filter" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting out of Meeting Hell: As a regular employee</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/01/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-employees/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-10-01:/blog/2021/10/01/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-employees/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short series on transitioning to distributed work and asynchronous collaboration. This article is on what you can do if you are stuck in meeting hell as a regular employee who isn&amp;rsquo;t in a management role.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please have a look at the
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/"&gt;introduction&lt;/a&gt; for
background, for applicable disclaimers, and for information about
the specific environments this series talks about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you’re a regular employee (sometimes called an &lt;em&gt;Individual
Contributor&lt;/em&gt; or IC), who doesn’t have a team that reports to you. And
you are in an organization that, although it does have remote
employees or may even have switched to an all-distributed mode on
account of the pandemic, does not adopt basic rules of
distributed work and asynchronous communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You spend more time in meetings than is healthy, your productivity is
severely impacted, you’re stressed out from frequent interruptions,
you have trouble getting into a state of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)"&gt;flow&lt;/a&gt;. You may be
asked to keep your camera on for hours at a time, and you feel that
this badly encroaches on your privacy or sense of personal space. Your
manager or your peers like to
&lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/No_naked_pings"&gt;naked-ping&lt;/a&gt; you or
send you “hey, I need you for a minute” one-liners that &lt;a href="https://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/"&gt;disrupt your
train of
thought&lt;/a&gt;
for half an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And your organization (including your peers and direct manager)
tolerate or condone this kind of collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds like your typical day, I have great news for you. You
have at hand an excellent opportunity to improve your personal
situation, be more productive, and communicate better with your peers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Leave.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hand in your notice. Quit. Hightail it outta there. If &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you want to truly improve your personal situation and work
  effectively in a distributed team, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;neither your direct manager nor the top leadership of the
  organization takes any interest in optimizing for distributed and
  asynchronous collaboration,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then the way to do that &lt;em&gt;for yourself&lt;/em&gt; is to leave your current
organisation behind, and go elsewhere. There’s plenty of employment
opportunities for you to pick up in this industry at this time, and
there are a number of organizations that handle distributed work
better than the one you’re currently in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, you could consider trying to change the system from within. And
there is a small (I’d say minute, but nonzero) probability that you’ll
be successful, and drive real change in your organization. However,
there is an inordinately &lt;em&gt;larger&lt;/em&gt; probability that you’ll burn out in
the process — and endangering your health is never a gamble that’s
worth taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may think that that’s a pessimistic view. I think the opposite is
true. You’re not “failing” to drive change in an organization that
resists it, instead you can succeed at pushing change in an
organization that embraces it. Throwing your energy into meaningful
change for the better is the definition of optimism, in my book. And
if the place for that is elsewhere from where you are now, seize that
opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, note that the foregoing is all predicated on the entire
company (including your direct manager) being &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt; with synchronous
work and people having their calendar jammed with back-to-back
meetings, with no apparent intent to change. If it’s just you that
wants change, or perhaps only you and people at your level in &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt;
teams that you can’t reasonably join forces with, I’d argue that you
just shouldn’t be risking your health. In contrast, if your
manager&lt;sup id="fnref:direct-manager"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:direct-manager"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a couple of your peers are on your side —
consider your manager may be in their own
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/02/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-managers/"&gt;learning&lt;/a&gt; phase
about distributed and async collaboration — then things are a lot less
clean cut, and maybe you’d want to stay on for the ride. Particularly
so if there’s an active, supportive push &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/10/03/getting-out-of-meeting-hell-executives/"&gt;from the
top&lt;/a&gt; of the
organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Even if&lt;/em&gt; your manager and some of your peers are on your side, I can
think of a few situations where you should still leave: like when your
company has an “always on camera” policy, or doesn’t allow people to
go audio-only on calls, or promotes &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoftteams/teams-analytics-and-reports/teams-reporting-reference"&gt;number crunching on employee
“engagement” in a meeting
app&lt;/a&gt;. Companies
doing that are, in my view, beyond salvation and will never be able to
attain the levels of trust required for a distributed organization to
function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: if you’re stuck in meeting hell with nobody on your side, as a
regular employee with no reports, your best way forward is probably
the way to the exit. If you’re stuck in meeting hell &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; but there’s
a gale blowing the company into async &amp;amp; distributed mode, and/or you
have a very thick-skinned manager that gets it, and will deflect and
absorb any pressure from meeting-addicted higher-ups, you may want to
hang on for the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:direct-manager"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d posit that the only manager that really matters
in this scenario is your &lt;em&gt;direct&lt;/em&gt; line manager. That person would
your make-or-break partner in any transformation of how your team
collaborates. If you and they don’t share views, then don’t expect
to be able to play four-dimensional chess by forming an alliance
with some &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; manager who you then expect to influence &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt;
manager so that &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; gets better at distributed and async
work. You don’t want to trade being stuck in meeting hell for
being in stuck in meeting hell &lt;em&gt;and corporate politics.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:direct-manager" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting out of Meeting Hell: What this is about</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-09-30:/blog/2021/09/30/getting-out-of-meeting-hell/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short series on transitioning to distributed work and asynchronous collaboration. This article is the introduction.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2020, I presented a talk at &lt;a href="https://www.froscon.de"&gt;FrOSCon&lt;/a&gt;
titled &lt;a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/froscon2020-2605-no_we_won_t_have_a_video_call_for_that"&gt;No, we won’t have a video call for that: Communications for
distributed
teams.&lt;/a&gt;
In early 2021 I put together a full-length writeup of that talk, and
&lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;published it
here&lt;/a&gt;. And for no
apparent reason that article then &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28636536"&gt;made it to the top of Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt; on one day in
September 2021,&lt;sup id="fnref:newsy"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:newsy"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and apparently &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/xahteiwi/status/1442371424543444994"&gt;resonated with quite a few
people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after that, I got a fair number of questions along the lines of
“okay, what you talk about is a spot-on description of how I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to
work, but how do I get there?” In other words, &lt;strong&gt;what can you do in
order to transition from a team that’s stuck in meeting hell, to one
that actually goes fully distributed and embraces asynchronous
communications?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; I use the shorthand &lt;em&gt;Meeting Hell&lt;/em&gt; for a situation in
which people are forced to be in unnecessary and unproductive video
meetings&lt;sup id="fnref:in-person-meeting"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:in-person-meeting"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for an unhealthy fraction of their work
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is admittedly a mere &lt;em&gt;symptom&lt;/em&gt; of not having adopted
asynchronous and distributed ways of working, but it’s such a
tell-tale sign thereof that it counts as a dead giveaway. Thus, I
think it’s okay to say “I’m stuck in meeting hell” when what someone
means is really “I work in an organization that’s failing badly at
distributed and asynchronous work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what I’m doing here is offer &lt;strong&gt;suggestions&lt;/strong&gt; for getting out of that. If&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you’re one of the people that has 25 meetings a week, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28652514"&gt;spend 60% of your work
  week&lt;/a&gt; in standups and
  planning and retro, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the only time you have for doing what you actually signed up for &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28653696"&gt;is
  in overtime&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and it’s grinding you down, and you want to work differently, then
this series might be for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal strategies: one size does not fit all&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it’s very important to &lt;strong&gt;differentiate personal strategies&lt;/strong&gt; for
getting to distributed &amp;amp; async, based on your position in the company
or organization. So, I’m going to look at it from three angles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your options if you are what some companies call an “Individual
   Contributor”, or IC. In other words, these are for you if you are a
   &lt;strong&gt;regular employee&lt;/strong&gt; (or contractor), and you’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; personally
   responsible for other people — in other words, you have no reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your options if you are at some level of &lt;strong&gt;management&lt;/strong&gt; that is
   &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; top organizational leadership. That is to say, you have
   people that report to you, but you also report to someone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your options if you’re a &lt;strong&gt;top-level executive&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning you’re a
   Chief Executive Officer or Managing Director or Executive Director
   or something of the sort. You have people that report to you, but
   you don’t directly report to anyone — even though you may be
   answerable to a Board of Directors or some other oversight body, of
   course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;These are my views, not self-evident truths&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m only going to talk about my industry (software-driven
technology) because that’s the only industry I feel remotely qualified
to talk about. Also, I have never worked in a company that had more
than 3,000 employees, and I feel most at home in small outfits under
50. I’m reasonably confident that what I talk about is somewhat useful
for companies from 3 to 3,000 people in the software industry. It
&lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be applicable elsewhere — larger companies, other industries —
but at any rate, I make no guarantees of any kind. Feel free to adopt
an entirely contrarian position. And, you should also know I am not a
scientist, so none of what I write is informed by rigorous empiricism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, are we cool with that? &lt;strong&gt;My opinion, my thoughts, my views — not
pronouncements of absolute truth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:newsy"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For context: it was at the top for like three hours on a
Saturday morning. So it might have landed there just because
enough people were simultaneously bored enough to give it a
read… &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:newsy" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:in-person-meeting"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meeting Hell might &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; apply to excessive
in-person meetings in a shared work space, such as an
office. However, I really don’t believe my industry will ever go
back to defaulting to office-based work, now that it has shown for
nearly two years that it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; function, in principle, in a
default-distributed mode. Thus, I am using the word “meeting” as
synonymous with “video meeting” in this series, and I wouldn’t be
surprised if this eventually became the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of this as
akin to the transition undergone by the word &lt;em&gt;call:&lt;/em&gt; before
the advent of the telephone, a &lt;em&gt;call&lt;/em&gt; was a visit you paid to
someone’s house. Then, if you metaphorically “visited” someone by
telephone, that was a &lt;em&gt;telephone call&lt;/em&gt;. Now a &lt;em&gt;call&lt;/em&gt; is always a
phone call, except when explicitly specified as a &lt;em&gt;house call.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:in-person-meeting" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category><category term="Communications"></category></entry><entry><title>No, We Won’t Have a Video Call for That: Reader Feedback</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that-reader-feedback/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-09-26:/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that-reader-feedback/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Communications in distributed teams: a write-up of my talk from FrOSCon 2020, Cloud Edition.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a short summary of selected reactions to &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;the original
article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Twitter, 2021-04-10&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Twitter, &lt;a href="https://musings.danlj.org/about/"&gt;Michael K Johnson&lt;/a&gt; made
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mcdanlj/status/1380661700664422406"&gt;an interesting
point&lt;/a&gt; in
response to this article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My way of thinking about DMs is a little different, or maybe we
 think differently about confidentiality. Work goes in public,
 meta-work is often about relationships, and I want my reports to be
 100% confident they can bring any question or concern to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So “encrypted email” is not the right metaphor or measuring stick in
my view. DMs are a tool for saying what you aren’t comfortable
saying “out loud”, but that shouldn’t be about the work
itself. Never “how do I do this?” But “advice pls about how to work
with fred?” — yes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I entirely agree with the sentiments behind this; I still maintain
that chat DMs are not necessarily a good approach for addressing this,
for reason that some chat systems give merely an illusion of
confidentiality. If both participants in a conversation use OTR
encryption over a protocol like IRC or XMPP, inadvertent disclosure to
a third party is highly unlikely. Slack DMs? &lt;a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/better/business/slack-updates-privacy-policy-employers-can-read-private-dms-without-ncna862811"&gt;I wouldn’t be so
sure&lt;/a&gt;. If
your report confides in you, you don’t want them to have to worry if
their message is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; just between you and them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hacker News, 2021-09-25&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 2021-09-25, &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28636536"&gt;a link to this
article&lt;/a&gt; ended up being
the top post on Hacker News for a few hours. You’re very welcome to
read through the 200-odd comments in that thread, but here I’d like to
respond to just a couple. I’m deliberately only picking out ones where I
feel like &lt;em&gt;clarification&lt;/em&gt; on my part is necessary; as far as
differences of opinion are concerned I’ll be happy to let those stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article also assumes every one is a native speaker who can write
quickly and clearly in a chat – in a lot of international projects
this is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28651678"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;code&gt;papaf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My native language is German, and neither at the time of presenting
the original talk nor at the time of writing this update did I work
with anyone who is a first-language English speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an objection to the author’s blanket disregard for “pings” in
chat - while the request could/should be worded a bit more clearly
than just “ping”, IMHO they’re a valid way of requesting if an
opportunity for synchronous communication is available in the (not
that rare!) cases where asynchronous communication would be
worthless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28652633"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;code&gt;PeterisP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My blanket disregard is for &lt;em&gt;naked&lt;/em&gt; pings, not for pings in general.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category><category term="Conference"></category><category term="Communications"></category><category term="Work"></category></entry><entry><title>Rules are rules</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2021/09/16/rules-are-rules/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2021-09-16:/blog/2021/09/16/rules-are-rules/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a reputation for being rigid when it comes to communication rules. Here&amp;rsquo;s why I am.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a reputation among my colleagues that I am very strict and
rigid about the communications rules I follow for myself, and for my
team. That reputation is entirely deserved, and I am indeed not
particularly flexible in my strong preference for asynchronous,
non-interruptive communication methods. I have discussed
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/CyzoF7mHEBo"&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;at
length&lt;/a&gt;, what
those are and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I have that strong preference. But I haven’t
really outlined why I very rarely allow myself, or others if I can
help it, to deviate from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Florian, the complaint usually goes, can’t you occasionally make
an exception? Sometimes there’s something you could easily do to
unblock someone else, if they could only quickly chat you up and ask
you to jump in. You’d be in and out of there in no time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Let’s use an analogy here.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you’re out of an indispensable food product, say milk or flour
or potatoes or eggs. So you make a quick run to the grocery store, and
because you don’t live in a country with proper cycling infrastructure
and the store is out of walking distance, you drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You arrive at the grocery store parking lot, and for some unfathomable
reason it’s chock full. Completely packed. Not a single spot
available. Except those two spots right near the store entrance that
are reserved for wheelchair users, which you are not. You don’t see a
single car around with a wheelchair plaque or decal. Not even one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now. When you look at the situation, the objectively simplest and most
practical solution is for you to park in a wheelchair spot. You know
exactly how long it takes you to buy a carton of eggs; you’d be in and
out of that place in two minutes. The chance that one car needing a
wheelchair spot arrives in exactly that time is minute, and even then
there would be another one available. The probability of &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;
wheelchair users arriving in their cars, simultaneously, in those two
minutes, is infinitesimal. There is an overwhelming probability that
you will vacate the spot again, without it ever being needed by one of
its intended users while you were occupying it. So, why not use it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that if it’s OK for &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to break the rule that that
spot is for wheelchair users only, &lt;em&gt;there is absolutely no reason why
it shouldn’t also be OK for everyone else.&lt;/em&gt; You’re not special, the
same rules apply to you as to everyone else — so if we were to decide
that this rule &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; apply to you this very minute, then it also
needn’t apply to anyone else under similar circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, promptly, we’re in a situation where everyone flouts the
rules, and an actual wheelchair user can no longer do their grocery
shopping. That’s why you, if you are not a wheelchair user, shouldn’t
park there, and nobody else that isn’t shouldn’t either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with interruptive communications — such as pinging someone in a
chat when you could send them an email just the same — it’s much the
same way: if you needlessly ping me and I acquiesce, drop the thing
I’m doing, and focus on your interruption instead, it would be unfair
of me to not do the same for somebody else. And I know if &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt;
does this to me, my work day is purely interrupt driven and that’s
awful. The same goes for tolerating interruptive communications
towards my team — or, worse, engaging in such interruptive
communications myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Are there exceptions to this rule?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah but of course. Let me take you back to the grocery store. Suppose
someone had a heart attack or other major health emergency that struck
them down right as they were exiting the store and walking back to
their car. Would anyone — including a wheelchair-using motorist that
arrived just at that moment to do their shopping — complain if the
ambulance parked across &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; wheelchair accessible spots, if that
was the only practical way to get closest to the patient? I hope
not. And caring for the patient and stabilising them for the trip to
the hospital would surely take longer than your two-minute egg
procurement dash that we discussed earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this has a parallel in interruptive communications in a (much
less dire) regular work situation: stuff is actually on fire? Or
there’s something that for some legitimate reason needs doing &lt;em&gt;right
now&lt;/em&gt; that only I or someone on my team can do, or is most comfortable
with? Ping me in chat, use the back channel, give me a ring on my
&lt;em&gt;phone&lt;/em&gt; for cryinoutloud, whatever it takes to get my
attention. Nobody will hold that against you, least of all me. And in
this case that’s a rule that I can &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; easily apply generally,
treating everyone around me fairly and equitably: when stuff is urgent
and seriously overrides the priority of what’s currently being worked
on, you get to interrupt me or, if necessary anyone on my
team. (Though I would prefer that you interrupt me specifically, and I
can decide whether we really need to mobilise another person.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just don’t abuse that. If you do, you’ll just condition people into
taking your sense of “urgent” with a big pinch of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit, 2021-09-21:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague &lt;a href="https://be.linkedin.com/in/evrardjp"&gt;Jean-Philippe Evrard&lt;/a&gt;
has suggested that I refer to another, much more elaborate article on
a similar subject: Siderea’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1209794.html"&gt;The Asshole
Filter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. I recommend you
give it a read if you’re inclined.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Communications"></category><category term="Work"></category></entry><entry><title>No, We Won’t Have a Video Call for That!</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2020-08-22:/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Communications in distributed teams: a write-up of my talk from FrOSCon 2020, Cloud Edition.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;FrOSCon 2020 was an online event due to the COVID-19 pandemic, and
gave me the opportunity to present an extended and heavily updated
version of my &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/devopsdays-tel-aviv-2019/"&gt;DevOpsDays 2019&lt;/a&gt; talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I normally make my talks available as a video, and a slide deck with
full speaker notes. In this case though, I consider it fitting to
write the whole thing out, so that you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; need to watch a full
length video in 45 minutes, but can read the whole thing in 15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll still find links to the recording and deck downpage, as usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, we won’t have a video call for that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communications for distributed teams&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FrOSCon 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Note --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This presentation is a talk presented at &lt;a href="https://www.froscon.de/"&gt;FrOSCon 2020
Cloud Edition&lt;/a&gt;. It is &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"&gt;CC-BY-SA
4.0&lt;/a&gt; licensed, see
&lt;a href="/LICENSE"&gt;the license&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome, dear FrOScon people — this is my talk on
communications in distributed teams. My name is Florian, this is the
second time I‘m speaking at FrOScon, and you probably want to know
what the hell qualifies me to talk about this specific issue. So:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why am I talking here?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why am I talking about &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or rather more precisely, why am &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; talking about that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I turned 40 last year, have been in IT for about 20 years now (19
full-time), and out of that I have worked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in 4 successive companies, all of which worked out of offices,
  for 11 years, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in a completely distributed company, that I founded, for 6 years,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and now, for about three years, I have been running a distributed
  team that is a business unit of a company that has existed for 15
  years and throughout that time, has only ever worked from a single
  office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think I might have seen and become aware of some of the rather
interesting challenges that come with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What changed since last time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I originally wrote and presented this talk for the first time in
December 2019. At the time, you probably had forgotten about SARS, had
no idea what SARS-CoV2 or COVID-19 were, and many of you were probably
working from offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then something like three months later, everything changed and
suddenly, this talk became much more relevant to a much greater
audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And something else happened: a lot of people suddenly started talking
about working from home and distributed teams, and a lot of those
people who were talking very loudly, had themselves only been working
with or managing distributed teams since March. And a fair amount of
what you could about the subject then, and can still read now, is
complete and utter bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there’s one point I actually &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; make in the initial version
of this talk, because I thought it was self-evident. But I have come
to the conclusion that to a lot of people it is not, so to rectify
this omission from last December — and with apologies for that
omission to the wonderful DevOpsDays Tel Aviv crowd, who were my first
audience for this talk, let me make this one thing very clear from the
outset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective distributed collaboration is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; pretending to be in
an office while staring into a webcam all day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will never be able to capitalize on work as a distributed team
unless you kick some office habits. The key to distributed teams being
effective is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; that they happen to not be in the same place, as
you’ll see from the remainder of this talk. So to expect success from
the approach that you take the habits of an office, simply remove the
element of locality, replace every face to face meeting with a video
call and carry on, is ludicrous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that if you do it right, you’ll end up with a far
better team than a local one would ever be, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; everyone has a
chance at far better work-life balance, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you don’t waste awful
amounts of time and energy and fossil fuels on your commute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What’s in this talk?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you’ll find a few general themes throughout this talk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What modes we have &lt;em&gt;available&lt;/em&gt; for communications in teams;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why distributed teams always collaborate &lt;em&gt;asynchronously,&lt;/em&gt; and what
  communication modes lend themselves to that particularly well;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why &lt;em&gt;written communication&lt;/em&gt; is so important in distributed teams;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And why &lt;em&gt;meetings&lt;/em&gt; (like video calls) are a mode of communication
  that effective distributed teams hardly ever need to use — except
  for very specific reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I do want to state one thing upfront:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;not science.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing of what I am talking about is steeped in any scientific
rigour. I present anecdotes, not evidence. I might be mistaking
correlation for causation, or the other way round. It’s solely based
on my personal experience, and the experience of others I have talked
to, watched, or read. Everything I say here is subject to debate and
rebuttal, or you can simply have a different opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s definitely &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now with all of that said, let me attempt to give a definition of a
distributed team, according to my understanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distributed team is a &lt;strong&gt;professional&lt;/strong&gt; group whose members do not
rely on proximity in order to &lt;strong&gt;routinely&lt;/strong&gt; collaborate
productively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is clearly not an ideal definition, not least because it
defines something by a negative, and an outside factor to boot: it
defines a distributed team by what it &lt;em&gt;does not need&lt;/em&gt; to exist to
function. But it’s the best definition I’ve been able to come up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there’s a couple of key words in here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professional.&lt;/strong&gt; I’m talking about teams that work towards a
  professional goal. This doesn’t necessarily mean that they all work
  in the same company. They could, for example, all work in different
  companies collaborating on a joint project, which is what frequently
  happens in open source software projects. But they’re not pursuing
  their hobby, they’re doing their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Routinely.&lt;/strong&gt; I’m talking about teams that &lt;em&gt;habitually&lt;/em&gt; work in a
  distributed fashion, not the work that goes on in an office-based
  team when one person is having a work-from-home day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand that that lack of proximity is not only
spatial, it is temporal as well, because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in a distributed team means &lt;strong&gt;working asynchronously.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your team is distributed, this is equivalent to saying that it
works in an asynchronous fashion, that is to say, that people will
work on things in parallel, and a capable distributed team will have
just as few synchronization points as absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is not just working in different timezones, but
also the fact that everyone will have their own daily routine, and/or
have their individual times when they are most productive. Which you
&lt;em&gt;will not attempt to synchronize.&lt;/em&gt; (Doing so would mean setting the
entire team up for failure.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this doesn’t come for free, nor does it fall in our lap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being productive in a distributed team is a skill
that most people must &lt;strong&gt;learn;&lt;/strong&gt; it is not innate to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are not born with the ability to work in a distributed
team. Humans function best in groups that collaborate in close
proximity to one another; it is only very recently that technology has
started to enable us to override that to an extent — giving us other
benefits like the ability to work from home, or the ability to hire
people residing anywhere, provided they have internet connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we now &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; work in teams despite being continental distances away
from each other but we do have to acquire the skills to do that. And
if we fail to do so, that has a rather grave disadvantage, which is
that…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nothing&lt;/strong&gt; has as dire an impact on productivity as &lt;strong&gt;poor
communications.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a truism that applies to both distributed and non-distributed
teams. Having bad communications will wreck any project, blow any
budget, fail any objective. Now note that the reverse is &lt;em&gt;not true:&lt;/em&gt;
having &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; communications does not guarantee success. But having
bad communications does guarantee failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is one thing to start with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A capable distributed team &lt;strong&gt;habitually externalises&lt;/strong&gt; information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information is generally far less useful when it is only stored in one
person’s head, as opposed to being accessible in a shared system that
everyone trusts and can use. If you take important information out of
your own head and store it in a medium that allows others to easily
find and contextualise it, that’s a win for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since we’re all technology people, we typically have multiple
facilities to externalise, share, and then access information at our
disposal. So let’s see how those compare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Modes of communication in distributed teams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distributed team will habitually use multiple modes of
communication, relying mostly on those that make sharing, finding, and
contextualising information easy, and avoiding those that make it
difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many teams, distributed or not, using chat as a default mode of
communication is becoming the norm. Now with an important exception,
which I’ll get to near the end of the talk, this is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a symptom
of having a particularly dynamic or efficient team; it’s the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excessively using chat isn’t being efficient.
It’s being lazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a symptom of the worst kind of laziness &lt;em&gt;(not malice!)&lt;/em&gt;: in an
attempt to communicate quickly and easily, for yourself, you are really
making things harder for everyone, including yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table-striped table"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Share&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Find&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Contextualise&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙁&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because, while &lt;em&gt;sharing&lt;/em&gt; information in a chat is extremely
easy, it is also a “fire and forget” mode of communications. Chat
makes it difficult to find information after the fact. If you’ve ever
attempted to scour a busy Slack or IRC archive for a discussion on a
specific topic that you only remember to have happened a “few months
ago”, you’ll agree with me here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; difficult to read a Slack discussion in context, that
is to say in relation to &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; discussions on the same topic, days
or weeks earlier or later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s compare that to other communication modes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table-striped table"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Share&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Find&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Contextualise&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙁&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Email&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email makes it easy to share information with a person or a group
  from the get-go, but quite difficult to loop people into an ongoing
  discussion after the fact. Finding information later is just as hard
  as with chat, and it’s marginally better at contextualizing
  information than chat (because you get proper threading).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table class="table-striped table"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Share&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Find&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Contextualise&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙁&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Email&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wiki&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Issue tracker&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A wiki and an issue tracker (provided you don’t lock them down with
  silly view permissions), in contrast, both make it &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; easy to
  share, find, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; contextualise information.&lt;br/&gt;
  Note that “wiki”, in this context, is shorthand for any facility
  that allows you to collaboratively edit long-form documents
  online. That can be an actual wiki like a MediaWiki, but also
  something like Confluence, or even shared Google Docs.&lt;br/&gt;
  Likewise, “issue tracker” can mean RT, OTRS, Jira, Taiga, Bugzilla,
  whatever works for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table class="table-striped table"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Share&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Find&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Contextualise&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙁&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Email&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wiki&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Issue tracker&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙂&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Video call&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;😐&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;🙁&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;🙁&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video calls are even worse than chat or email, because sharing
  information works but doesn’t scale — you can’t reasonably have more
  than 5-or-so people in a video call, and sharing the recording of a
  full video call is just pointless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So really, make your wiki and your issue tracker your default mode of
communications, and use the others sparingly. (This isn’t meant to be
a euphemism for “don’t use them”, as we’ll get to in a moment.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Text chat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. Let’s talk about text chat. These days, that frequently means
&lt;a href="https://slack.com/"&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, but what I am talking about also and
equally applies to
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat"&gt;IRC&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://mattermost.com/"&gt;Mattermost&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://riot.im/"&gt;Riot&lt;/a&gt;, and 
anything similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is text chat universally useful? No. Is it universally bad? Not that,
either. There is a very specific type of situation in which text chat
is a good thing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;chat&lt;/strong&gt; for collaboration that requires &lt;strong&gt;immediate,
interactive mutual feedback.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using interactive chat is a good idea for the kind of communication
that requires immediate, interactive mutual feedback from two or more
participants. If that is not the case, chat is not a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that the only thing that chat is good for is communication
that is required to be &lt;em&gt;synchronous,&lt;/em&gt; and remember, in a distributed
team &lt;em&gt;asychronicity&lt;/em&gt; is the norm. So using interactive chat for
communications needs to be an &lt;em&gt;exceptional&lt;/em&gt; event for a distributed
team; if it is instead a regular occurrence you’ll make everyone on
the team miserable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any interaction that does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; require feedback that is &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt;
immediate and interactive, email, a wiki, or an issue tracker are &lt;em&gt;far
superior&lt;/em&gt; modes of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason to use &lt;strong&gt;DMs&lt;/strong&gt; for collaboration&lt;br/&gt;
is a need for immediate, interactive mutual feedback&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;and confidentiality.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using chat direct messages (DMs) as the &lt;em&gt;default&lt;/em&gt; means of
communication is utterly braindead. In order for a chat DM to be
useful, there is precisely one clearly delineated confluence of events
that must occur:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need immediate feedback from the other person,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you need mutual back-and-forth with the other person,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you don’t want others to follow the conversation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t emphasize enough that this combination is perfectly valid —
but it is &lt;em&gt;exceedingly rare.&lt;/em&gt; If you want just a private exchange of
ideas with someone, encrypted email will do. If you want to work on
something together with one person before you share it with others,
restricted view permissions on a wiki page or an issue tracker ticket
will work just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t need confidentiality but you do need interactive and
immediate feedback, chances are that you’re working on something
urgent, and it is far more likely you’ll eventually need to poll other
opinions, than that you won’t. So just use a shared channel from the
get-go, that way it’s easier for others to follow the conversation if
needed — and they might be able to point out an incorrect assumption
that one of you has, before you end up chasing a red herring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A chat ping is a shoulder tap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Pinging” someone in a chat (that is, mentioning their username, which
usually triggers a visual or auditory notification), is exactly like
walking up to a person, interrupting what they are doing, tapping them
on the shoulder, and asking them a question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No matter whether it is your intention or not,&lt;/strong&gt; they will feel
compelled to answer, relatively promptly (the only exception is when
you’ve done this so often that you have conditioned your colleagues
to ignore you — congratulations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you’ve broken their train of thought, yanked them out
of a potentially complex task, forced them to redo what they did
pre-interruption, or actually have them commit a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So pinging someone in a chat is something you should only do if you
are aware of exactly this risk, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you are convinced that whatever
you’re pinging about is more important. Otherwise, to be very blunt,
you’ll be seen as the asshole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want people to hate you? Send naked pings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A “naked ping” is the action of sending someone a message consisting
only of their username and a marker like “ping”, “hi”, “hey” or
similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;00&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;02&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Z&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;johndoe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;florian&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ping&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;[...]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;56&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Z&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;florian&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;johndoe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;I&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;hate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t. Just don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any person who is versed in the use of chat communications will, when
subjected to this behavior, be inclined to flay you alive. Infinitely
more so if it’s a DM. &lt;strong&gt;Do not do this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, always provide context. Always always always. Don’t say “can
I ask you a question, instead, &lt;em&gt;ask the question.&lt;/em&gt; If something isn’t
urgent, say something like “no urgency.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;00&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;02&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Z&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;johndoe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;florian&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;can&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;I&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;your&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;eyes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1422&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;[...]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;56&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Z&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;florian&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;johndoe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;                   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;was&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;afk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;–&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sick&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;kiddo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;56&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;58&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Z&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;johndoe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;florian&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be self-evident why this is better than naked pings, but if
to you it is not, then please read &lt;a href="https://blogs.gnome.org/markmc/2014/02/20/naked-pings/"&gt;Naked
Pings&lt;/a&gt;,
courtesy of Adam Jackson and Mark McLoughlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Video calls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Zoom, Hangouts, BlueJeans etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I’d like to talk about video calls. Doesn’t matter what
technology you’re using. Could be Zoom, Google Hangouts, BlueJeans,
Jitsi, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’d like to address this specifically, given the fact that in the
current pandemic the use of video calls appears to have skyrocketed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a very good reason to use video calls: they give you the
ability to pick up on nontextual and nonverbal cues from the call
participants. But that’s really the only good reason to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video calls have a significant drawback: until we get reliable
automatic speech recognition and transcription, they are only
half-on-the-record. Hardly anyone goes to the trouble of preparing a
full transcript of a meeting, and if anything, we get perhaps a
summary of points discussed and action items agreed to. So even if we
keep recordings of every video call we attend, it’s practically
impossible to discern, after the fact, what was discussed in a meeting
&lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; decisions were made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also practically impossible to &lt;em&gt;find&lt;/em&gt; a discussion point that
you only have a vague recollection of when it was discussed in a video
call, whereas doing so has a much greater probability of success if
a discussion took place on any archived text-based medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every video call needs an agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, true for any meeting, not just those conducted by
video call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A conversation without an agenda is useless. You want people to know
what to expect of the call. You also want to give people the option to
prepare for the call, such as doing some research or pulling together
some documentation. If you fail to circulate those &lt;em&gt;ahead of time,&lt;/em&gt; I
can guarantee that the call will be ineffective, and will likely
result in a repeat performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until machines get intelligent enough to automatically transcribe
and summarise words spoken in a meeting, &lt;strong&gt;write notes and a summary
of every meeting you attend,&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;circulate them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as important as an agenda to set the &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt; of the meeting, is
a set of notes that describes its &lt;em&gt;outcome&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective distributed teams understand that the &lt;em&gt;record&lt;/em&gt; of a call is
what counts, not the call itself. It is not the spoken word that
matters, but the written one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that follows this consequence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be useful, the write-up of a call &lt;strong&gt;takes more time and effort&lt;/strong&gt;
than the call itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think that video calls are any less work than chat meetings or
a shared document that’s being edited together or dicussed in
comments, think again. The only way a video call is less work, is when
everyone’s lazy and the call is, therefore, useless. Every meeting
needs notes and a summary, and you need to circulate these notes not
only with everyone who attended the meeting, but with everyone who has
a need-to-know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the standard outline I use for meeting notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meeting title&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date, time, attendees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discussion points (tabular)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action items&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting an executive summary at the very top is extraordinarily
helpful so people can decide if they&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should familiarise themselves with what was discussed, immediately,
  and possibly respond if they have objections, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only want to be aware of what was decided, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;just keep in the back of their head that a meeting happened, that
  notes exist, and where they can find them when they need to refer
  back to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you do meetings right, you no longer need most of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is that once you adhere to this standard — and I
repeat, having a full and detailed record is &lt;em&gt;the only acceptable
standard&lt;/em&gt; for video meetings – you’ll note that you can actually skip
the meeting altogether, use &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; a collaboratively edited document
&lt;em&gt;instead&lt;/em&gt; of your meeting notes, and remove your unnecessary
synchronization point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Video calls for recurring team meetings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one thing that I do believe video calls are good for, and
that is to use them for &lt;em&gt;recurring&lt;/em&gt; meetings as as an
opportunity to feel the pulse of your team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, a distributed team has &lt;em&gt;few&lt;/em&gt; recurring meetings, because
they are synchronization points, and we’ve already discussed that we
strive to minimize those. So the idea of having daily standups, sprint
planning meetings, and sprint retrospectives is fundamentally
incompatible with distributed teams. &lt;em&gt;Aside: in my humble opinion,
this is also why using Scrum is a terrible idea in distributed teams —
not to mention &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/f-ULT_Ic4qk"&gt;that it’s a terrible idea,
period.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, having perhaps one meeting per week (or maybe even one every
two weeks) in a video call is useful &lt;em&gt;precisely for the aforementioned
reasons&lt;/em&gt; of being able to pick up on nonverbal clues like body
language, posture, facial expressions, and tone. If people are
stressed out or unhappy, it’ll show. If they are relaxed and
productive, that will show too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that these meetings, which of course do follow the same rules
about agenda and notes, are not strictly &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to get the work
done. The team I run has one one-hour meeting a week, but whenever
that meeting conflicts with anything we skip it and divide up our
work via just the circulated coordination notes, and that works
too. The meeting really serves the purpose of syncing emotionally, and
picking up on nonverbal communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Briefing people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you need to thoroughly &lt;strong&gt;brief a group of people on an
important matter,&lt;/strong&gt; consider using a &lt;strong&gt;5-paragraph format.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Command and Signal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a format as it is being used by many armed forces; in NATO
parlance it’s called the 5-paragraph field order. Now I’m generally
not a fan of applying military thinking to civilian life — after all
we shouldn’t forget that the military is an institution that kills
people and breaks things, and I say that as a commissioned officer in
my own country’s army —, but in this case it’s actually something that
can very much be applied to professional communications, with some
rather minor modifications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Objective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s break these down in a little detail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Situation is about what position we’re in, and &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; we set out
   to do what we want to do. You can break this down into three
   sub-points, like the customer’s situation, the situation of your
   own company, any extra help that is available, and the current
   market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Objective is &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; we want to achieve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan is &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; we want to achieve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistics is about what budget and resources are available, and how
   they are used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communications is about how you’ll be coordinating among yourselves
   and with others in order to achieve your goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that people &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; have questions on what they’ve just been
briefed about. They just might not think of them straight away. Give
people time to think through what you’ve just briefed them on, and
they will think of good questions. So always have a follow-up round at
a later time (2 hours later, the following day, whatever), for which
you &lt;em&gt;encourage&lt;/em&gt; your group to come back with questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, use that same follow-up for checking how your briefing came
across, by gently quizzing people with questions like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“by what date do we want to implement X?”, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Joe, what things will you need to coordinate with Jane on?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives you valuable feedback on the quality of your briefing: if
your team can’t answer these questions, chances are that you weren’t
as clear as you should have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pinching the firehose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to say a few words about what I like to call pinching
the figurative firehose you might otherwise be forced to drink from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of incoming information in a distributed team can be
daunting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you work in a distributed team, since everyone is on their own
schedule and everything is asynchronous, you may be dealing with a
constant incoming stream of information — from your colleagues, your
reports, your manager, your customers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no way to change this, so what you need to do is apply your
own structure to that stream. What follows is not &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; way to do
that, but &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; way, and you may find another works better for
you. But you will need to define and apply &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; structure, otherwise
you’ll feel constantly overwhelmed and run the risk of burning out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider using the &lt;strong&gt;“4-D” approach&lt;/strong&gt; when dealing with incoming
information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Hat tip to David Allen)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a defined approach for doing this, which I learned about from
reading &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Allen_(author)"&gt;David
Allen&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1633.Getting_Things_Done"&gt;Getting
Things
Done&lt;/a&gt;. I
don’t know if Allen invented the 4-D approach or whether someone came
up with it before him, but that’s how I know about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his book, David Allen suggests to apply one of the following four
actions to any incoming bit of information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drop&lt;/strong&gt; means read, understand, and then archive. It’s what you use
  for anything that doesn’t require any action on your part.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delegate&lt;/strong&gt; is for things that do require action, but not from
  you. Make sure that it gets to the right person and is understood by
  &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;, and make a note for follow-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defer&lt;/strong&gt; means it needs doing, and it’s you who needs to do it, but
  it doesn’t need doing &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt;. Enter it into your task list
  (to use a very generic term, more on this in a bit), and clear it
  from your inbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do&lt;/strong&gt; are the (typically very few) things that remain that need to
  be done &lt;em&gt;by you, and immediately.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this approach does not mean that you’ll never be overwhelmed
by the amount of information that you need to process. But it’ll
greatly reduce that risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;“Drop” rules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Dropping” things doesn’t mean ignoring them. You still have to read
and understand what’s in them, and be able to find them later. So:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never delete things (except spam).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only archive them in a way that that keeps them retrievable in the
  future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there something isn’t understandable to you, think it through and
  look for clarification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;“Delegate” rules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delegation obviously requires that there is a person you can delegate
to. This is &lt;em&gt;not necessarily&lt;/em&gt; someone who reports to you; indeed, it
might be someone &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; report to. (You might be asked to deal with
something that you have no control over, but your manager does.) So:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the right person that can get the task done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preemptively send them &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the information that you think they
  might need (and that you have access to), rather than relying on
  them to ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask them to acknowledge that they have received what they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a note to follow up to see if they need anything else, and
  follow through by seeing the task to completion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within your own team, &lt;strong&gt;you only ever delegate tasks, not
responsibility.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasks without follow-up and follow-through are a waste of people’s
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not delegate, or even define, tasks that you are not prepared to
follow through on. If you handwave “everyone use encrypted email from
now on,” and you’re not even prepared to make that work for your own
email account, you might as well just leave it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you do proclaim an objective or rule and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; you find yourself
unable to see it through — &lt;em&gt;this happens,&lt;/em&gt; and is no sign of
ineptitude or failure — then loudly and clearly rescind it. It’s far
better for you to visibly backtrack, than to be perceived as someone
whose pronouncements are safe to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;“Defer” rules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deferring simply means that because something you need to do doesn’t
need doing &lt;em&gt;immediately,&lt;/em&gt; you can do it at a time that suits your
schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you’ll need to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;add the task immediately to some sort of queue (for email, this can
  be a folder named “Needs Reply”),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;make sure to go through that queue at a later time to prioritize
  (ideally, right after you’re done with your “Do” tasks, which we’ll
  get to in a second),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;absolutely ensure that you make time to go back and actually do your
  prioritized tasks, at a time you consider convenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;“Do” rules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, there’ll be your “Do” tasks — stuff that &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; need to
do, and do immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell people that you’re doing them, because you’ll want to be
  uninterrupted. Update your chat status, put some blocked time in
  your calendar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you’ll be uninterrupted. For email, turn off all your
  notifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plow through all the undropped, undelegated,
  undeferred items in your inbox until it’s empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But what about the watercooler?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entirety of this talk, up to this point, has focused on
professional communications. And among people unfamiliar or
unexperienced with work in a distributed team, it is often accepted
that teams can communicate well “professionally.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, they frequently ask, “what about watercooler chats? What about
the many informal discussions that happen at work while people are
getting some water or coffee, or sit together over lunch? There’s
always so much communication happening at work that’s informal, but is
extremely beneficial to everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Office workers often don’t habitually externalise information. A
distributed team that tries that won’t last a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, many companies where information exchange hinges on coffee or
cafeteria talk simply don’t give a damn about externalising
information. Sure, if 90% of your company’s knowledge is only in
people’s heads, you’re dead without the lunchroom. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if the same thing happens in a distributed team, it never gets off
the ground. So, if you have a team that’s functional and productive,
&lt;em&gt;because it habitually externalises information,&lt;/em&gt; the absence of
chit-chat over coffee has zero negative impact on information flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, you may also be interested in the completely non-work-related
talk that happens over coffee, that simply contributes to people’s
relaxation and well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People working in distributed teams are often introverts. Or they
simply choose to have their social relationships outside of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this might shock some people, but there are plenty of people
who can make a terrific contribution to your company, but who dislike
the “social” aspect of work. They might thrive when being left
alone, with as little small-talk as possible, and ample opportunity to
socialize with their friends and family, away from work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you do have people on your team that enjoy having an entirely
informal conversation every once in a while, there totally is room for
that even in a distributed team. All you need to do is agree on a
signal that means “I’m taking a break and I’d be happy to chat with
anyone who’s inclined, preferably about non work related things” (or
whatever meaning your group agrees on). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a keyword on IRC,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a message to a specific channel, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(if you want to get fancy) a bot that updates your group calendar
  when it receives a message with a particular format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a word of caution, I’ve actually done this with my team
before, and it didn’t catch on — for the simple reason that we almost
never took breaks that happened to overlap. But that doesn’t rule out
that it works on &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; team, and also there’s always the remote
possibility that two or more people on your team might like to
schedule their breaks concurrently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you can &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; do, of course, is have a channel in which you can
discuss completely random things that are not work related. And if the
rule is that confidential or company-proprietary discussion topics are
off-limits there, the channel might as well be public. It might even
be Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The antithesis: ChatOps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do want to mention one other thing for balance. There is a complete
alternative framework for distributed teams working together, and it’s
what people refer to as ChatOps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the best of my knowledge, the first company to run ChatOps on a
large scale &lt;em&gt;and talk about it publicly&lt;/em&gt; was GitHub, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/NST3u-GjjFw"&gt;back in
2013&lt;/a&gt; in a
&lt;a href="https://www.rubyfuza.org/"&gt;RubyFuza&lt;/a&gt; talk by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jnewland"&gt;Jesse
Newland&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a distributed team operates on a ChatOps basis, the interactive
text chat is where absolutely everything happens. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone lives in chat all the time, and all issues, alerts and events are
  piped into the chat.&lt;br/&gt;
  Everything is discussed in the chat, and everything is also
  &lt;em&gt;resolved&lt;/em&gt; in the chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a system relies on heavy use of chat bots. For example, if an
  alert lands in the channel, and the discussion then yields that the
  proper fix to the problem is to run a specific Ansible playbook,
  you send an in-chat bot command that kicks off that playbook, and
  then reports its result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is of course very laudable, because it resolves a major issue
with using chat, which is the classic scenario of something being
discussed in a chat, someone else then going away for a bit and then
coming back saying “I fixed it!”, and nobody else actually
understanding what the problem was. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make everything explicit and in-band, in becomes easy, in
principle, to go back to a previously-solved problem that reappears,
and replay the resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When does ChatOps make sense? Here’s a hint: It’s called Chat&lt;strong&gt;Ops&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So can this make sense? Yes, absolutely. Under what circumstances
though? I maintain that this is best suited for when your work tends
to be inherently linear with respect to some dimension. For example,
if your primary job is to keep a system operational versus the linear
passage of &lt;em&gt;time,&lt;/em&gt; ChatOps is an excellent approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And keeping complex systems operational over time is the definition
of, you guessed it, ops. So ChatOps may be a very suitable
communication mode for operations, but it’s highly unlikely to be
efficient as a generic mode of communication across distributed teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even then I posit it’s difficult to get right, since you’ll have
to curb channel sprawl and threading and other things, but’s that’s a
whole ‘nother talk and indeed a talk for another &lt;em&gt;speaker,&lt;/em&gt; because I
don’t lead an ops team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To summarize…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to summarize, here are my key points from this talk, in a nutshell
— please make these your key takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distributed teams are better than localized teams — not because
  they’re distributed, but because they’re asynchronous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid anything that makes a distributed team run synchronously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use less chat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fewer meetings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write. Things. Down.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category><category term="Conference"></category><category term="Communications"></category><category term="Work"></category></entry><entry><title>No, We Won’t Have a Video Call for That: Slides and Recordings</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that-slides-and-recordings/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2020-08-22:/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that-slides-and-recordings/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are the slides and recordings of the original talk that
ultimately became &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk recording is available from two different sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video and audio in multiple formats, for viewing and download: &lt;a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/froscon2020-2605-no_we_won_t_have_a_video_call_for_that"&gt;CCC
  Media
  server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Streaming: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/NVnci3tyDa4"&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, as always, you can also review my slides, with all …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are the slides and recordings of the original talk that
ultimately became &lt;a href="https://xahteiwi.eu/resources/presentations/no-we-wont-have-a-video-call-for-that/"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk recording is available from two different sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video and audio in multiple formats, for viewing and download: &lt;a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/froscon2020-2605-no_we_won_t_have_a_video_call_for_that"&gt;CCC
  Media
  server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Streaming: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/NVnci3tyDa4"&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, as always, you can also review my slides, with all my speaker notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rendered slides: &lt;a href="https://fghaas.github.io/froscon2020/"&gt;GitHub
  Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slide sources (CC-BY-SA): &lt;a href="https://github.com/fghaas/froscon2020"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category><category term="Conference"></category><category term="Communications"></category><category term="Work"></category></entry><entry><title>Paying People</title><link href="https://xahteiwi.eu/blog/2020/02/04/paying-people/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Florian Haas</name></author><id>tag:xahteiwi.eu,2020-02-04:/blog/2020/02/04/paying-people/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Paying people equally is straightforward, right? We all agree on that, and then once we’re talking about people living in different countries, we all disagree on what “equal” really means.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my now almost 10ish years of first running my own company, and then
managing a team in the company I sold my company to, I have very
frequently struggled with what’s a “fair” way of paying people. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve come to the conclusion that when it comes to hiring distributed,
and thus hiring people living in different countries, there is no such
thing. At least not one that everyone agrees on to be fair. The best
thing we can hope for is an approximation of fairness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How much do you earn?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I ask you how much you make, you’ll either&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be very offended at the invasion of your privacy, and refuse to
  answer, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give me an answer straight away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which it is, is likely going to be determined by your culture and your
upbringing. I am Austrian, I have interacted a lot with Americans, and
now I work with Swedes — I can tell you, there are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different
views on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether or not you choose to answer, you’ll likely have a number in
your head. And again, there are multiple ways you’ll think of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could be your annual salary, before income tax.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could be your monthly salary, before income tax and public
  healthcare and pension payments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could be really weird, as in Austria: you’d think of your
  “monthly” salary, but in reality that’s 1/14th rather than 1/12th of
  your annual salary, because you’re paid a double salary in June and
  November.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But whichever it is, you’d probably think of a number, in your home
currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Equal work, equal pay. Right?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope we generally agree that two people who do the same (or
equivalent) work should be paid the same. And as long as you’re
comparing two people, living in the same place, whose salary is paid
out in the same currency, that’s easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what about people from different countries? We can even assume
that those two countries use the same currency, to facilitate the
discussion. (Talking about &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; currencies makes things even
more murky, and is perhaps a topic for another article.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s the actual “worth” of the money you make?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no correct answer for this. There are two possible approaches,
both of which are “wrong” in a way and “right” in another. Let’s say
we’re talking about two people being paid 3,000 euros a month, one
living in Finland, one in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could say that a euro is a euro. Thus, if you’ve got € 3,000 in
  your hand in Finland, that’s the same as having € 3,000 in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you could look at the question, what does that euro buy? If
  you’ve got € 3,000 in Finland, that will buy you things that, on
  average, you need to spend only about € 2,080 euros on in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So look at two people, one living in Finland and one in Greece. You
pay them both € 3,000 for the same work. Are you paying them equally,
or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you wouldn’t. If I had a person working for me in Finland, and
I paid that person € 3,000, and another person in Greece that also
made € 3,000 for the same work, I’d be massively short-changing the
person in Finland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can argue that € 3,000 is € 3,000 and that’s the end of the
story. I tend to think that economists are on my side — that’s why the
concept of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Purchasing_power_parity"&gt;purchasing power
parity&lt;/a&gt; (PPP)
exists —, but you can certainly be of the opposite opinion.&lt;sup id="fnref:inflation"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:inflation"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the problem that most PPP conversion rates are
per-country. And they may be way off if you compare, say, someone
living in Athens to someone living in
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%84teritsiputeritsipuolilautatsij%C3%A4nk%C3%A4"&gt;Äteritsiputeritsipuolilautatsijänkä&lt;/a&gt;,
to stick with the Greece and Finland example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact of the matter is, neither approach is perfect, and I can only
choose one approach or the other. And the approach that I’ve chosen,
in the distributed team that I run, is to make PPP adjustments. Others
opt for a different approach. Neither of these is right, or
wrong. They’re both an attempt to treat your people equally, and
neither is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:inflation"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will put forward one small thought though: if you are
convinced that the money you earn is just that number in your
currency (as in, € 3,000 is € 3,000), then I posit that you should
also stick to that opinion in the face of inflation. Under that
assumption, then € 3,000 next year is still the same € 3,000 it
was this year, regardless of whether inflation was maybe 5%. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:inflation" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="Work"></category></entry></feed>